<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cardiac Mitochondrial PTEN-L determines cell fate between apoptosis and survival 
during chronic alcohol consumption.

Chronic alcohol consumption induces myocardial damage and a type of non-ischemic 
cardiomyopathy termed alcoholic cardiomyopathy, where mitochondrial 
ultrastructural damages and suppressed fusion activity promote cardiomyocyte 
apoptosis. The aim of the present study is to determine the role of 
mitochondrial fission proteins and/or other proteins that localise on cardiac 
mitochondria for apoptosis upon ethanol consumption. In vivo and in vitro 
chronic alcohol exposure increased mitochondrial Drp1 levels but knockdown of 
the same did not confer cardioprotection in H9c2 cells. These cells displayed 
downregulated expression of MFN2 and OPA1 for Bak-mediated cytochrome c release 
and apoptosis. Dysregulated PTEN/AKT cell survival signal in both ethanol 
treated and Drp1 knockdown cells augmented oxidative stress by promoting  
mitochondrial PTEN-L and MFN1 interaction. Inhibiting this interaction with 
VO-OHpic, a reversible PTEN inhibitor, prevented Bak insertion into the 
mitochondria and release of cytochrome c to cytoplasm. Thus, our study provides 
evidence that Drp1-mediated mitochondrial fission is dispensable for 
ethanol-induced cardiotoxicity and that stress signals induce mitochondrial 
PTEN-L accumulation for structural and functional dyshomeostasis. Our in vivo 
results also demonstrates the therapeutic potential of VO-OHpic for habitual 
alcoholics developing myocardial dysfunction.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="897~911" text="Drp1 knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1037~1074" text="VO-OHpic, a reversible PTEN inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="549~556" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="561~569" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="694~704" text="H9c2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="712~717" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="912~917" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="814~823" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>