<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Effect of miR-27b-5p on apoptosis of human vascular endothelial cells induced by 
simulated microgravity.

Weightlessness-induced cardiovascular dysfunction can lead to physiological and 
pathological consequences. It has been shown that spaceflight or simulated 
microgravity can alter expression profiles of some microRNAs (miRNAs). Here, we 
attempt to identify the role of miRNAs in human umbilical vein endothelial cells 
(HUVECs) apoptosis under simulated microgravity. RNA-sequencing and quantitative 
real-time PCR (qRT-PCR) assays were used to identify differentially expressed 
miRNAs in HUVECs under simulated microgravity. Then we obtained the target genes 
of these miRNAs through target analysis software. Moreover, GO and KEGG 
enrichment analysis were performed. The effects of these miRNAs on HUVECs 
apoptosis were evaluated by flow cytometry, Western blot and Hoechst staining. 
Furthermore, we obtained the target gene of miR-27b-5p by luciferase assay, 
qRT-PCR and Western blot. Finally, we investigated the relationship between this 
target gene and miR-27b-5p in HUVECs apoptosis under normal gravity or simulated 
microgravity. We found 29 differentially expressed miRNAs in HUVECs under 
simulated microgravity. Of them, the expressions of 3 miRNAs were validated by 
qRT-PCR. We demonstrated that miR-27b-5p affected HUVECs apoptosis by inhibiting 
zinc fingers and homeoboxes 1 (ZHX1). Our results reported here demonstrate for 
the first time that simulated microgravity can alter the expression of some 
miRNAs in HUVECs and miR-27b-5p may protect HUVECs from apoptosis under 
simulated microgravity by targeting ZHX1.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1344~1350" text="HUVECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="387~435" text="human umbilical vein endothelial cells  (HUVECs)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="598~604" text="HUVECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="810~816" text="HUVECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1087~1093" text="HUVECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1200~1206" text="HUVECs" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1351~1360" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="436~445" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="818~827" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1094~1103" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1335~1343" text="affected" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>