<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A potent protective effect of baicalein on liver injury by regulating 
mitochondria-related apoptosis.

Liver injury is the early stage of liver disease, which is caused by multiple 
factors. Baicalein has shown extensive bioactivity. But whether baicalein has a 
protective effect on liver injury has not been reported thus far. In this study, 
we aim to investigate the protective effects of baicalein on liver injury 
induced by oxidative stress. H2O2 and CCl4 were employed to establish liver 
injury models in vivo and in vitro, respectively. The protective effect of 
baicalein on oxidative stress-induced liver injury was evaluated by detecting 
the mitochondrial dynamics, the level of autophagy and apoptosis, the 
histopathology of liver, the indicators of liver function, and the level of 
oxidative stress in vitro and in vivo. March5 is the key regulator during liver 
injury induced by oxidative stress. March5 can ubiquitinate Drp1 and promote 
Drp1 degradation, then maintain the homeostasis of mitochondrial dynamics, keep 
the balance of autophagy, and reduce apoptosis. Baicalein is able to effectively 
reduce liver injury; it can contribute to the expression of March5 by regulating 
KLF4 during liver injury. These results indicate that baicalein plays a key role 
in salvaging liver from injury induced by oxidative stress via regulating the 
KLF4-March5-Drp1 signal pathway.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="491~496" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="512~519" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="524~532" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="612~617" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="818~826" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="831~838" text="in vivo" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="875~880" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1130~1135" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1217~1222" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C9" spans="742~747" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C10" spans="767~772" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1056~1065" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1078~1087" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1071~1077" text="reduce" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>