<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Centchroman induces redox-dependent apoptosis and cell-cycle arrest in human 
endometrial cancer cells.

Centchroman (CC) or Ormeloxifene has been shown to induce apoptosis and cell 
cycle arrest in various types of cancer cells. This has, however, not been 
addressed for endometrial cancer cells where its (CC) mechanism of action 
remains unclear. This study focuses on the basis of antineoplasticity of CC by 
blocking the targets involved in the cell cycle, survival and apoptosis in 
endometrial cancer cells. Ishikawa Human Endometrial Cancer Cells were cultured 
under estrogen deprived medium, exposed to CC and analyzed for proliferation and 
apoptosis. Additionally, we also analyzed oxidative stress induced by CC. Cell 
viability studies confirmed the IC50 of CC in Ishikawa cells to be 20 µM after 
48 h treatment. CC arrests the cells in G0/G1 phase through cyclin D1 and cyclin 
E mediated pathways. Phosphatidylserine externalization, nuclear morphology 
changes, DNA fragmentation, PARP cleavage, and alteration of Bcl-2 family 
protein expression clearly suggest ongoing apoptosis in the CC treated cells. 
Activation of caspase 3 & 9, up-regulation of AIF and inhibition of apoptosis by 
z-VAD-fmk clearly explains the participation of the intrinsic pathway of 
programmed cell death. Further, the increase of ROS, loss of MMP, inhibition of 
antioxidant (MnSOD, Cu/Zn-SOD and GST) and inhibition of apoptosis with L-NAC 
suggests CC induced oxidative stress leading to apoptosis via mitochondria 
mediated pathway. Therefore, CC could be a potential therapeutic agent for the 
treatment of Endometrial Cancer adjunct to its utility as a contraceptive and an 
anti-breast cancer agent.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="516~555" text="Ishikawa Human Endometrial Cancer Cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="779~793" text="Ishikawa cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1118~1123" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="490~514" text="endometrial cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="832~864" text="arrests the cells in G0/G1 phase" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1090~1099" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1194~1203" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1293~1303" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1420~1429" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1490~1499" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1180~1190" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1406~1416" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1479~1489" text="leading to" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>