<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PP2Ac upregulates PI3K-Akt signaling and induces hepatocyte apoptosis in liver 
donor after brain death.

Multiple research groups have demonstrated that the outcome of patients 
receiving liver grafts from brain death donors (DBD) is poorer when compared 
with patients receiving grafts from living donors. This might be due to an 
increased hepatocyte apoptosis induced after brain death (BD). In this work, we 
found that the activity of PP2A-Akt pathway is significantly increased in 
clinical donor ex vivo hepatocytes after BD by iTRAQ protein quantification 
analysis. The same results were confirmed in animal models. A time-dependent 
promotion of apoptosis was also found in DBD rabbit liver, as demonstrated by 
the increased levels of cleaved Caspase 3 and the decreased of Bcl-2. To further 
investigate the roles of PP2A and Akt in regulating apoptosis of hepatocytes 
after BD, we cultivated human liver cell line L02 with serum deprivation and 
hypoxia, to simulate the ischemic and hypoxic conditions of hepatocytes in DBD. 
Increased apoptosis and decreased viability were observed during the time in 
this model. Meanwhile PP2A activity and Akt activity were respectively increased 
and decreased. Notably, the proportion of Akt phosphorylation at Ser473 
decreased, while other known targets of PP2A (p38, JNK and ERK) were not 
affected in terms of protein levels or phosphorylation. These results suggested 
that PP2A is involved in apoptotic induction of hepatocytes after brain death by 
specific suppression of Akt. This discovery was further confirmed with 
pharmaceutical and genetic methods. Our work implied potential targets for 
reducing liver cell apoptosis and improving organ donor quality after BD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="907~932" text="human liver cell line L02" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="689~701" text="rabbit liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1052~1061" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1042~1051" text="Increased" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>