<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SDF-1 induces TNF-mediated apoptosis in cardiac myocytes.

Chemokines are small secreted proteins with chemoattractant properties that play 
a key role in inflammation. One such chemokine, Stromal cell-derived factor-1 
(SDF-1) also known as CXCL12, and its receptor, CXCR4, are expressed and 
functional in cardiac myocytes. SDF-1 both stimulates and enhances the cellular 
signal which attracts potentially beneficial stem cells for tissue repair within 
the ischemic heart. Paradoxically however, this chemokine is known to act in 
concert with the inflammatory cytokines of the innate immune response which 
contributes to cellular injury through the recruitment of inflammatory cells 
during ischemia. In the present study, we have demonstrated that SDF-1 has dose 
dependent effects on freshly isolated cardiomyocytes. Using Tunnel and caspase 
3-activation assays, we have demonstrated that the treatment of isolated adult 
rat cardiac myocyte with SDF-1 at higher concentrations (pathological 
concentrations) induced apoptosis. Furthermore, ELISA data demonstrated that the 
treatment of isolated adult rat cardiac myocyte with SDF-1 at higher 
concentrations upregulated TNF-α protein expression which directly correlated 
with subsequent apoptosis. There was a significant reduction in SDF-1 mediated 
apoptosis when TNF-α expression was neutralized which suggests that SDF-1 
mediated apoptosis is TNF-α-dependent. The fact that certain stimuli are capable 
of driving cardiomyocytes into apoptosis indicates that these cells are 
susceptible to clinically relevant apoptotic triggers. Our findings suggest that 
the elevated SDF-1 levels seen in a variety of clinical conditions, including 
ischemic myocardial infarction, may either directly or indirectly contribute to 
cardiac cell death via a TNF-α mediated pathway. This highlights the importance 
of this receptor/ligand in regulating the cardiomyocyte response to stress 
conditions.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="931~950" text="rat cardiac myocyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1112~1131" text="rat cardiac myocyte" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1026~1035" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1249~1258" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1313~1322" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1397~1406" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1018~1025" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1169~1180" text="upregulated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1284~1293" text="reduction" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1388~1396" text="mediated" effect="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1303~1311" text="mediated" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>