<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The extracellular lactate-to-pyruvate ratio modulates the sensitivity to 
oxidative stress-induced apoptosis via the cytosolic NADH/NAD(+) redox state.

The advantages of the Warburg effect on tumor growth and progression are well 
recognized. However, the relevance of the Warburg effect for the inherent 
resistance to apoptosis of cancer cells has received much less attention. Here, 
we show here that the Warburg effect modulates the extracellular 
lactate-to-pyruvate ratio, which profoundly regulates the sensitivity towards 
apoptosis induced by oxidative stress in several cell lines. To induce oxidative 
stress, we used the rapid apoptosis inducer Raptinal. We observed that medium 
conditioned by HepG2 cells has a high lactate-to-pyruvate ratio and confers 
resistance to Raptinal-induced apoptosis. In addition, imposing a high 
extracellular lactate-to-pyruvate ratio in media reduces the cytosolic NADH/NAD+ 
redox state and protects against Raptinal-induced apoptosis. Conversely, a low 
extracellular lactate-to-pyruvate ratio oxidizes the cytosolic NADH/NAD+ redox 
state and sensitizes HepG2 cells to oxidative stress-induced apoptosis. 
Mechanistically, a high extracellular lactate-to-pyruvate ratio decreases the 
activation of JNK and Bax under oxidative stress, thereby inhibiting the 
intrinsic apoptotic pathway. Our observations demonstrate that the Warburg 
effect of cancer cells generates an anti-apoptotic extracellular environment by 
elevating the extracellular lactate-to-pyruvate ratio which desensitizes cancer 
cells towards apoptotic insults. Consequently, our study suggests that the 
Warburg effect can be targeted to reverse the lactate-to-pyruvate ratios in the 
tumor microenvironment and thereby re-sensitize cancer cells to oxidative 
stress-inducing therapies.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="709~720" text="HepG2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1106~1117" text="HepG2 cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="802~811" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1146~1155" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1321~1338" text="apoptotic pathway" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="975~984" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="941~949" text="protects" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="967~974" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1138~1145" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1295~1305" text="inhibiting" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>