<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Effects of annexin A7 inhibitor-ABO on the expression and distribution of long 
noncoding RNA-CERNA1 in vascular endothelial cells apoptosis.

More and more studies reported that diverse biological roles of long noncoding 
RNAs were usually dependent on their subcellular location. In our previous 
study, long noncoding RNA CERNA1 was identified both located in cytoplasm and 
nucleus of vascular endothelial cells (VECs). And CERNA1 in cytoplasm, which 
functioned as competitive endogenous RNA (ceRNA), alleviated the apoptosis of 
VECs. However, the function of CERNA1 in nucleus was still unclear. In this 
study, we found that nuclear CERNA1 positively regulated BCL2L10, which 
accelerated the serum and FGF-2 starvation-induced apoptosis of VECs, by 
enhancing the histone modification level of H3K9ac and H3K4me3 in BCL2L10 
promoter region. Furthermore, due to the paradoxical function, we investigated 
the variation of CERNA1 subcellular location in VECs. The results showed that, 
as the change of apoptosis status, CERNA1 altered the cellular distribution in 
VECs. And the annexin A7 inhibitor, ABO 
(6-amino-2,3-dihydro-3-hydroxymethyl-1,4-benzoxazine), not only increased the 
expression of CERNA1 by TIA-1, but also specifically improved its cytoplasm 
distribution proportion so as to inhibit the apoptosis of VECs. This evidence 
suggested that the subcellular location of CERNA1 played an important role in 
the VECs apoptosis and ABO might be a potential chemical molecule for therapy of 
VECs apoptosis related cardiovascular diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="389~422" text="vascular endothelial cells (VECs)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="535~539" text="VECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="749~753" text="VECs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1329~1333" text="VECs" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="521~530" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="736~745" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1316~1325" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="506~516" text="alleviated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="685~696" text="accelerated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="728~735" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1304~1311" text="inhibit" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>