<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Hemocompatible LAT1-inhibitor can induce apoptosis in cancer cells without 
affecting brain amino acid homeostasis.

Increased amounts of amino acids are essential for cancer cells to support their 
sustained growth and survival. Therefore, inhibitors of amino acid transporters, 
such as L-type amino acid transporter 1 (LAT1) have been developed. In this 
study, a previously reported LAT1-inhibitor (KMH-233) was studied for its 
hemocompatibility and toxicity towards human umbilical vein endothelial cells 
(HUVEC) and human aortic smooth muscle cells (AoSMCs). Furthermore, the 
cytotoxic effects against human breast adenocarcinoma cells (MCF-7) and its 
ability to affect mammalian (or mechanistic) target of rapamycin (mTOR) and 
nuclear factor kappa-light-chain-enhancer of activated B cells (NF-κB) signaling 
were evaluated. Moreover, the effects of this inhibitor to modulate LAT1 
function on the cell surface and the brain amino acid homeostasis were evaluated 
after intraperitoneal (i.p.) administration of LAT1-inhibitor (23 µmol/kg) in 
mice. The results showed that LAT1-inhibitor (KMH-233) is hemocompatible at 
concentrations below 25 µM and it does not affect coagulation in plasma. 
However, it can reduce the total protein amount of mTOR and NF-κB, resulting in 
increased apoptosis in LAT1-expressing cancer cells. Most importantly, the 
inhibitor did not affect mouse brain levels of L-Leu, L-Tyr or L-Trp or modulate 
the function of LAT1 on the MCF-7 cell surface. Therefore, this inhibitor can be 
considered as a safe but effective anti-cancer agent. However, due to the 
compensative mechanism of cancer cells for their increased amino acid demand, 
this compound is most effective inducing apoptosis when used in combinations 
with other chemotherapeutics, such as protease inhibitor, bestatin, as 
demonstrated in this study.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="387~411" text="LAT1-inhibitor (KMH-233)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1024~1038" text="LAT1-inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1086~1110" text="LAT1-inhibitor (KMH-233)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="472~519" text="human umbilical vein endothelial cells  (HUVEC)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="524~565" text="human aortic smooth muscle cells (AoSMCs)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="611~652" text="human breast adenocarcinoma cells (MCF-7)" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1056~1060" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1474~1484" text="MCF-7 cell" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1298~1307" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1288~1297" text="increased" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>