<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Loss of HMBOX1 promotes LPS-induced apoptosis and inhibits LPS-induced autophagy 
of vascular endothelial cells in mouse.

Our previous study revealed that Homeobox containing 1 (HMBOX1), essential for 
the survival of vascular endothelial cells (VECs), was involved in the 
progression of atherosclerosis. Knockdown of HMBOX1 promoted apoptosis and 
inhibited autophagy through regulating intracellular free zinc level in cultured 
VECs. In current study, in order to investigate the roles of HMBOX1 in vivo and 
in endothelium, we generated a knockout (KO) mouse for HMBOX1 by using 
transcription activator-like effector nucleases (TALENs) technology. Herein, we 
reported that the protein level of HMBOX1 was gradually increased during mouse 
development. The HMBOX1 KO mouse was viable and fertile. There existed no 
differences in apoptosis and autophagy of aortic endothelial cells between wild 
type and KO mouse. Whereas, loss of HMBOX1 promoted apoptosis and inhibited 
autophagy of aortic endothelial cells under lipopolysaccharide (LPS) stimulation 
in mouse. We also demonstrated that HMBOX1 deletion had no influence on the 
secretion of inflammatory cytokines TNF-α and IL-6. Moreover, overexpression or 
knockdown of HMBOX1 failed to regulate multiple pro-apoptotic genes expression 
in vitro. In conclusion, HMBOX1 participated in the functional maintenance of 
mouse aortic endothelial cells, the aortic endothelial cells of HMBOX1 KO mouse 
showed increased apoptosis and decreased autophagy with LPS treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="764~773" text="HMBOX1 KO" perturbingaction="-" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="931~945" text="loss of HMBOX1" perturbingaction="-" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1098~1113" text="HMBOX1 deletion" perturbingaction="-" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1201~1239" text="overexpression or  knockdown of HMBOX1" perturbingaction="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="501~508" text="in vivo" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="740~745" text="mouse" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="774~779" text="mouse" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="864~888" text="aortic endothelial cells" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="993~1017" text="aortic endothelial cells" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1065~1070" text="mouse" context="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1300~1308" text="in vitro" context="-" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="837~846" text="apoptosis" phenotype="-" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="851~860" text="autophagy" phenotype="-" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="955~964" text="apoptosis" phenotype="-" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="980~989" text="autophagy" phenotype="-" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="818~833" text="no  differences" effect="-" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="946~954" text="promoted" effect="-" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="969~978" text="inhibited" effect="-" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="loss of HMBOX1" effectID="E2" effectText="inhibited" phenotypeID="PH3" phenotypeText="autophagy" contextID="C6" contextText="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>