<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[NG25, a novel inhibitor of TAK1, suppresses KRAS-mutant colorectal cancer growth 
in vitro and in vivo.

KRAS mutations are one of the most prevalent genetic alterations in colorectal 
cancer (CRC). Although directly targeting KRAS still is a challenge in 
anti-cancer therapies, alternatively inhibiting KRAS related signaling pathways 
has been approached effectively. Here we firstly reported that MAP kinase, 
transforming growth factor-β-activated kinase 1 (TAK1), commonly expressed in 
CRC cell lines and significantly associated with KRAS mutation status. 
Inhibition of TAK1 by the small molecular inhibitor NG25 could inhibit CRC cells 
proliferation in vitro and in vivo, especially in KRAS-mutant cells. NG25 
induced caspase-dependent apoptosis in KRAS-mutant cells and in orthotopic CRC 
mouse models by regulating the B-cell lymphoma-2 (Bcl-2) family and the 
inhibitor of apoptosis protein (IAP) family. Besides inhibiting molecules 
downstream of MAPK, including ERK, JNK and p38 phosphorylation, NG25 could block 
NF-κB activation in KRAS-mutant cells. As a target gene of NF-κB, down-regulated 
XIAP expression may be not only involved in apoptosis induced by NG25, but also 
reducing the formation of TAK1-XIAP complex that can activate TAK1 downstream 
signaling pathways, which forms a positive feedback loop to further induce 
apoptosis in KRAS-mutant CRC cells. Together, these findings indicated that TAK1 
is an important kinase for survival of CRCs harboring KRAS mutations, and that 
NG25 may be a potential therapeutic strategy for KRAS-mutant CRC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="591~621" text="small molecular inhibitor NG25" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="697~708" text="KRAS-mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="761~772" text="KRAS-mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1052~1063" text="KRAS-mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1363~1374" text="KRAS-mutant" perturbingaction="-" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="493~507" text="CRC cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="661~669" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="674~681" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="773~778" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="802~807" text="mouse" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1064~1069" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C9" spans="1375~1384" text="CRC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C10" spans="709~714" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C11" spans="636~645" text="CRC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="748~757" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1158~1167" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1350~1359" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="647~660" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="628~635" text="inhibit" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="722~729" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1168~1175" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1342~1349" text="induce " effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>