<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Podocyte hypertrophy precedes apoptosis under experimental diabetic conditions.

Podocyte hypertrophy and apoptosis are two hallmarks of diabetic glomeruli, but 
the sequence in which these processes occur remains a matter of debate. Here we 
investigated the effects of inhibiting hypertrophy on apoptosis, and vice versa, 
in both podocytes and glomeruli, under diabetic conditions. Hypertrophy and 
apoptosis were inhibited using an epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitor 
(PKI 166) and a pan-caspase inhibitor (zAsp-DCB), respectively. We observed 
significant increases in the protein expression of p27, p21, phospho-eukaryotic 
elongation factor 4E-binding protein 1, and phospho-p70 S6 ribosomal protein 
kinase, in both cultured podocytes exposed to high-glucose (HG) medium, and 
streptozotocin-induced diabetes mellitus (DM) rat glomeruli. These increases 
were significantly inhibited by PKI 166, but not by zAsp-DCB. In addition, the 
amount of protein per cell, the relative cell size, and the glomerular volume 
were all significantly increased under diabetic conditions, and these changes 
were also blocked by treatment with PKI 166, but not zAsp-DCB. Increased protein 
expression of cleaved caspase-3 and cleaved poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase, 
together with increased Bax/Bcl-2 ratios, were also observed in HG-stimulated 
podocytes and DM glomeruli. Treatment with either zAsp-DCB or PKI 166 resulted 
in a significant attenuation of these effects. Both PKI 166 and zAsp-DCB also 
inhibited the increase in number of apoptotic cells, as assessed by Hoechst 
33342 staining and TUNEL assay. Under diabetic conditions, inhibition of 
podocyte hypertrophy results in attenuated apoptosis, whereas blocking apoptosis 
has no effect on podocyte hypertrophy, suggesting that podocyte hypertrophy 
precedes apoptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="436~489" text="epidermal growth factor receptor inhibitor  (PKI 166)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="496~528" text="pan-caspase inhibitor (zAsp-DCB)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1345~1354" text="podocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="839~852" text="rat glomeruli" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="402~411" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="417~426" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>