<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[mPGES-1-derived prostaglandin E2 stimulates Stat3 to promote podocyte apoptosis.

We previously reported that microsomal prostaglandin E synthase-1 (mPGES-1) 
contributed to adriamycin (Adr)-induced podocyte apoptosis. However, the 
molecular mechanism remains unclear. Here we studied the role of mPGES-1/PGE2 
cascade in activating Stat3 signaling and the contribution of Stat3 in PGE2- and 
Adr-induced podocyte apoptosis. In murine podocytes, PGE2 dose- and 
time-dependently increased the phosphorylation of Stat3 in line with the 
enhanced cell apoptosis and reduced podocyte protein podocin. In agreement with 
the increased Stat3 phosphorylation, Stat3-derived cytokines including IL-6, 
IL-17, MCP-1, and ICAM-1 were significantly upregulated following PGE2 
treatment. By application of a specific Stat3 inhibitor S3I-201, PGE2-induced 
podocyte apoptosis was largely abolished in parallel with a blockade of podocin 
reduction. Next, we observed that Adr treatment also enhanced p-Stat3 and 
activated mPGES-1/PGE2 cascade. Blockade of Stat3 by S3I-201 significantly 
ameliorated Adr-induced cell apoptosis and podocin reduction. More 
interestingly, silencing mPGES-1 in podocytes by mPGES-1 siRNA blocked 
Adr-induced increments of Stat-3 phosphorylation, PGE2 production, and 
Stat3-derived inflammatory cytokines. Taken together, this study suggested that 
mPGES-1-derived PGE2 could activate Stat3 signaling to promote podocyte 
apoptosis. Targeting mPGES-1/PGE2/Stat3 signaling might be a potential strategy 
for the treatment of podocytopathy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="808~831" text="Stat3 inhibitor S3I-201" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1035~1063" text="Blockade of Stat3 by S3I-201" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1196~1209" text="mPGES-1 siRNA" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="436~445" text="podocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="847~855" text="podocyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1183~1192" text="podocytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="551~560" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="856~865" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1108~1117" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="537~545" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="838~845" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="878~887" text="abolished" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1079~1090" text="ameliorated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1095~1102" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Stat3 inhibitor S3I-201" contextID="C1" contextText="podocyte" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="apoptosis" effectID="E2" effectText="abolished" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>