<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Oroxylin A induces apoptosis of activated hepatic stellate cells through 
endoplasmic reticulum stress.

Hepatic stellate cell (HSC) activation plays an indispensable role in hepatic 
fibrosis. Inducing apoptosis of activated HSCs can attenuate or reverse 
fibrogenesis. In this study, we initially found that oroxylin A (OA) protected 
CCl4-induced liver injury accompanied by endoplasmic reticulum stress (ERS) 
activation of HSCs in mice. In vitro, OA treatment markedly reduced fibrogenesis 
by modulating extracellular matrix synthesis and degradation. OA inhibited cell 
proliferation and induced cell cycle arrest of HSCs at S phase. Further, OA was 
observed to induce HSC apoptosis, as indicated by caspase activation. Using the 
eIF2α dephosphorylation inhibitor salubrinal, we found that ERS pathway 
activation was required for OA to induce HSC apoptosis. ERS-related proteins 
were significantly upregulated by OA treatment, and salubrinal abrogated the 
effects of OA on HSCs. Thus, we inferred that OA attenuated HSC activation by 
promoting ERS. In vivo, inhibition of ERS by salubrinal partly abrogated the 
hepatoprotective effect of OA in CCl4-treated mice. In conclusion, our findings 
suggest a role for ERS in the mechanism underlying amelioration of hepatic 
fibrosis by OA.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="428~432" text="HSCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="436~440" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="677~680" text="HSC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="853~856" text="HSC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="985~989" text="HSCs" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="571~590" text="cell  proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="603~620" text="cell cycle arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="681~690" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="857~866" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="561~570" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="595~602" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="670~676" text="induce" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="846~852" text="induce" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>