<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MLKL mediates apoptosis via a mutual regulation with PERK/eIF2α pathway in 
response to reactive oxygen species generation.

The pseudokinase mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein (MLKL) is a core 
effector of necroptosis, and its function in necroptosis is widely studied. 
However, the function of MLKL in apoptosis remains unclear. In the present 
study, the role of MLKL in chelerythrine (CHE)-promoted apoptosis was studied. A 
special band of MLKL (i.e., *MLKL) was observed after treatment with CHE. MLKL 
and *MLKL were accumulated in the nucleus upon treatment with CHE and MLKL 
silencing reversed the CHE-induced apoptosis. Blockade of CHE-triggered reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) generation or inhibition of CHE-activated protein 
kinase-like endoplasmic reticulum kinase (PERK)-eukaryotic initiation factor 2 α 
subunit (eIF2α) pathway reversed the apoptosis. A decreased ROS level inhibited 
CHE-mediated nuclear translocation of MLKL and *MLKL and the activation of 
eIF2α, whereas MLKL or eIF2α silencing did not affect the CHE-triggered ROS 
generation. Furthermore, MLKL silencing prevented the CHE-activated eIF2α 
signal, and eIF2α silencing blocked the CHE-induced nuclear translocation of 
MLKL and *MLKL. Our studies suggested that CHE possibly induces apoptosis 
through the nuclear translocation of MLKL and *MLKL, which is promoted by a 
mutual regulation between MLKL and PERK-eIF2α pathway in response to ROS 
formation. The present study clarified the new function of MLKL in apoptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1000~1023" text="MLKL or eIF2α silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1087~1101" text="MLKL silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1149~1164" text="eIF2α silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="578~601" text="CHE and MLKL  silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="627~636" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="865~874" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="602~610" text="reversed" effect="rescues" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="619~626" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="852~860" text="reversed" effect="rescues" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>