<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The neuroprotective action of 3,3'-diindolylmethane against ischemia involves an 
inhibition of apoptosis and autophagy that depends on HDAC and AhR/CYP1A1 but 
not ERα/CYP19A1 signaling.

There are no studies examining the effects of 3,3'-diindolylmethane (DIM) in 
neuronal cells subjected to ischemia. Little is also known about the roles of 
apoptosis and autophagy as well as AhR and ERα signaling and HDACs in DIM 
action. We demonstrated for the first time the strong neuroprotective capacity 
of DIM in mouse primary hippocampal cell cultures exposed to ischemia at early 
and later stages of neuronal development. The protective effects of DIM were 
mediated via inhibition of ischemia-induced apoptosis and autophagy that was 
accompanied by a decrease in AhR/CYP1A1 signaling and an increase in HDAC 
activity. DIM decreased the levels of pro-apoptotic factors, i.e., Fas, 
Caspase-3, and p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK). DIM also reduced the 
protein levels of autophagy-related Beclin-1 (BECN1) and microtubule-associated 
proteins 1A/1B light chain (LC3), partially reversed the ischemia-induced 
decrease in Nucleoporin 62 (NUP62) and inhibited autophagosome formation. In 
addition, DIM completely reversed the ischemia-induced decrease in histone 
deacetylase (HDAC) activity in hippocampal neurons. Although DIM inhibited 
AhR/CYP1A1 signaling, it did not influence the protein expression levels of ERα 
and ERα-regulated CYP19A1 which are known to be controlled by AhR. This study 
demonstrated for the first time, that the neuroprotective action of 
3,3'-diindolylmethane against ischemia involves an inhibition of apoptosis and 
autophagy and depends on AhR/CYP1A1 signaling and HDAC activity, thus creating 
the possibility of developing new therapeutic strategies that target neuronal 
degeneration at specific molecular levels.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1320~1327" text="neurons" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="703~712" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="717~726" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1172~1195" text="autophagosome formation" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="627~645" text="protective effects" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="659~667" text="mediated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="695~702" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1162~1171" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>