<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mechanisms of cell death induced by arginase and asparaginase in precursor 
B-cell lymphoblasts.

Arginase has therapeutic potential as a cytotoxic agent in some cancers, but 
this is unclear for precursor B acute lymphoblastic leukaemia (pre-B ALL), the 
commonest form of childhood leukaemia. We compared arginase cytotoxicity with 
asparaginase, currently used in pre-B ALL treatment, and characterised the forms 
of cell death induced in a pre-B ALL cell line 697. Arginase and asparaginase 
both efficiently killed 697 cells and mature B lymphoma cell line Ramos, but 
neither enzyme killed normal lymphocytes. Arginase depleted cellular arginine, 
and arginase-treated media induced cell death, blocked by addition of arginine 
or arginine-precursor citrulline. Asparaginase depleted both asparagine and 
glutamine, and asparaginase-treated media induced cell death, blocked by 
asparagine, but not glutamine. Both enzymes induced caspase cleavage and 
activation, chromatin condensation and phosphatidylserine exposure, indicating 
apoptosis. Both arginase- and asparaginase-induced death were blocked by caspase 
inhibitors, but with different sensitivities. BCL-2 overexpression inhibited 
arginase- and asparaginase-induced cell death, but did not prevent 
arginase-induced cytostasis, indicating a different mechanism of growth arrest. 
An autophagy inhibitor, chloroquine, had no effect on the cell death induced by 
arginase, but doubled the cell death induced by asparaginase. In conclusion, 
arginase causes death of lymphoblasts by arginine-depletion induced apoptosis, 
via mechanism distinct from asparaginase. Therapeutic implications for childhood 
ALL include: arginase might be used as treatment (but antagonised by dietary 
arginine and citrulline), chloroquine may enhance efficacy of asparaginase 
treatment, and partial resistance to arginase and asparaginase may develop by 
BCL-2 expression. Arginase or asparaginase might potentially be used to treat 
Burkitt lymphoma.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1167~1187" text="BCL-2 overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1112~1131" text="caspase  inhibitors" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1348~1383" text="An autophagy inhibitor, chloroquine" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="444~467" text="pre-B ALL cell line 697" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="520~529" text="697 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="541~561" text="B lymphoma cell line" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="603~614" text="lymphocytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="689~699" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1039~1048" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1234~1244" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1406~1416" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH6" spans="1455~1465" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH7" spans="861~871" text="cell death" phenotype="-" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="681~689" text="induced " effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="929~937" text="induced " effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1188~1197" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1226~1233" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E10" spans="1389~1398" text="no effect" effect="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E11" spans="1443~1450" text="doubled" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="853~860" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1388~1398" text=" no effect" effect="no effect" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>