<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ClC-3 deficiency protects preadipocytes against apoptosis induced by palmitate 
in vitro and in type 2 diabetes mice.

Palmitate, a common saturated free fatty acid (FFA), has been demonstrated to 
induce preadipocyte apoptosis in the absence of adipogenic stimuli, suggesting 
that preadipocytes may be prone to apoptosis under adipogenic insufficient 
conditions, like type 2 diabetes mellitus (T2DM). ClC-3, encoding Cl(-) channel 
or Cl(-)/H(+) antiporter, is critical for cell fate choices of proliferation 
versus apoptosis under diseased conditions. However, it is unknown whether ClC-3 
is related with preadipocyte apoptosis induced by palmitate or T2DM. Palmitate, 
but not oleate, induced apoptosis and increase in ClC-3 protein expression and 
endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress in 3T3-L1 preadipocyte. ClC-3 specific siRNA 
attenuated palmitate-induced apoptosis and increased protein levels of Grp78, 
ATF4, CHOP and phosphorylation of JNK1/2, whereas had no effects on increased 
phospho-PERK and phospho-eIF2α protein expression. Moreover, the enhanced 
apoptosis was shown in preadipocytes from high-sucrose/fat, low-dose STZ induced 
T2DM mouse model with hyperglycemia, hyperlipidemia (elevated serum TG and FFA 
levels) and insulin resistance. ClC-3 knockout significantly attenuated 
preadipocyte apoptosis and the above metabolic disorders in T2DM mice. These 
data demonstrated that ClC-3 deficiency prevent preadipocytes against 
palmitate-induced apoptosis via suppressing ER stress, and also suggested that 
ClC-3 may play a role in regulating cellular apoptosis and disorders of glucose 
and lipid metabolism during T2DM.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="814~834" text="ClC-3 specific siRNA" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1263~1277" text="ClC-3 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1092~1105" text="preadipocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1304~1316" text="preadipocyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1369~1373" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="700~709" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="865~875" text="apoptosis " phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1069~1078" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1317~1326" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="692~699" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="836~846" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="857~864" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1059~1067" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1292~1302" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" phenotypeID="PH3" phenotypeText="apoptosis" contextID="C2" contextText="mice" effectID="E4" effectText="attenuated" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ClC-3 knockout" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>