<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Exploitation of a novel phenothiazine derivative for its anti-cancer activities 
in malignant glioblastoma.

Glioblastoma remains the most malignant of all primary adult brain tumours with 
poor patient survival and limited treatment options. This study adopts a drug 
repurposing approach by investigating the anti-cancer activity of a derivative 
of the antipsychotic drug phenothiazine (DS00329) in malignant U251 and U87 
glioblastoma cells. Results from MTT 
(3-(4,5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide) and clonogenic 
assays showed that DS00329 inhibited short-term glioblastoma cell viability and 
long-term survival while sparing non-cancerous cells. Western blot analysis with 
an antibody to γH2AX showed that DS00329 induced DNA damage and flow cytometry 
and western blotting confirmed that it triggered a G1 cell cycle arrest which 
correlated with decreased levels in Cyclin A, Cyclin B, Cyclin D1 and cyclin 
dependent kinase 2 and an increase in levels of the cyclin dependent kinase 
inhibitor p21. DS00329 treated glioblastoma cells exhibited morphological and 
molecular markers typical of apoptotic cells such as membrane blebbing and cell 
shrinkage and an increase in levels of cleaved PARP. Flow cytometry with annexin 
V-FITC/propidium iodide staining confirmed that DS00329 induced apoptotic cell 
death in glioblastoma cells. We also show that DS00329 treatment of glioblastoma 
cells led to an increase in the autophagosome marker LC3-II and autophagy 
inhibition studies using bafilomycin A1 and wortmannin, showed that 
DS00329-induced-autophagy was a pro-death mechanism. Furthermore, DS00329 
treatment of glioblastoma cells inhibited the phosphatidylinositol 3'-kinase/Akt 
cell survival pathway. Our findings suggest that DS00329 may be an effective 
treatment for glioblastoma and provide a rationale for further exploration and 
validation of the use of phenothiazines and their derivatives in the treatment 
of glioblastoma.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="591~603" text="glioblastoma" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="657~676" text="non-cancerous cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1051~1069" text="glioblastoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1351~1369" text="glioblastoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1410~1429" text="glioblastoma  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1656~1674" text="glioblastoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="604~618" text="cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="840~857" text="cell cycle arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1336~1347" text="cell  death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1488~1497" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1584~1593" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH6" spans="1725~1738" text="cell survival" phenotype="cell survival" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="570~579" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="825~834" text="triggered" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1318~1325" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1499~1509" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1576~1583" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1675~1684" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>