<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Beta1 integrin inhibits apoptosis induced by cyclic stretch in annulus fibrosus 
cells via ERK1/2 MAPK pathway.

Low back pain is associated with intervertebral disc degeneration (IVDD) due to 
cellular loss through apoptosis. Mechanical factors play an important role in 
maintaining the survival of the annulus fibrosus (AF) cells and the deposition 
of extracellular matrix. However, the mechanisms that excessive mechanical 
forces lead to AF cell apoptosis are not clear. The present study was to look 
for how AF cells sense mechanical changes. In vivo experiments, the involvement 
of mechanoreceptors in apoptosis was examined by RT-PCR and/or immunoblotting in 
the lumbar spine of rats subjected to unbalanced dynamic and static forces. In 
vitro experiments, we investigated apoptotic signaling pathways in untransfected 
and transfected AF cells with the lentivirus vector for rat β1 integrin 
overexpression after cyclic stretch. Apoptosis in AF cells was assessed using 
flow cytometry, Hoechst 33258 nuclear staining. Western blotting was used to 
analyze expression of β1 integrin and caspase-3 and ERK1/2 MAPK signaling 
molecules. In the rat IVDD model, unbalanced dynamic and static forces induced 
apoptosis of disc cells, which corresponded to decreased expression of β1 
integrin. Cyclic stretch-induced apoptosis in rat AF cells correlated with the 
activation of caspase-3 and with decreased levels of β1 integrin and the 
phosphorylation levels of ERK1/2 activation level. However, the overexpression 
of β1 integrin in AF cells ameliorated cyclic stretch-induced apoptosis and 
decreased caspase-3 activation. Furthermore, ERK1/2-specific inhibitor promotes 
apoptosis in vector β1-infected AF cells. These results suggest that the 
disruption of β1 integrin signaling may underlie disc cell apoptosis induced by 
mechanical stress. Further work is necessary to fully elucidate the 
pathophysiological mechanisms that underlie IVDD caused by unbalanced dynamic 
and static forces.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1511~1541" text="overexpression  of β1 integrin" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1649~1674" text="ERK1/2-specific inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1156~1159" text="rat" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1231~1241" text="disc cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1343~1351" text="AF cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1545~1553" text="AF cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="551~558" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="747~756" text="In  vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="305~332" text="annulus fibrosus (AF) cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="675~695" text="lumbar spine of rats" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1717~1725" text="AF cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1218~1227" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1326~1335" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1589~1598" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1685~1694" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1209~1216" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1318~1325" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1581~1588" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1554~1565" text="ameliorated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1675~1683" text="promotes" effect="-" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="ERK1/2-specific inhibitor" effectID="E4" effectText="promotes" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="apoptosis" contextID="C8" contextText="AF cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>