<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[YTHDF1 promotes gastric carcinogenesis by controlling translation of FZD7.

N6-methyladenosine (m6A) is the most prevalent internal RNA modification in 
mammals that regulates homeostasis and function of modified RNA transcripts. 
Here we aimed to investigate the role of YTH N6-methyladenosine RNA binding 
protein 1 (YTHDF1), a key regulator of m6A methylation in gastric cancer (GC) 
tumorigenesis. Multiple bioinformatic analyses of different human cancer 
databases identified key m6A-associated genetic mutations that regulated gastric 
tumorigenesis. YTHDF1 was mutated in about 7% of gastric cancer patients and 
high expression of YTHDF1 was associated with more aggressive tumor progression 
and poor overall survival. Inhibition of YTHDF1 attenuated GC cell proliferation 
and tumorigenesis in vitro and in vivo. Mechanistically, YTHDF1 promoted the 
translation of a key Wnt receptor frizzled7 (FZD7) in an m6A-dependent manner, 
and mutated YTHDF1 enhanced expression of FZD7, leading to hyper-activation of 
the Wnt/β-catenin pathway and promotion of gastric carcinogenesis. Our results 
demonstrate the oncogenic role of YTHDF1 and its m6A-mediated regulation of 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling in gastric cancer, providing a novel approach of 
targeting such epigenetic regulators in this disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="729~749" text="Inhibition of YTHDF1" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="946~960" text="mutated YTHDF1" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="761~768,802~810" text="GC cell ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="761~768,815~822" text="GC cell ... in vivo" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="750~760,769~782" text="attenuated ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="750~760,788~801" text="attenuated ... tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1052~1087" text="promotion of gastric carcinogenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Inhibition of YTHDF1" effectID="E0" effectText="attenuated ... proliferation" contextID="C1" contextText="GC cell ... in vitro" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Inhibition of YTHDF1" contextID="C2" contextText="GC cell ... in vivo" effectID="E0" effectText="attenuated ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Inhibition of YTHDF1" contextID="C1" contextText="GC cell ... in vitro" effectID="E1" effectText="attenuated ... tumorigenesis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN3" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Inhibition of YTHDF1" contextID="C2" contextText="GC cell ... in vivo" effectID="E1" effectText="attenuated ... tumorigenesis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>