<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[USP10 Promotes Proliferation of Hepatocellular Carcinoma by Deubiquitinating and 
Stabilizing YAP/TAZ.

Yes-associated protein (YAP) and its paralog, transcriptional coactivator with 
PDZ-binding motif (TAZ), play pivotal roles in promoting the progression of 
hepatocellular carcinoma. However, the regulatory mechanism underpinning 
aberrant activation of YAP/TAZ in hepatocellular carcinoma remains unclear. In 
this study, we globally profiled the contribution of deubiquitinating enzymes 
(DUB) to both transcriptional activity and protein abundance of YAP/TAZ in 
hepatocellular carcinoma models and identified ubiquitin-specific peptidase 10 
(USP10) as a potent YAP/TAZ-activating DUB. Mechanistically, USP10 directly 
interacted with and stabilized YAP/TAZ by reverting their proteolytic 
ubiquitination. Depletion of USP10 enhanced polyubiquitination of YAP/TAZ, 
promoted their proteasomal degradation, and ultimately arrested the 
proliferation of hepatocellular carcinoma in vitro and in vivo. Expression 
levels of USP10 positively correlated with the abundance of YAP/TAZ in 
hepatocellular carcinoma patient samples as well as in N-nitrosodiethylamine 
(DEN)-induced liver cancer mice models. Collectively, this study establishes the 
causal link between USP10 and hyperactivated YAP/TAZ in hepatocellular carcinoma 
cells and provides a rationale for potential therapeutic interventions in the 
treatment of patients with hepatocellular carcinoma harboring a high level of 
YAP/TAZ. SIGNIFICANCE: These findings identify USP10 as a DUB of YAP/TAZ and its 
role in hepatocellular carcinoma progression, which may serve as a potential 
therapeutic target for hepatocellular carcinoma treatment.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="814~832" text="Depletion of USP10" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="960~993" text="hepatocellular carcinoma in vitro" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="960~984,998~1005" text="hepatocellular carcinoma ... in vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1196~1207" text="mice models" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="929~937,943~956" text="arrested ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1175~1195" text="induced liver cancer" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Depletion of USP10" contextID="C0" contextText="hepatocellular carcinoma in vitro" effectID="E2" effectText="arrested ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Depletion of USP10" contextID="C1" contextText="hepatocellular carcinoma ... in vivo" effectID="E2" effectText="arrested ... proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>