<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PSF Promotes ER-Positive Breast Cancer Progression via Posttranscriptional 
Regulation of ESR1 and SCFD2.


Endocrine therapy is standard treatment for estrogen receptor (ER)-positive 
breast cancer, yet long-term treatment often causes acquired resistance, which 
results in recurrence and metastasis. Recent studies have revealed that 
RNA-binding proteins (RBP) are involved in tumorigenesis. Here, we demonstrate 
that PSF/SFPQ is an RBP that potentially predicts poor prognosis of patients 
with ER-positive breast cancer by posttranscriptionally regulating ERα (ESR1) 
mRNA expression. Strong PSF immunoreactivity correlated with shorter overall 
survival in patients with ER-positive breast cancer. PSF was predominantly 
expressed in a model of tamoxifen-resistant breast cancer cells, and depletion 
of PSF attenuated proliferation of cultured cells and xenografted tumors. PSF 
expression was significantly associated with estrogen signaling. PSF siRNA 
downregulated ESR1 mRNA by inhibiting nuclear export of the RNA. Integrative 
analyses of microarray and RNA immunoprecipitation sequencing also identified 
SCFD2, TRA2B, and ASPM as targets of PSF. Among the PSF targets, SCFD2 was a 
poor prognostic indicator of breast cancer and SCFD2 knockdown significantly 
suppressed breast cancer cell proliferation. Collectively, this study shows that 
PSF plays a pathophysiologic role in ER-positive breast cancer by 
posttranscriptionally regulating expression of its target genes such as ESR1 and 
SCFD2. Overall, PSF and SCFD2 could be potential diagnostic and therapeutic 
targets for primary and hormone-refractory breast cancers. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="798~815" text="depletion  of PSF" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="953~962" text="PSF siRNA" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1246~1261" text="SCFD2 knockdown" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="844~858" text="cultured cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="863~881" text="xenografted tumors" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1288~1306" text="breast cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="816~840" text="attenuated proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1277~1287,1307~1320" text="suppressed ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="depletion  of PSF" effectID="E0" effectText="attenuated proliferation" contextID="C0" contextText="cultured cells" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="depletion  of PSF" contextID="C1" contextText="xenografted tumors" effectID="E0" effectText="attenuated proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="SCFD2 knockdown" contextID="C2" contextText="breast cancer cell" effectID="E1" effectText="suppressed ... proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>