<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ETV4 Is Necessary for Estrogen Signaling and Growth in Endometrial Cancer Cells.

Estrogen signaling through estrogen receptor alpha (ER) plays a major role in 
endometrial cancer risk and progression, however, the molecular mechanisms 
underlying ER's regulatory role in endometrial cancer are poorly understood. In 
breast cancer cells, ER genomic binding is enabled by FOXA1 and GATA3, but the 
transcription factors that control ER genomic binding in endometrial cancer 
cells remain unknown. We previously identified ETV4 as a candidate factor 
controlling ER genomic binding in endometrial cancer cells, and here we explore 
the functional importance of ETV4. Homozygous deletion of ETV4, using 
CRISPR/Cas9, led to greatly reduced ER binding at the majority of loci normally 
bound by ER. Consistent with the dramatic loss of ER binding, the gene 
expression response to estradiol was dampened for most genes. ETV4 contributes 
to estrogen signaling in two distinct ways. ETV4 loss affects chromatin 
accessibility at some ER bound loci and impairs ER nuclear translocation. The 
diminished estrogen signaling upon ETV4 deletion led to decreased growth, 
particularly in 3D culture, where hollow organoids were formed and in vivo in 
the context of estrogen-dependent growth. These results show that ETV4 plays an 
important role in estrogen signaling in endometrial cancer cells. SIGNIFICANCE: 
Estrogen receptor alpha (ER) is a key oncogene in endometrial cancer. This study 
uncovers ETV4 as an important factor in controlling the activity of ER and the 
growth of endometrial cancer cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="666~713" text="Homozygous deletion of ETV4, using  CRISPR/Cas9" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1122~1135" text="ETV4 deletion" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1178~1224" text="3D culture, where hollow organoids were formed" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1229~1236" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1136~1159" text="led to decreased growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ETV4 deletion" contextID="C0" contextText="3D culture, where hollow organoids were formed" effectID="E0" effectText="led to decreased growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ETV4 deletion" effectID="E0" effectText="led to decreased growth" contextID="C1" contextText="in vivo" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>