<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Inactivation of the Prolyl Isomerase Pin1 Sensitizes BRCA1-Proficient Breast 
Cancer to PARP Inhibition.

PARP inhibitor monotherapies are effective to treat patients with breast, ovary, 
prostate, and pancreatic cancer with BRCA1 mutations, but not to the much more 
frequent BRCA wild-type cancers. Searching for strategies that would extend the 
use of PARP inhibitors to BRCA1-proficient tumors, we found that the stability 
of BRCA1 protein following ionizing radiation (IR) is maintained by 
postphosphorylational prolyl-isomerization adjacent to Ser1191 of BRCA1, 
catalyzed by prolyl-isomerase Pin1. Extinction of Pin1 decreased homologous 
recombination (HR) to the level of BRCA1-deficient cells. Pin1 stabilizes BRCA1 
by preventing ubiquitination of Lys1037 of BRCA1. Loss of Pin1, or introduction 
of a BRCA1-mutant refractory to Pin1 binding, decreased the ability of BRCA1 to 
localize to repair foci and augmented IR-induced DNA damage. In vitro growth of 
HR-proficient breast, prostate, and pancreatic cancer cells were modestly 
repressed by olaparib or Pin1 inhibition using all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA), 
while combination treatment resulted in near-complete block of cell 
proliferation. In MDA-MB-231 xenografts and triple-negative breast cancer 
patient-derived xenografts, either loss of Pin1 or ATRA treatment reduced BRCA1 
expression and sensitized breast tumors to olaparib. Together, our study reveals 
that Pin1 inhibition, with clinical widely used ATRA, acts as an effective HR 
disrupter that sensitizes BRCA1-proficient tumors to PARP inhibition. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="608~626" text="Extinction of Pin1" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="780~792" text="Loss of Pin1" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="816~855" text="BRCA1-mutant refractory to Pin1 binding" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1073~1125" text="Pin1 inhibition using all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1307~1319" text="loss of Pin1" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="953~961,973~1032" text="In vitro ... HR-proficient breast, prostate, and pancreatic cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1191~1195" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1215~1236" text="MDA-MB-231 xenografts" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1241~1298" text="triple-negative breast cancer  patient-derived xenografts" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="962~968,1033~1057" text="growth ... were modestly  repressed" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1182~1190,1197~1210" text="block of ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="Pin1 inhibition using all-trans retinoic acid (ATRA)" effectID="E0" effectText="growth ... were modestly  repressed" contextID="C1" contextText="In vitro ... HR-proficient breast, prostate, and pancreatic cancer cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>