<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Activation of Canonical BMP4-SMAD7 Signaling Suppresses Breast Cancer 
Metastasis.

Metastasis is the major cause of death in patients with cancer; with no 
therapeutic cure, treatments remain largely palliative. As such, new targets and 
therapeutic strategies are urgently required. Here, we show that bone 
morphogenetic protein-4 (BMP4) blocks metastasis in animal models of breast 
cancer and predicts improved survival in patients. In preclinical models of 
spontaneous metastasis, BMP4 acted as an autocrine mediator to modulate a range 
of known metastasis-regulating genes, including Smad7, via activation of 
canonical BMP-SMAD signaling. Restored BMP4 expression or therapeutically 
administered BMP4 protein, blocked metastasis and increased survival by 
sensitizing cancer cells to anoikis, thereby reducing the number of circulating 
tumor cells. Gene silencing of Bmp4 or its downstream mediator Smad7, reversed 
this phenotype. Administration of recombinant BMP4 markedly reduced spontaneous 
metastasis to lung and bone. Elevated levels of BMP4 and SMAD7 were prognostic 
for improved recurrence-free survival and overall survival in patients with 
breast cancer, indicating the importance of canonical BMP4 signaling in the 
suppression of metastasis and highlighting new avenues for therapy against 
metastatic disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="649~673" text="Restored BMP4 expression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="861~883" text="Gene silencing of Bmp4" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="861~878,911~916" text="Gene silencing of ... Smad7" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="779~791" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="848~859" text="tumor cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="721~739" text="blocked metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="767~778,792~802" text="sensitizing ... to anoikis" phenotype="anoikis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="988~995,1009~1036" text="reduced ... metastasis to lung and bone" phenotype="metastasis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Restored BMP4 expression" contextID="C1" contextText="cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="blocked metastasis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Restored BMP4 expression" contextID="C1" contextText="cancer cells" effectID="E1" effectText="sensitizing ... to anoikis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>