<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Tumor Fibroblast-Derived FGF2 Regulates Expression of SPRY1 in Esophageal 
Tumor-Infiltrating T Cells and Plays a Role in T-cell Exhaustion.

T-cell exhaustion was initially identified in chronic infection in mice and was 
subsequently described in humans with cancer. Although the distinct signature of 
exhausted T (TEX) cells in cancer has been well investigated, the molecular 
mechanism of T-cell exhaustion in cancer is not fully understood. Using 
single-cell RNA sequencing, we report here that TEX cells in esophageal cancer 
are more heterogeneous than previously clarified. Sprouty RTK signaling 
antagonist 1 (SPRY1) was notably enriched in two subsets of exhausted CD8+ T 
cells. When overexpressed, SPRY1 impaired T-cell activation by interacting with 
CBL, a negative regulator of ZAP-70 tyrosine phosphorylation. Data from the 
Tumor Immune Estimation Resource revealed a strong correlation between FGF2 and 
SPRY1 expression in esophageal cancer. High expression of FGF2 was evident in 
fibroblasts from esophageal cancer tissue and correlated with poor overall 
survival. In vitro administration of FGF2 significantly upregulated expression 
of SPRY1 in CD8+ T cells and attenuated T-cell receptor-triggered CD8+ T-cell 
activation. A mouse tumor model confirmed that overexpression of FGF2 in 
fibroblasts significantly upregulated SPRY1 expression in TEX cells, impaired 
T-cell cytotoxic activity, and promoted tumor growth. Thus, these findings 
identify FGF2 as an important regulator of SPRY1 expression involved in 
establishing the dysfunctional state of CD8+ T cells in esophageal cancer. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="698~718" text="overexpressed, SPRY1" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1286~1308" text="overexpression of FGF2" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="728~734" text="T-cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1172~1184" text="CD8+ T cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1226~1237" text="CD8+ T-cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1253~1270" text="mouse tumor model" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1313~1324" text="fibroblasts" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1371~1380" text="TEX cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1423~1444" text="promoted tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="overexpression of FGF2" contextID="C4" contextText="fibroblasts" effectID="E0" effectText="promoted tumor growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>