<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[
Endothelin-1-Mediated Drug Resistance in EGFR-Mutant Non-Small Cell Lung 
Carcinoma.

Progression on therapy in non-small cell lung carcinoma (NSCLC) is often 
evaluated radiographically, however, image-based evaluation of said therapies 
may not distinguish disease progression due to intrinsic tumor drug resistance 
or inefficient tumor penetration of the drugs. Here we report that the 
inhibition of mutated EGFR promotes the secretion of a potent vasoconstrictor, 
endothelin-1 (EDN1), which continues to increase as the cells become resistant 
with a mesenchymal phenotype. As EDN1 and its receptor (EDNR) is linked to 
cancer progression, EDNR-antagonists have been evaluated in several clinical 
trials with disappointing results. These trials were based on a hypothesis that 
the EDN1-EDNR axis activates the MAPK-ERK signaling pathway that is vital to the 
cancer cell survival; the trials were not designed to evaluate the impact of 
tumor-derived EDN1 in modifying tumor microenvironment or contributing to drug 
resistance. Ectopic overexpression of EDN1 in cells with mutated EGFR resulted 
in poor drug delivery and retarded growth in vivo but not in vitro. Intratumoral 
injection of recombinant EDN significantly reduced blood flow and subsequent 
gefitinib accumulation in xenografted EGFR-mutant tumors. Furthermore, depletion 
of EDN1 or the use of endothelin receptor inhibitors bosentan and ambrisentan 
improved drug penetration into tumors and restored blood flow in 
tumor-associated vasculature. Correlatively, these results describe a simplistic 
endogenous yet previously unrealized resistance mechanism inherent to a subset 
of EGFR-mutant NSCLC to attenuate tyrosine kinase inhibitor delivery to the 
tumors by limiting drug-carrying blood flow and the drug concentration in 
tumors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="392~418" text="inhibition of mutated EGFR" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1039~1069" text="Ectopic overexpression of EDN1" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1084~1096" text="mutated EGFR" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1338~1356" text="depletion  of EDN1" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="528~533" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1073~1078,1149~1156" text="cells ... in vivo" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1073~1078,1165~1173" text="cells ... in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1293~1323" text="xenografted EGFR-mutant tumors" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1133~1148" text="retarded growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1133~1148,1161~1164" text="retarded growth ... not" phenotype="cell growth" activity="no effect" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Ectopic overexpression of EDN1" contextID="C2" contextText="cells ... in vivo" effectID="E0" effectText="retarded growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Ectopic overexpression of EDN1" contextID="C3" contextText="cells ... in vitro" effectID="E1" effectText="retarded growth ... not" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>