<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ANXA1 Binds and Stabilizes EphA2 to Promote Nasopharyngeal Carcinoma Growth and 
Metastasis.

Overexpression of ANXA1 and EphA2 has been linked to various cancers and both 
proteins have attracted considerable attention for the development of new 
anticancer drugs. Here we report that ANXA1 competes with Cbl for binding EphA2 
and increases its stability by inhibiting Cbl-mediated EphA2 ubiquitination and 
degradation in nasopharyngeal carcinoma (NPC). Binding of ANXA1 to EphA2 
promoted NPC cell growth and metastasis in vitro and in vivo by elevating EphA2 
levels and increasing activity of EphA2 oncogenic signaling (pS897-EphA2). 
Expression of ANXA1 and EphA2 was positively correlated and both were 
significantly higher in NPC tissues than in the normal nasopharyngeal epithelial 
tissues. Patients with high expression of both proteins presented poorer 
disease-free survival and overall survival relative to patients with high 
expression of one protein alone. Furthermore, amino acid residues 20-30aa and 
28-30aa of the ANXA1 N-terminus bound EphA2. An 11 amino acid-long ANXA1-derived 
peptide (EYVQTVKSSKG) was developed on the basis of this N-terminal region, 
which disrupted the connection of ANXA1 with EphA2, successfully downregulating 
EphA2 expression and dramatically suppressing NPC cell oncogenicity in vitro and 
in mice. These findings suggest that ANXA1 promotes NPC growth and metastasis 
via binding and stabilization of EphA2 and present a strategy for targeting 
EphA2 degradation and treating NPC with a peptide. This therapeutic strategy may 
also be extended to other cancers with high expression of both proteins. 
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1067~1125,1246~1278" text="An 11 amino acid-long ANXA1-derived  peptide (EYVQTVKSSKG) ... downregulating  EphA2 expression" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1308~1316,1330~1338" text="NPC cell ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1308~1316,1344~1351" text="NPC cell ... in mice" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="493~496,524~532" text="NPC ... in vitro" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="493~496,537~544" text="NPC ... in vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1296~1307,1317~1329" text="suppressing ... oncogenicity" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="484~492,497~508" text="promoted ... cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="484~492,513~523" text="promoted ... metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="An 11 amino acid-long ANXA1-derived  peptide (EYVQTVKSSKG) ... downregulating  EphA2 expression" contextID="C4" contextText="NPC cell ... in vitro" effectID="E4" effectText="suppressing ... oncogenicity" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="An 11 amino acid-long ANXA1-derived  peptide (EYVQTVKSSKG) ... downregulating  EphA2 expression" contextID="C5" contextText="NPC cell ... in mice" effectID="E4" effectText="suppressing ... oncogenicity" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>