<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Proteomic Profiling of the ECM of Xenograft Breast Cancer Metastases in 
Different Organs Reveals Distinct Metastatic Niches.


Metastasis causes most cancer-related deaths, and one poorly understood aspect 
of metastatic cancer is the adaptability of cells from a primary tumor to create 
new niches and survive in multiple, different secondary sites. We used 
quantitative mass spectrometry to analyze the extracellular matrix (ECM), a 
critical component of metastatic niches, in metastases to the brain, lungs, 
liver, and bone marrow, all derived from parental MDA-MB-231 triple-negative 
breast cancer cells. Tumor and stromal cells cooperated in forming niches; 
stromal cells produced predominantly core, structural ECM proteins and tumor 
cells produced a diverse array of ECM-associated proteins, including secreted 
factors and modulators of the matrix. In addition, tumor and stromal cells 
together created distinct niches in each tissue. Downregulation of SERPINB1, a 
protein elevated in brain metastases, led to a reduction in brain metastasis, 
suggesting that some niche-specific ECM proteins may be involved in metastatic 
tropism. SIGNIFICANCE: Tumor and stromal cells together create distinct ECM 
niches in breast cancer metastases to various tissues, providing new insight 
into how tumor cells adapt to survive in different tissue environments.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="952~978" text="Downregulation of SERPINB1" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="566~613" text="MDA-MB-231 triple-negative  breast cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1021~1059" text="led to a reduction in brain metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Downregulation of SERPINB1" contextID="C0" contextText="MDA-MB-231 triple-negative  breast cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="led to a reduction in brain metastasis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>