<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Tumor Cell-Derived Angiopoietin-2 Promotes Metastasis in Melanoma.

The angiopoietin (Angpt)-TIE signaling pathway controls vascular maturation and 
maintains the quiescent phenotype of resting vasculature. The contextual 
agonistic and antagonistic Tie2 ligand ANGPT2 is believed to be exclusively 
produced by endothelial cells, disrupting constitutive ANGPT1-TIE2 signaling to 
destabilize the microvasculature during pathologic disorders like inflammation 
and cancer. However, scattered reports have also portrayed tumor cells as a 
source of ANGPT2. Employing ISH-based detection of ANGPT2, we found strong tumor 
cell expression of ANGPT2 in a subset of patients with melanoma. Comparative 
analysis of biopsies revealed a higher fraction of ANGPT2-expressing tumor cells 
in metastatic versus primary sites. Tumor cell-expressed Angpt2 was dispensable 
for primary tumor growth, yet in-depth analysis of primary tumors revealed 
enhanced intratumoral necrosis upon silencing of tumor cell Angpt2 expression in 
the absence of significant immune and vascular alterations. Global 
transcriptional profiling of Angpt2-deficient tumor cells identified 
perturbations in redox homeostasis and an increased response to cellular 
oxidative stress. Ultrastructural analyses illustrated a significant increase of 
dysfunctional mitochondria in Angpt2-silenced tumor cells, thereby resulting in 
enhanced reactive oxygen species (ROS) production and downstream MAPK stress 
signaling. Functionally, enhanced ROS in Angpt2-silenced tumor cells reduced 
colonization potential in vitro and in vivo. Taken together, these findings 
uncover the hitherto unappreciated role of tumor cell-expressed ANGPT2 as an 
autocrine-positive regulator of metastatic colonization and validate ANGPT2 as a 
therapeutic target for a well-defined subset of patients with melanoma. 
SIGNIFICANCE: This study reveals that tumor cells can be a source of ANGPT2 in 
the tumor microenvironment and that tumor cell-derived ANGPT2 augments 
metastatic colonization by protecting tumor cells from oxidative stress.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="973~985,997~1014" text="silencing of ... Angpt2 expression" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1116~1132" text="Angpt2-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1343~1358" text="Angpt2-silenced" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1513~1528" text="Angpt2-silenced" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="986~996" text="tumor cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1133~1144" text="tumor cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1359~1370" text="tumor cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1529~1540,1573~1581" text="tumor cells ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1529~1540,1586~1593" text="tumor cells ... in vivo" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="937~967" text="enhanced intratumoral necrosis" phenotype="necrosis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1541~1572" text="reduced  colonization potential" phenotype="colony formation" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="silencing of ... Angpt2 expression" contextID="P0" contextText="silencing of ... Angpt2 expression" effectID="E0" effectText="enhanced intratumoral necrosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="Angpt2-silenced" contextID="C4" contextText="tumor cells ... in vitro" effectID="E3" effectText="reduced  colonization potential" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="Angpt2-silenced" contextID="C5" contextText="tumor cells ... in vivo" effectID="E3" effectText="reduced  colonization potential" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>