<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Protein Arginine Methyltransferase 5 Promotes pICln-Dependent Androgen Receptor 
Transcription in Castration-Resistant Prostate Cancer.

The majority of advanced prostate cancer therapies aim to inhibit androgen 
receptor (AR) signaling. However, AR reactivation inevitably drives disease 
progression to castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). Here we demonstrate 
that protein arginine methyltransferase 5 (PRMT5) functions as an epigenetic 
activator of AR transcription in CRPC, requiring cooperation with a methylosome 
subunit pICln. In vitro and in xenograft tumors in mice, targeting PRMT5 or 
pICln suppressed growth of CRPC cells. Full-length AR and AR-V7 transcription 
activation required both PRMT5 and pICln but not MEP50. This activation of 
transcription was accompanied by PRMT5-mediated symmetric dimethylation of H4R3 
at the proximal AR promoter. Further, knockdown of PRMT5 abolished the binding 
of pICln (but not vice versa) to the AR proximal promoter region, suggesting 
that PRMT5 recruits pICln to the AR promoter to activate AR transcription. 
Differential gene expression analysis in 22Rv1 cells confirmed that PRMT5 and 
pICln both regulate the androgen signaling pathway. In addition, PRMT5 and pICln 
protein expression positively correlated with AR and AR-V7 protein expression in 
CRPC tissues and their expression was highly correlated at the mRNA level across 
multiple publicly available CRPC datasets. Our results suggest that targeting 
PRMT5 or pICln may be explored as a novel therapy for CRPC treatment by 
suppressing expression of AR and AR splice variants to circumvent AR 
reactivation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="587~612" text="targeting PRMT5 or  pICln" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="881~899" text="knockdown of PRMT5" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="545~553,634~644" text="In vitro ... CRPC cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="561~577,634~644" text="xenograft tumors ... CRPC cells" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="581~585" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="613~630" text="suppressed growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="targeting PRMT5 or  pICln" contextID="C2" contextText="In vitro ... CRPC cells" effectID="E0" effectText="suppressed growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="targeting PRMT5 or  pICln" effectID="E0" effectText="suppressed growth" contextID="C4" contextText="xenograft tumors ... CRPC cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>