<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Infiltrating Mast Cell-Mediated Stimulation of Estrogen Receptor Activity in 
Breast Cancer Cells Promotes the Luminal Phenotype.

Tumor growth and development is determined by both cancer cell-autonomous and 
microenvironmental mechanisms, including the contribution of infiltrating immune 
cells. Because the role of mast cells (MC) in this process is poorly 
characterized and even controversial, we investigated their part in breast 
cancer. Crossing C57BL/6 MMTV-PyMT mice, which spontaneously develop mammary 
carcinomas, with MC-deficient C57BL/6-KitW-sh/W-sh (Wsh) mice, showed that MCs 
promote tumor growth and prevent the development of basal CK5-positive areas in 
favor of a luminal gene program. When cocultured with breast cancer cells in 
vitro, MCs hindered activation of cMET, a master regulator of the basal program, 
and simultaneously promoted expression and activation of estrogen receptor 
(ESR1/ER) and its target genes (PGR, KRT8/CK8, BCL2), which are all luminal 
markers. Moreover, MCs reduced ERBB2/HER2 levels, whose inhibition further 
increased ESR1 expression. In vivo and in silico analysis of patients with 
breast cancer revealed a direct correlation between MC density and ESR1 
expression. In mice engrafted with HER2-positive breast cancer tumors, 
coinjection of MCs increased tumor engraftment and outgrowth, supporting the 
link between MCs and increased risk of relapse in patients with breast cancer. 
Together, our findings support the notion that MCs influence the phenotype of 
breast cancer cells by stimulating a luminal phenotype and ultimately modifying 
the outcome of the disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="455~472" text="C57BL/6 MMTV-PyMT" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="546~572" text="C57BL/6-KitW-sh/W-sh (Wsh)" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="473~477" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="573~577" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="731~760" text="breast cancer cells in  vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1230~1284" text="mice engrafted with HER2-positive breast cancer tumors" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="596~616" text="promote tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="499~526" text="develop mammary  carcinomas" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1306~1347" text="increased tumor engraftment and outgrowth" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="C57BL/6 MMTV-PyMT" contextID="C0" contextText="mice" effectID="E1" effectText="develop mammary  carcinomas" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>