<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[FTO Inhibition Enhances the Antitumor Effect of Temozolomide by Targeting 
MYC-miR-155/23a Cluster-MXI1 Feedback Circuit in Glioma.

Malignant glioma constitutes one of the fatal primary brain tumors in adults. 
Such poor prognosis calls for a better understanding of cancer-related signaling 
pathways of this disease. Here we elucidate a MYC-miRNA-MXI1 feedback loop that 
regulates proliferation and tumorigenesis in glioma. MYC suppressed MXI1 
expression via microRNA-155 (miR-155) and the microRNA-23a∼27a∼24-2 cluster 
(miR-23a cluster), whereas MXI1, in turn, inhibited MYC expression by binding to 
its promoter. Overexpression of miR-155 and the miR-23a cluster promoted 
tumorigenesis in U87 glioma cells. Furthermore, fat mass and obesity-associated 
protein (FTO), an N6-methyladenosine (m6A) RNA demethylase, regulated the loop 
by targeting MYC. The ethyl ester form of meclofenamic acid (MA2) inhibited FTO 
and enhanced the effect of the chemotherapy drug temozolomide on suppressing 
proliferation of glioma cells and negatively regulated the loop. These data 
collectively highlight a key regulatory circuit in glioma and provide potential 
targets for clinical treatment. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="622~671" text="Overexpression of miR-155 and the miR-23a cluster" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="861~922" text="The ethyl ester form of meclofenamic acid (MA2) inhibited FTO" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="699~715" text="U87 glioma cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1019~1031" text="glioma cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="672~695" text="promoted  tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="928~936,989~1015" text="enhanced ... suppressing  proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of miR-155 and the miR-23a cluster" contextID="C0" contextText="U87 glioma cells" effectID="E0" effectText="promoted  tumorigenesis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="The ethyl ester form of meclofenamic acid (MA2) inhibited FTO" contextID="C1" contextText="glioma cells" effectID="E2" effectText="enhanced ... suppressing  proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>