<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Methylation of HSP70 Orchestrates Its Binding to and Stabilization of BCL2 mRNA 
and Renders Pancreatic Cancer Cells Resistant to Therapeutics.

Pancreatic cancer is a lethal disease owing to its intrinsic and acquired 
resistance to therapeutic modalities. The altered balance between pro- and 
antiapoptosis signals within cancer cells is critical to therapeutic resistance. 
However, the molecular mechanisms underlying increased antiapoptosis signals 
remain poorly understood. In this study, we report that PRMT1 expression is 
increased in pancreatic cancer tissues and is associated with higher tumor 
grade, increased aggressiveness, and worse prognosis. PRMT1 overexpression 
increased arginine methylation of HSPs of 70 kDa (HSP70); this methylation 
enhanced HSP70 binding and stabilization of BCL2 mRNA through AU-rich elements 
in 3'-untranslated region and consequentially increased BCL2 protein expression 
and protected cancer cells from apoptosis induced by cellular stresses and 
therapeutics. RNA binding and regulation function of HSP70 was involved in 
pancreatic cancer drug resistance and was dependent on protein arginine 
methylation. These findings not only reveal a novel PRMT1-HSP70-BCL2 signaling 
axis that is crucial to pancreatic cancer cell survival and therapeutic 
resistance, but they also provide a proof of concept that targeted inhibition of 
this axis may represent a new therapeutic strategy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="663~683" text="PRMT1 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="936~948" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="926~935,949~963" text="protected ... from apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="PRMT1 overexpression" contextID="C0" contextText="cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="protected ... from apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>