<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[HDAC6 Plays a Noncanonical Role in the Regulation of Antitumor Immune Responses, 
Dissemination, and Invasiveness of Breast Cancer.

Despite the outstanding clinical results of immune checkpoint blockade (ICB) in 
melanoma and other cancers, clinical trials in breast cancer have reported low 
responses to these therapies. Current efforts are now focused on improving the 
treatment efficacy of ICB in breast cancer using new combination designs such as 
molecularly targeted agents, including histone deacetylase inhibitors (HDACi). 
These epigenetic drugs have been widely described as potent cytotoxic agents for 
cancer cells. In this work, we report new noncanonical regulatory properties of 
ultra-selective HDAC6i over the expression and function of 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition pathways and the invasiveness potential of 
breast cancer. These unexplored roles position HDAC6i as attractive options to 
potentiate ongoing immunotherapeutic approaches. These new functional activities 
of HDAC6i involved regulation of the E-cadherin/STAT3 axis. Pretreatment of 
tumors with HDAC6i induced critical changes in the tumor microenvironment, 
resulting in improved effectiveness of ICB and preventing dissemination of 
cancer cells to secondary niches. Our results demonstrate for the first time 
that HDAC6i can both improve ICB antitumor immune responses and diminish the 
invasiveness of breast cancer with minimal cytotoxic effects, thus departing 
from the cytotoxicity-centric paradigm previously assigned to HDACi. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1311~1317" text="HDAC6i" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1059~1071,1083~1094" text="Pretreatment ... with HDAC6i" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1076~1082" text="tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1400~1413" text="breast cancer" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1228~1240" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1370~1396" text="diminish the  invasiveness" phenotype="invasion" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1199~1223,1241~1260" text="preventing dissemination ... to secondary niches" activity="inhibits" phenotype="metastasis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="Pretreatment ... with HDAC6i" contextID="C0" contextText="tumors" effectID="E2" effectText="preventing dissemination ... to secondary niches" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="Pretreatment ... with HDAC6i" contextID="C2" contextText="cancer cells" effectID="E2" effectText="preventing dissemination ... to secondary niches" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="HDAC6i" contextID="C1" contextText="breast cancer" effectID="E1" effectText="diminish the  invasiveness" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>