<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PHB2 (prohibitin 2) promotes PINK1-PRKN/Parkin-dependent mitophagy by the 
PARL-PGAM5-PINK1 axis.

Mitophagy, which is a conserved cellular process for selectively removing 
damaged or unwanted mitochondria, is critical for mitochondrial quality control 
and the maintenance of normal cellular physiology. However, the precise 
mechanisms underlying mitophagy remain largely unknown. Prior studies on 
mitophagy focused on the events in the mitochondrial outer membrane. PHB2 
(prohibitin 2), which is a highly conserved membrane scaffold protein, was 
recently identified as a novel inner membrane mitophagy receptor that mediates 
mitophagy. Here, we report a new signaling pathway for PHB2-mediated mitophagy. 
Upon mitochondrial membrane depolarization or misfolded protein aggregation, 
PHB2 depletion destabilizes PINK1 in the mitochondria, which blocks the 
mitochondrial recruitment of PRKN/Parkin, ubiquitin and OPTN (optineurin), 
leading to an inhibition of mitophagy. In addition, PHB2 overexpression directly 
induces PRKN recruitment to the mitochondria. Moreover, PHB2-mediated mitophagy 
is dependent on the mitochondrial inner membrane protease PARL, which interacts 
with PHB2 and is activated upon PHB2 depletion. Furthermore, PGAM5, which is 
processed by PARL, participates in PHB2-mediated PINK1 stabilization. Finally, a 
ligand of PHB proteins that we synthesized, called FL3, was found to strongly 
inhibit PHB2-mediated mitophagy and to effectively block cancer cell growth and 
energy production at nanomolar concentrations. Thus, our findings reveal that 
the PHB2-PARL-PGAM5-PINK1 axis is a novel pathway of PHB2-mediated mitophagy and 
that targeting PHB2 with the chemical compound FL3 is a promising strategy for 
cancer therapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="792~806" text="PHB2 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="993~1012" text="PHB2 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1217~1231" text="PHB2 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1342~1399" text="a  ligand of PHB proteins that we synthesized, called FL3" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1481~1492" text="cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="955~978" text="inhibition of mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1424~1431,1446~1455" text="inhibit ... mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1475~1480,1493~1499" text="block ... growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="a  ligand of PHB proteins that we synthesized, called FL3" contextID="C0" contextText="cancer cell" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibit ... mitophagy" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="a  ligand of PHB proteins that we synthesized, called FL3" contextID="C0" contextText="cancer cell" effectID="E2" effectText="block ... growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>