<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Afadin cooperates with Claudin-2 to promote breast cancer metastasis.

Claudin-2 promotes breast cancer liver metastasis by enabling seeding and early 
cancer cell survival. We now demonstrate that the PDZ-binding motif of Claudin-2 
is necessary for anchorage-independent growth of cancer cells and is required 
for liver metastasis. Several PDZ domain-containing proteins were identified 
that interact with the PDZ-binding motif of Claudin-2 in liver metastatic breast 
cancer cells, including Afadin, Arhgap21, Pdlim2, Pdlim7, Rims2, Scrib, and 
ZO-1. We specifically examined the role of Afadin as a potential 
Claudin-2-interacting partner that promotes breast cancer liver metastasis. 
Afadin associates with Claudin-2, an interaction that requires the PDZ-binding 
motif of Claudin-2. Loss of Afadin also impairs the ability of breast cancer 
cells to form colonies in soft agar and metastasize to the lungs or liver. 
Immunohistochemical analysis of Claudin-2 and/or Afadin expression in 206 
metastatic breast cancer tumors revealed that high levels of both Claudin-2 and 
Afadin in primary tumors were associated with poor disease-specific survival, 
relapse-free survival, lung-specific relapse, and liver-specific relapse. Our 
findings indicate that signaling downstream from a Claudin-2/Afadin complex 
enables the efficient formation of breast cancer metastases. Moreover, combining 
Claudin-2 and Afadin as prognostic markers better predicts the potential of 
breast cancer to metastasize to soft tissues.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="793~807" text="Loss of Afadin" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="836~856" text="breast cancer  cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="813~832,857~886" text="impairs the ability ... to form colonies in soft agar" phenotype="colony formation" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="813~832,857~859,891~924" text="impairs the ability ... to ... metastasize to the lungs or liver" phenotype="metastasis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Loss of Afadin" contextID="C0" contextText="breast cancer  cells" effectID="E0" effectText="impairs the ability ... to form colonies in soft agar" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Loss of Afadin" contextID="C0" contextText="breast cancer  cells" effectID="E1" effectText="impairs the ability ... to ... metastasize to the lungs or liver" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>