<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Identification of transcription factors that regulate ATG8 expression and 
autophagy in Arabidopsis.

Autophagy is a conserved catabolic process in eukaryotes that contributes to 
cell survival in response to multiple stresses and is important for organism 
fitness. In Arabidopsis thaliana, the core machinery of autophagy is well 
defined, but its transcriptional regulation is largely unknown. The ATG8 
(autophagy-related 8) protein plays central roles in decorating autophagosomes 
and binding to specific cargo receptors to recruit cargo to autophagosomes. We 
propose that the transcriptional control of ATG8 genes is important during the 
formation of autophagosomes and therefore contributes to survival during stress. 
Here, we describe a yeast one-hybrid (Y1H) screen for transcription factors 
(TFs) that regulate ATG8 gene expression in Arabidopsis, using the promoters of 
4 ATG8 genes. We identified a total of 225 TFs from 35 families that bind these 
promoters. The TF-ATG8 promoter interactions revealed a wide array of diverse TF 
families for different promoters, as well as enrichment for families of TFs that 
bound to specific fragments. These TFs are not only involved in plant 
developmental processes but also in the response to environmental stresses. TGA9 
(TGACG (TGA) motif-binding protein 9)/AT1G08320 was confirmed as a positive 
regulator of autophagy. TGA9 overexpression activated autophagy under both 
control and stress conditions and transcriptionally up-regulated expression of 
ATG8B, ATG8E and additional ATG genes via binding to their promoters. Our 
results provide a comprehensive resource of TFs that regulate ATG8 gene 
expression and lay a foundation for understanding the transcriptional regulation 
of plant autophagy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1386~1405" text="TGA9 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="850~861" text="Arabidopsis" experiment_type="organism" species="other" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1352~1384" text="positive  regulator of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1406~1425" text="activated autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="TGA9 overexpression" contextID="C0" contextText="Arabidopsis" effectID="E1" effectText="activated autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>