<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The rRNA m(6)A methyltransferase METTL5 is involved in pluripotency and 
developmental programs.

Covalent chemical modifications of cellular RNAs directly impact all biological 
processes. However, our mechanistic understanding of the enzymes catalyzing 
these modifications, their substrates and biological functions, remains vague. 
Amongst RNA modifications N6-methyladenosine (m6A) is widespread and found in 
messenger (mRNA), ribosomal (rRNA), and noncoding RNAs. Here, we undertook a 
systematic screen to uncover new RNA methyltransferases. We demonstrate that the 
methyltransferase-like 5 (METTL5) protein catalyzes m6A in 18S rRNA at position 
A1832 We report that absence of Mettl5 in mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs) 
results in a decrease in global translation rate, spontaneous loss of 
pluripotency, and compromised differentiation potential. METTL5-deficient mice 
are born at non-Mendelian rates and develop morphological and behavioral 
abnormalities. Importantly, mice lacking METTL5 recapitulate symptoms of 
patients with DNA variants in METTL5, thereby providing a new mouse disease 
model. Overall, our biochemical, molecular, and in vivo characterization 
highlights the importance of m6A in rRNA in stemness, differentiation, 
development, and diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="677~694" text="absence of Mettl5" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="862~878" text="METTL5-deficient" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="992~1006" text="lacking METTL5" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="698~732" text="mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs)" experiment_type="cells" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="879~883" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="987~991" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="823~860" text="compromised differentiation potential" phenotype="differentiation" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="absence of Mettl5" contextID="C0" contextText="mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs)" effectID="E0" effectText="compromised differentiation potential" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>