<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Autophagy modulates lipid metabolism to maintain metabolic flexibility for 
Lkb1-deficient Kras-driven lung tumorigenesis.

Loss of tumor suppressor liver kinase B1 (LKB1) promotes cancer cell 
proliferation but also leads to decreased metabolic plasticity in dealing with 
energy crises. Autophagy is a protective process involving self-cannibalization 
to maintain cellular energy homeostasis during nutrient deprivation. We 
developed a mouse model for Lkb1-deficient lung cancer with conditional deletion 
of essential autophagy gene Atg7 to test whether autophagy compensates for LKB1 
loss for tumor cells to survive energy crises. We found that autophagy ablation 
was synthetically lethal during Lkb1-deficient lung tumorigenesis in both tumor 
initiation and tumor growth. We further found that autophagy deficiency causes 
defective intracellular recycling, which limits amino acids to support 
mitochondrial energy production in starved cancer cells and causes 
autophagy-deficient cells to be more dependent on fatty acid oxidation (FAO) for 
energy production, leading to reduced lipid reserve and energy crisis. Our 
findings strongly suggest that autophagy inhibition could be a strategy for 
treating LKB1-deficient lung tumors.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="488~512,538~542" text="conditional deletion  of ... Atg7" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="456~470" text="Lkb1-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="585~595" text="LKB1  loss" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="704~718" text="Lkb1-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="440~455,471~482" text="mouse model for ... lung cancer" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="600~611" text="tumor cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="719~723" text="lung" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="940~960" text="starved cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="973~998" text="autophagy-deficient cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="724~737" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="767~780" text=" tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="not stated" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="Lkb1-deficient" contextID="C2" contextText="lung" effectID="E0" effectText="tumorigenesis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>