<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[miR-26 suppresses adipocyte progenitor differentiation and fat production by 
targeting Fbxl19.

Fat storage in adult mammals is a highly regulated process that involves the 
mobilization of adipocyte progenitor cells (APCs) that differentiate to produce 
new adipocytes. Here we report a role for the broadly conserved miR-26 family of 
microRNAs (miR-26a-1, miR-26a-2, and miR-26b) as major regulators of APC 
differentiation and adipose tissue mass. Deletion of all miR-26-encoding loci in 
mice resulted in a dramatic expansion of adipose tissue in adult animals fed 
normal chow. Conversely, transgenic overexpression of miR-26a protected mice 
from high-fat diet-induced obesity. These effects were attributable to a 
cell-autonomous function of miR-26 as a potent inhibitor of APC differentiation. 
miR-26 blocks adipogenesis, at least in part, by repressing expression of 
Fbxl19, a conserved miR-26 target without a previously known role in adipocyte 
biology that encodes a component of SCF-type E3 ubiquitin ligase complexes. 
These findings have therefore revealed a novel pathway that plays a critical 
role in regulating adipose tissue formation in vivo and suggest new potential 
therapeutic targets for obesity and related disorders.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="453~489" text="Deletion of all miR-26-encoding loci" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="597~633" text="transgenic overexpression of miR-26a" description="knock in" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="494~498" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="553~566" text="adult animals" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="644~648" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="784~787" text="APC" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="771~783,788~803" text="inhibitor of ... differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="813~832" text="blocks adipogenesis" phenotype="differentiation" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="transgenic overexpression of miR-26a" contextID="C3" contextText="APC" effectID="E0" effectText="inhibitor of ... differentiation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>