<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Yap/Taz promote the scavenging of extracellular nutrients through 
macropinocytosis.


The uptake of macromolecules and cellular debris through macropinocytosis has 
emerged as an important nutrient acquisition strategy of cancer cells. Genetic 
alterations commonly found in human cancers (e.g. mutations in KRAS or loss of 
PTEN) have been shown to increase macropinocytosis. To identify additional 
effectors that enable cell growth dependent on the uptake of extracellular 
proteins, pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDA) cells were selected for growth 
in medium where extracellular albumin was the obligate source of the essential 
amino acid leucine. Analysis of global changes in chromatin availability and 
gene expression revealed that PDA cells selected under these conditions 
exhibited elevated activity of the transcriptional activators Yap/Taz. Knockout 
of Yap/Taz prevented growth of PDA cells in leucine-deficient medium, but not in 
complete medium. Furthermore, constitutively active forms of Yap or Taz were 
sufficient to stimulate macropinocytosis of extracellular protein. In addition 
to promoting the uptake of plasma proteins, Yap/Taz also promoted the scavenging 
of apoptotic cell bodies and necrotic debris by PDA cells. The Yap/Taz 
transcriptional target Axl was found to be essential for cell growth dependent 
on the uptake of dead cells and cell debris. Together, these studies suggest 
that the Hippo pathway effectors Yap and Taz are important transcriptional 
regulators of endocytic nutrient uptake.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="861~881" text="Knockout  of Yap/Taz" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="983~1017" text="constitutively active forms of Yap" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="983~1013,1021~1024" text="constitutively active forms of ... Taz" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="488~532" text="pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDA) cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="747~756" text="PDA cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="902~911" text="PDA cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1241~1250" text="PDA cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="882~898,912~939" text="prevented growth ... in leucine-deficient medium" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Knockout  of Yap/Taz" contextID="C2" contextText="PDA cells" effectID="E0" effectText="prevented growth ... in leucine-deficient medium" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>