<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Comparison of tumor-associated YAP1 fusions identifies a recurrent set of 
functions critical for oncogenesis.

YAP1 is a transcriptional coactivator and the principal effector of the Hippo 
signaling pathway, which is causally implicated in human cancer. Several YAP1 
gene fusions have been identified in various human cancers and identifying the 
essential components of this family of gene fusions has significant therapeutic 
value. Here, we show that the YAP1 gene fusions YAP1-MAMLD1, YAP1-FAM118B, 
YAP1-TFE3, and YAP1-SS18 are oncogenic in mice. Using reporter assays, RNA-seq, 
ChIP-seq, and loss-of-function mutations, we can show that all of these YAP1 
fusion proteins exert TEAD-dependent YAP activity, while some also exert 
activity of the C'-terminal fusion partner. The YAP activity of the different 
YAP1 fusions is resistant to negative Hippo pathway regulation due to 
constitutive nuclear localization and resistance to degradation of the YAP1 
fusion proteins. Genetic disruption of the TEAD-binding domain of these 
oncogenic YAP1 fusions is sufficient to inhibit tumor formation in vivo, while 
pharmacological inhibition of the YAP1-TEAD interaction inhibits the growth of 
YAP1 fusion-expressing cell lines in vitro. These results highlight 
TEAD-dependent YAP activity found in these gene fusions as critical for 
oncogenesis and implicate these YAP functions as potential therapeutic targets 
in YAP1 fusion-positive tumors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="461~531" text="YAP1 gene fusions YAP1-MAMLD1, YAP1-FAM118B,  YAP1-TFE3, and YAP1-SS18" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="984~1062" text="Genetic disruption of the TEAD-binding domain of these  oncogenic YAP1 fusions" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="549~553" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1104~1111" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1223~1242" text="cell lines in vitro" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="536~545" text="oncogenic" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1080~1103" text="inhibit tumor formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1176~1195" text="inhibits the growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Genetic disruption of the TEAD-binding domain of these  oncogenic YAP1 fusions" contextID="C1" contextText="in vivo" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibit tumor formation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>