<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Acyl-CoA thioesterase 1 prevents cardiomyocytes from Doxorubicin-induced 
ferroptosis via shaping the lipid composition.

In this study, we first established the doxorubicin-induced cardiotoxicity (DIC) 
model with C57BL/6 mice and confirmed cardiac dysfunction with transthoracic 
echocardiography examination. RNA-sequencing was then performed to explore the 
potential mechanisms and transcriptional changes in the process. The metabolic 
pathway, biosynthesis of polyunsaturated fatty acid was significantly altered in 
DOX-treated murine heart, and Acot1 was one of the leading-edge core genes. We 
then investigated the role of Acot1 to ferroptosis that was reported recently to 
be related to DIC. The induction of ferroptosis in the DOX-treated heart was 
confirmed by transmission electron microscopy, and the inhibition of ferroptosis 
using Fer-1 effectively prevented the cardiac injury as well as the 
ultrastructure changes of cardiomyocyte mitochondrial. Both in vitro and in vivo 
experiments proved the downregulation of Acot1 in DIC, which can be partially 
prevented with Fer-1 treatment. Overexpression of Acot1 in cell lines showed 
noteworthy protection to ferroptosis, while the knock-down of Acot1 sensitized 
cardiomyocytes to ferroptosis by DIC. Finally, the heart tissue of αMHC-Acot1 
transgenic mice presented altered free fatty acid composition, indicating that 
the benefit of Acot1 in the inhibition of ferroptosis lies biochemically and 
relates to its enzymatic function in lipid metabolism in DIC. The current study 
highlights the importance of ferroptosis in DIC and points out the potential 
protective role of Acot1 in the process. The beneficial role of Acot1 may be 
related to its biochemical function by shaping the lipid composition. In all, 
Acot1 may become a potential treating target in preventing DIC by 
anti-ferroptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1108~1131" text="Overexpression of Acot1" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1202~1221" text="knock-down of Acot1" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1301~1323" text="αMHC-Acot1  transgenic" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="536~548" text="murine heart" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="753~758" text="heart" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="941~954" text="cardiomyocyte" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="975~983" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="988~995" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1135~1145" text="cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1234~1248" text="cardiomyocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1285~1300,1324~1328" text="heart tissue of ... mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="709~733" text="induction of ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="819~844" text="inhibition of ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1165~1190" text="protection to ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1222~1232,1249~1263" text="sensitized ... to ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of Acot1" contextID="C5" contextText="cell lines" effectID="E2" effectText="protection to ferroptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knock-down of Acot1" effectID="E3" effectText="sensitized ... to ferroptosis" contextID="C6" contextText="cardiomyocytes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>