<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[AFP promotes HCC progression by suppressing the HuR-mediated Fas/FADD apoptotic 
pathway.

Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) is a major leading cause of cancer-related death 
worldwide. Alpha fetoprotein (AFP) is reactivated in a majority of 
hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) and associated with poor patient outcomes. 
Although increasing evidence has shown that AFP can regulate HCC cell growth, 
the precise functions of AFP in hepatocarcinogenesis and the associated 
underlying mechanism remain incompletely understood. In this study, we 
demostrated that depleting AFP significantly suppressed diethylnitrosamine 
(DEN)-induced liver tumor progression in an AFP gene-deficient mouse model. 
Similarly, knocking down AFP expression inhibited human HCC cell proliferation 
and tumor growth by inducing apoptosis. AFP expression level was inversely 
associated with the apoptotic rate in mouse and human HCC specimens. 
Investigation of potential cross-talk between AFP and apoptotic signaling 
revealed that AFP exerted its growth-promoting effect by suppressing the 
Fas/FADD-mediated extrinsic apoptotic pathway. Mechanistically, AFP bound to the 
RNA-binding protein HuR, increasing the accumulation of HuR in the cytoplasm and 
subsequent inhibition of Fas mRNA translation. In addition, we found that 
inhibiting AFP enhanced the cytotoxicity of therapeutics to AFP-positive HCC 
cells by activating HuR-mediated Fas/FADD apoptotic signaling. Conclusion: Our 
study defined the pro-oncogenic role of AFP in HCC progression and uncovered a 
novel antiapoptotic mechanism connecting AFP to HuR-mediated Fas translation. 
Our findings suggest that AFP is involved in the pathogenesis and 
chemosensitivity of HCC and that blockade of AFP may be a promising strategy to 
treat advanced HCC.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="556~569" text="depleting AFP" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="659~677" text="AFP gene-deficient" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="703~731" text="knocking down AFP expression" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1306~1320" text="inhibiting AFP" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="678~689" text="mouse model" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="629~640" text="liver tumor" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="742~756" text="human HCC cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1366~1389" text="AFP-positive HCC  cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="732~741,757~770" text="inhibited ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="732~741,776~788" text="inhibited ... tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="792~810" text="inducing apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="knocking down AFP expression" contextID="C2" contextText="human HCC cell" effectID="E0" effectText="inhibited ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="knocking down AFP expression" contextID="C2" contextText="human HCC cell" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited ... tumor growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="knocking down AFP expression" contextID="C2" contextText="human HCC cell" effectID="E2" effectText="inducing apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>