<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[LncRNA LINC00998 inhibits the malignant glioma phenotype via the CBX3-mediated 
c-Met/Akt/mTOR axis.

Long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs), once considered to be nonfunctional relics of 
evolution, are emerging as essential genes in tumor progression. However, the 
function and underlying mechanisms of lncRNAs in glioma remain unclear. This 
study aimed to investigate the role of LINC00998 in glioma progression. Through 
screening using TCGA database, we found that LINC00998 was downregulated in 
glioblastoma tissues and that low expression of LINC00998 was associated with 
poor prognosis. Overexpression of LINC00998 inhibited glioma cell proliferation 
in vitro and in vivo and blocked the G1/S cell cycle transition, which exerted a 
tumor-suppressive effect on glioma progression. Mechanistically, RNA pull-down 
and mass spectrometry results showed an interaction between LINC00998 and CBX3. 
IP assays demonstrated that LINC00998 could stabilize CBX3 and prevent its 
ubiquitination degradation. GSEA indicated that LINC00998 could regulate the 
c-Met/Akt/mTOR signaling pathway, which was further confirmed by a rescue assay 
using siRNA-mediated knockdown of CBX3 and the Akt inhibitor MK2206. In 
addition, dual-luciferase assays showed that miR-34c-5p could directly bind to 
LINC00998 and downregulate its expression. Our results identified LINC00998 as a 
novel tumor suppressor in glioma, and LINC00998 could be a novel prognostic 
biomarker, providing a strategy for precision therapy in glioma patients.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="590~617" text="Overexpression of LINC00998" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1139~1171" text="siRNA-mediated knockdown of CBX3" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1180~1200" text="Akt inhibitor MK2206" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="628~639,655~663" text="glioma cell ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="628~639,668~675" text="glioma cell ... in vivo" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="765~771" text="glioma" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="618~627,640~653" text="inhibited ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="680~718" text="blocked the G1/S cell cycle transition" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="737~761" text="tumor-suppressive effect" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of LINC00998" contextID="C0" contextText="glioma cell ... in vitro" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of LINC00998" contextID="C1" contextText="glioma cell ... in vivo" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of LINC00998" contextID="C2" contextText="glioma" effectID="E3" effectText="tumor-suppressive effect" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>