<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Upregulation of CPT1A is essential for the tumor-promoting effect of adipocytes 
in colon cancer.

Colon tumors grow in an adipose tissue-enriched microenvironment. Locally 
advanced colon cancers often invade into surrounding adipose tissue with a 
direct contact with adipocytes. We have previously shown that adipocytes promote 
tumor growth by modulating cellular metabolism. Here we demonstrate that 
carnitine palmitoyltransferase I (CPT1A), a key enzyme controlling fatty acid 
oxidation (FAO), was upregulated in colon cancer cells upon exposure to 
adipocytes or fatty acids. In addition, CPT1A expression was increased in 
invasive tumor cells within the adipose tissue compared to tumors without direct 
contact with adipocytes. Silencing CPT1A abolished the protective effect 
provided by fatty acids against nutrient deprivation and reduced tumor organoid 
formation in 3D culture and the expression of genes associated with cancer stem 
cells downstream of Wnt/β-catenin. Mechanistically, CPT1A-dependent FAO promoted 
the acetylation and nuclear translocation of β-catenin. Furthermore, knockdown 
of CPT1A blocked the tumor-promoting effect of adipocytes in vivo and inhibited 
xenograft tumor initiation. Taken together, our findings identify CPT1A-depedent 
FAO as an essential metabolic pathway that enables the interaction between 
adipocytes and colon cancer cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="740~755" text="Silencing CPT1A" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1102~1121" text="knockdown  of CPT1A" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="521~539" text="colon cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="860~868,880~893" text="organoid ... in 3D culture" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1160~1178" text="adipocytes in vivo" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1194~1203" text="xenograft" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="846~859,870~879" text="reduced tumor ... formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1183~1192,1204~1220" text="inhibited ... tumor initiation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Silencing CPT1A" contextID="C1" contextText="organoid ... in 3D culture" effectID="E0" effectText="reduced tumor ... formation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knockdown  of CPT1A" contextID="C3" contextText="xenograft" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited ... tumor initiation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>