<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Exosome-transferred LINC01559 promotes the progression of gastric cancer via 
PI3K/AKT signaling pathway.

Increasing evidence indicates that long non-coding RNAs (lncRNAs) are associated 
with the progression of human cancers. However, the expression level and 
function of LINC01559 (long intergenic non-protein coding RNA 1559) in gastric 
cancer (GC) are rarely reported. Here we found that LINC01559 was upregulated in 
GC tissues based on GEPIA (Gene Expression Profiling Interactive Analysis) and 
TCGA (The Cancer Genome Atlas) databases. Also, LINC01559 was expressed at a 
lower level in GC cells than in mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs). In vitro 
experiments revealed that silencing LINC01559 remarkably hindered GC cell 
proliferation, migration and stemness. Then, we identified that LINC01559 was 
transmitted form MSCs to GC cells via the exosomes. Immunofluorescence staining 
and electron microscope validated the existence of exosomes in GC cells. 
Mechanistically, LINC01559 sponged miR-1343-3p to upregulate PGK1 
(phosphoglycerate kinase 1), therefore activating PI3K/AKT pathway. Moreover, 
LINC01559 recruited EZH2 (enhancer of zeste 2 polycomb repressive complex 2 
subunit) to PTEN (phosphatase and tensin homolog) promoter, inducing the 
methylation of PTEN promoter and finally resulting in PTEN repression. Of note, 
LINC01559 targeted both PGK1 and PTEN to promote GC progression by activating 
PI3K/AKT pathway. Taken together, our study demonstrated that LINC01559 
accelerated GC progression via upregulating PGK1 and downregulating PTEN to 
trigger phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase/AKT serine/threonine kinase (PI3K/AKT) 
pathway, indicating LINC01559 as a potential biomarker for GC treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="682~701" text="silencing LINC01559" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="646~654" text="In vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="722~729" text="GC cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="713~721,731~744" text="hindered ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="713~721,746~755" text="hindered ... migration" phenotype="migration" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="silencing LINC01559" contextID="C1" contextText="GC cell" effectID="E0" effectText="hindered ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="silencing LINC01559" contextID="C1" contextText="GC cell" effectID="E1" effectText="hindered ... migration" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>