<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[GDF11 inhibits cardiomyocyte pyroptosis and exerts cardioprotection in acute 
myocardial infarction mice by upregulation of transcription factor HOXA3.

NLRP3 (Nucleotide-binding oligomerization domain-like receptor pyrin 
domain-containing 3) inflammasome-mediated cardiomyocytes pyroptosis plays a 
crucial part in progression of acute myocardial infarction (MI). GDF11 (Growth 
Differentiation Factor 11) has been reported to generate cytoprotective effects 
in phylogenesis and multiple diseases, but the mechanism that GDF11 contributes 
to cardioprotection of MI and cardiomyocytes pyroptosis remains poorly 
understood. In our study, we first determined that GDF11 was abnormally 
downregulated in the heart tissue of MI mice and hypoxic cardiomyocytes. 
Moreover, AAV9-GDF11 markedly alleviated heart function in MI mice. Meanwhile, 
GDF11 overexpression also decreased the pyroptosis of hypoxic cardiomyocytes. 
PROMO and JASPAR prediction software found that transcription factor HOXA3 was 
predicted as an important regulator of NLRP3, and was confirmed by ChIP assay. 
Further analysis identifying GDF11 promoted the Smad2/3 pathway resulted in 
HOXA3 overexpression. Taken together, our study implies that GDF11 prevents 
cardiomyocytes pyroptosis via HOXA3/NLRP3 signaling pathway in MI mice.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="772~782" text="AAV9-GDF11" description="viral vector" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="842~862" text="GDF11 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="821~828" text="MI mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="896~918" text="hypoxic cardiomyocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="868~892" text="decreased the pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="GDF11 overexpression" effectID="E0" effectText="decreased the pyroptosis" contextID="C1" contextText="hypoxic cardiomyocytes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>