<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Disrupting the TRIB3-SQSTM1 interaction reduces liver fibrosis by restoring 
autophagy and suppressing exosome-mediated HSC activation.

Impaired macroautophagy/autophagy is involved in the pathogenesis of hepatic 
fibrosis. However, how aberrant autophagy promotes fibrosis is far from 
understood. Here, we aimed to define a previously unrevealed pro-fibrotic 
mechanism for the stress protein TRIB3 (tribbles pseudokinase 3)-mediated 
autophagy dysfunction. Human fibrotic liver tissues were obtained from patients 
with cirrhosis who underwent an open surgical repair process. The functional 
implications of TRIB3 were evaluated in mouse models of hepatic fibrosis induced 
by bile duct ligation (BDL) or thioacetamide (TAA) injection. Human fibrotic 
liver tissues expressed higher levels of TRIB3 and selective autophagic receptor 
SQSTM1/p62 (sequestosome 1) than nonfibrotic tissues and the elevated expression 
of TRIB3 and SQSTM1 was positively correlated in the fibrotic tissues. Silencing 
Trib3 protected against experimentally induced hepatic fibrosis, accompanied by 
restored autophagy activity in fibrotic liver tissues. Furthermore, TRIB3 
interacted with SQSTM1 and hindered its binding to MAP1LC3/LC3, which caused the 
accumulation of SQSTM1 aggregates and obstructed autophagic flux. The 
TRIB3-mediated autophagy impairment not only suppressed autophagic degradation 
of late endosomes but also promoted hepatocellular secretion of INHBA/Activin 
A-enriched exosomes which caused migration, proliferation and activation of 
hepatic stellate cells (HSCs), the effector cells of liver fibrosis. Disrupting 
the TRIB3-SQSTM1 interaction with a specific helical peptide exerted potent 
protective effects against hepatic fibrosis by restoring autophagic flux in 
hepatocytes and HSCs. Together, stress-elevated TRIB3 expression promotes 
hepatic fibrosis by interacting with SQSTM1 and interfering with its functions 
in liver-parenchymal cells and activating HSCs. Targeting this interaction is a 
promising strategy for treating fibroproliferative liver diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="992~1008" text="Silencing  Trib3" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="637~669" text="mouse models of hepatic fibrosis" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="461~489" text="Human fibrotic liver tissues" experiment_type="organism" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="741~770" text="Human fibrotic  liver tissues" experiment_type="organism" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1115~1137" text="fibrotic liver tissues" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1548~1577" text="hepatic stellate cells (HSCs)" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1783~1794" text="hepatocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1799~1803" text="HSCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1084~1111" text="restored autophagy activity" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1497~1513" text="caused migration" phenotype="migration" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1497~1503,1515~1528" text="caused ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1753~1778" text="restoring autophagic flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Silencing  Trib3" contextID="C3" contextText="fibrotic liver tissues" effectID="E0" effectText="restored autophagy activity" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>