<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SYK inhibition targets acute myeloid leukemia stem cells by blocking their 
oxidative metabolism.

Spleen tyrosine kinase (SYK) is an important oncogene and signaling mediator 
activated by cell surface receptors crucial for acute myeloid leukemia (AML) 
maintenance and progression. Genetic or pharmacologic inhibition of SYK in AML 
cells leads to increased differentiation, reduced proliferation, and cellular 
apoptosis. Herein, we addressed the consequences of SYK inhibition to leukemia 
stem-cell (LSC) function and assessed SYK-associated pathways in AML cell 
biology. Using gain-of-function MEK kinase mutant and constitutively active 
STAT5A, we demonstrate that R406, the active metabolite of a small-molecule SYK 
inhibitor fostamatinib, induces differentiation and blocks clonogenic potential 
of AML cells through the MEK/ERK1/2 pathway and STAT5A transcription factor, 
respectively. Pharmacological inhibition of SYK with R406 reduced LSC 
compartment defined as CD34+CD38-CD123+ and CD34+CD38-CD25+ in vitro, and 
decreased viability of LSCs identified by a low abundance of reactive oxygen 
species. Primary leukemic blasts treated ex vivo with R406 exhibited lower 
engraftment potential when xenotransplanted to immunodeficient NSG/J mice. 
Mechanistically, these effects are mediated by disturbed mitochondrial 
biogenesis and suppression of oxidative metabolism (OXPHOS) in LSCs. These 
mechanisms appear to be partially dependent on inhibition of STAT5 and its 
target gene MYC, a well-defined inducer of mitochondrial biogenesis. In 
addition, inhibition of SYK increases the sensitivity of LSCs to cytarabine 
(AraC), a standard of AML induction therapy. Taken together, our findings 
indicate that SYK fosters OXPHOS and participates in metabolic reprogramming of 
AML LSCs in a mechanism that at least partially involves STAT5, and that SYK 
inhibition targets LSCs in AML. Since active SYK is expressed in a majority of 
AML patients and confers inferior prognosis, the combination of SYK inhibitors 
with standard chemotherapeutics such as AraC constitutes a new therapeutic 
modality that should be evaluated in future clinical trials.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="584~618" text="gain-of-function MEK kinase mutant" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="623~652" text="constitutively active  STAT5A" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="900~943" text="Pharmacological inhibition of SYK with R406" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="674~749" text="R406, the active metabolite of a small-molecule SYK  inhibitor fostamatinib" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1569~1586" text="inhibition of SYK" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="811~820" text="AML cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1055~1059" text="LSCs" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1119~1142,1151~1158" text="Primary leukemic blasts ... ex vivo" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1213~1259" text="xenotransplanted to immunodeficient NSG/J mice" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="952~955,1017~1025" text="LSC ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1616~1620" text="LSCs" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="751~774" text="induces differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="779~806" text="blocks clonogenic potential" phenotype="colony formation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1032~1051" text="decreased viability" activity="decreases" phenotype="cell survival" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="R406, the active metabolite of a small-molecule SYK  inhibitor fostamatinib" contextID="C0" contextText="AML cells" effectID="E0" effectText="induces differentiation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="R406, the active metabolite of a small-molecule SYK  inhibitor fostamatinib" contextID="C0" contextText="AML cells" effectID="E1" effectText="blocks clonogenic potential" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="Pharmacological inhibition of SYK with R406" contextID="C2" contextText="LSCs" effectID="E2" effectText="decreased viability" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>