<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DEPTOR is a direct p53 target that suppresses cell growth and chemosensitivity.

DEP-domain containing mTOR-interacting protein (DEPTOR), a natural mTOR 
inhibitor, has essential roles in several processes, including cell growth, 
metabolism, apoptosis, and immunity. DEPTOR expression has been shown to be 
diversely controlled at transcriptional levels in cell- and context-specific 
manners. However, whether there is a general mechanism for the regulation of 
DEPTOR expression remains largely unknown. Here, we report that DEPTOR is a 
downstream target of the tumor suppressor, p53, whose activity is positively 
correlated with DEPTOR expression both in vitro in cell cultures and in vivo in 
mouse tissues. Mechanistically, p53 directly binds to the DEPTOR promoter and 
transactivates its expression. Depletion of the p53-binding site on the DEPTOR 
promoter by CRISPR-Cas9 technology decreases DEPTOR expression and promotes cell 
proliferation and survival by activating AKT signaling. Importantly, inhibition 
of AKT by small molecular inhibitors or genetic knockdown abrogates the 
induction of cell growth and survival induced by deletion of the p53-binding 
region on the DEPTOR promoter. Furthermore, p53, upon activation by the 
genotoxic agent doxorubicin, induces DEPTOR expression, leading to cancer cell 
resistance to doxorubicin. Together, DEPTOR is a direct p53 downstream target 
and contributes to p53-mediated inhibition of cell proliferation, survival, and 
chemosensitivity.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="810~893" text="Depletion of the p53-binding site on the DEPTOR  promoter by CRISPR-Cas9 technology" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1010~1058" text="inhibition  of AKT by small molecular inhibitors" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1010~1031,1062~1079" text="inhibition  of AKT by ... genetic knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1144~1202" text="deletion of the p53-binding  region on the DEPTOR promoter" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="935~939" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1313~1324" text="cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="926~934,941~954" text="promotes ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="926~934,959~967" text="promotes ... survival" phenotype="cell survival" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1080~1119" text="abrogates the  induction of cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1080~1089,1124~1132" text="abrogates ... survival" phenotype="cell survival" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1124~1140" text="survival induced" phenotype="cell survival" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E7" spans="1095~1119" text="induction of cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Depletion of the p53-binding site on the DEPTOR  promoter by CRISPR-Cas9 technology" contextID="C0" contextText="cell" effectID="E1" effectText="promotes ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Depletion of the p53-binding site on the DEPTOR  promoter by CRISPR-Cas9 technology" contextID="C0" contextText="cell" effectID="E2" effectText="promotes ... survival" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>