<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Impaired autophagy increases susceptibility to endotoxin-induced chronic 
pancreatitis.

Chronic pancreatitis (CP) is associated with elevated plasma levels of bacterial 
lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and we have demonstrated reduced acinar cell autophagy 
in human CP tissue. Therefore, we investigated the role of autophagy in 
experimental endotoxin-induced pancreatic injury and aimed to identify LPS in 
human CP tissue. Pancreatic Atg7-deficient mice were injected with a single 
sub-lethal dose of LPS. Expression of autophagy, apoptosis, necroptosis, and 
inflammatory markers was determined 3 and 24 h later utilizing immunoblotting 
and immunofluorescence. The presence of LPS in pancreatic tissue from mice and 
from patients and healthy controls was determined using immunohistochemistry, 
immunoblots, and chromogenic assay. Mice lacking pancreatic autophagy exhibited 
local signs of inflammation and were particularly sensitive to the toxic effect 
of LPS injection as compared to control mice. In response to LPS, Atg7Δpan mice 
exhibited enhanced vacuolization of pancreatic acinar cells, increase in TLR4 
expression coupled to enhanced expression of NF-κΒ, JNK, and pro-inflammatory 
cytokines by acinar cells and enhanced infiltration by myeloid cells (but not 
Atg7F/F controls). Cell death was enhanced in Atg7Δpan pancreata, but only 
necroptosis and trypsin activation was further amplified following LPS injection 
along with elevated pancreatic LPS. The presence of LPS was identified in the 
pancreata from all 14 CP patients examined but was absent in the pancreata from 
all 10 normal controls. Altogether, these results support a potential role for 
metabolic endotoxemia in the pathogenesis of CP. Moreover, the evidence also 
supports the notion that autophagy plays a major cytoprotective and 
anti-inflammatory role in the pancreas, and blunting metabolic 
endotoxemia-induced CP.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="420~446" text=" Pancreatic Atg7-deficient" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1025~1033" text="Atg7Δpan" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1323~1331" text="Atg7Δpan" description="conditional knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="447~451" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="833~837" text="Mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="999~1003" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1034~1038" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1076~1099" text="pancreatic acinar cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1211~1223" text="acinar cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1253~1266" text="myeloid cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C10" spans="1332~1341" text="pancreata" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1296~1319" text="Cell death was enhanced" phenotype="cell death" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1353~1364,1388~1409" text="necroptosis ... was further amplified" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="Atg7Δpan" effectID="E0" effectText="Cell death was enhanced" contextID="C10" contextText="pancreata" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>