<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Metformin alleviates hyperglycemia-induced endothelial impairment by 
downregulating autophagy via the Hedgehog pathway.

Studies regarding macroautophagic/autophagic regulation in endothelial cells 
(ECs) under diabetic conditions are very limited. Clinical evidence establishes 
an endothelial protective effect of metformin, but the underlying mechanisms 
remain unclear. We aimed to investigate whether metformin exerts its protective 
role against hyperglycemia-induced endothelial impairment through the autophagy 
machinery. db/db mice were treated with intravitreal metformin injections. Human 
umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs) were cultured either in normal glucose 
(NG, 5.5 mM) or high glucose (HG, 33 mM) medium in the presence or absence of 
metformin for 72 h. We observed an obvious inhibition of hyperglycemia-triggered 
autophagosome synthesis in both the diabetic retinal vasculature and cultured 
HUVECs by metformin, along with restoration of hyperglycemia-impaired Hedgehog 
(Hh) pathway activity. Specifically, deletion of ATG7 in retinal vascular ECs of 
db/db mice and cultured HUVECs indicated a detrimental role of autophagy in 
hyperglycemia-induced endothelial dysfunction. Pretreatment with GANT61, a Hh 
pathway inhibitor, abolished the metformin-mediated downregulation of autophagy 
and endothelial protective action. Furthermore, GLI-family (transcription 
factors of the Hh pathway) knockdown in HUVECs and retinal vasculature revealed 
that downregulation of hyperglycemia-activated autophagy by the 
metformin-mediated Hh pathway activation was GLI1 dependent. Mechanistically, 
GLI1 knockdown-triggered autophagy was related to upregulation of BNIP3, which 
subsequently disrupted the association of BECN1/Beclin 1 and BCL2. The role of 
BNIP3 in BECN1 dissociation from BCL2 was further confirmed by BNIP3 
overexpression or BNIP3 RNAi. Taken together, the endothelial protective effect 
of metformin under hyperglycemia conditions could be partly attributed to its 
role in downregulating autophagy via Hh pathway activation. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1042~1082" text="deletion of ATG7 in retinal vascular ECs" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1372~1435" text="GLI-family (transcription  factors of the Hh pathway) knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1624~1638" text="GLI1 knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1847~1868" text="BNIP3  overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1872~1882" text="BNIP3 RNAi" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="532~542" text="db/db mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="596~644" text="Human  umbilical vein endothelial cells (HUVECs)" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="915~931" text="cultured  HUVECs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1087~1097" text="db/db mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1102~1117" text="cultured HUVECs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1439~1445" text="HUVECs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="807~820,846~869" text="inhibition of ... autophagosome synthesis" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1639~1658" text="triggered autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="2022~2046" text="downregulating autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" contextID="C6" contextText="HUVECs" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="GLI1 knockdown" effectID="E1" effectText="triggered autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>