<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A20 promotes melanoma progression via the activation of Akt pathway.

Melanoma is the most life-threatening skin cancer with increasing incidence 
around the world. Although recent advances in targeted therapy and immunotherapy 
have brought revolutionary progress of the treatment outcome, the survival of 
patients with advanced melanoma remains unoptimistic, and metastatic melanoma is 
still an incurable disease. Therefore, to further understand the mechanism 
underlying melanoma pathogenesis could be helpful for developing novel 
therapeutic strategy. A20 is a crucial ubiquitin-editing enzyme implicated 
immunity regulation, inflammatory responses and cancer pathogenesis. Herein, we 
report that A20 played an oncogenic role in melanoma. We first found that the 
expression of A20 was significantly up-regulated in melanoma cell lines. Then, 
we showed that knockdown of A20 suppressed melanoma cell proliferation in vitro 
and melanoma growth in vivo through the regulation of cell-cycle progression. 
Moreover, A20 could potentiate the invasive and migratory capacities of melanoma 
cell in vitro and melanoma metastasis in vivo by promoting 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT). Mechanistically, we found that Akt 
activation mediated the oncogenic effect of A20 on melanoma development, with 
the involvement of glycolysis. What's more, the up-regulation of A20 conferred 
the acquired resistance to Vemurafenib in BRAF-mutant melanoma. Taken together, 
we demonstrated that up-regulated A20 promoted melanoma progression via the 
activation of Akt pathway, and that A20 could be exploited as a potential 
therapeutic target for melanoma treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="869~885" text="knockdown of A20" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="897~910,925~933" text="melanoma cell ... in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="939~947,955~962" text="melanoma ... in vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1086~1109" text="melanoma  cell in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1114~1122,1134~1141" text="melanoma ... in vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1520~1528" text="melanoma" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1446~1454" text="melanoma" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="886~896,911~924" text="suppressed ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="886~896,948~954" text="suppressed ... growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1034~1044,1049~1057,1072~1082" text="potentiate ... invasive ... capacities" phenotype="invasion" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1034~1044,1062~1082" text="potentiate ... migratory capacities" phenotype="migration" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1034~1044,1123~1133" text="potentiate ... metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1145~1195" text="promoting  epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of A20" contextID="C0" contextText="melanoma cell ... in vitro" effectID="E0" effectText="suppressed ... proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of A20" contextID="C2" contextText="melanoma ... in vivo" effectID="E1" effectText="suppressed ... growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>