<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Consequences of Zmat3 loss in c-MYC- and mutant KRAS-driven tumorigenesis.

TP53 is a critical tumor suppressor that is mutated in approximately 50% of 
human cancers. Unveiling the downstream target genes of TP53 that fulfill its 
tumor suppressor function is an area of intense investigation. Zmat3 (also known 
as Wig-1 or PAG608) is one such downstream target of p53, whose loss in 
hemopoietic stem cells lacking the apoptosis and cell cycle regulators, Puma and 
p21, respectively, promotes the development of leukemia. The function of Zmat3 
in tumorigenesis however remains unclear. Here, to investigate which oncogenic 
drivers co-operate with Zmat3 loss to promote neoplastic transformation, we 
utilized Zmat3 knockout mice in models of c-MYC-driven lymphomagenesis and 
KrasG12D-driven lung adenocarcinoma development. Interestingly, unlike loss of 
p53, Zmat3 germline loss had little impact on the rate of tumor development or 
severity of malignant disease upon either the c-MYC or KrasG12D oncogenic 
activation. Furthermore, loss of Zmat3 failed to rescue KrasG12D primary lung 
tumor cells from oncogene-induced senescence. Taken together, we conclude that 
in the context of c-MYC-driven lymphomagenesis or mutant KrasG12D-driven lung 
adenocarcinoma development, additional co-occurring mutations are required to 
resolve Zmat3 tumor suppressive activity.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="715~729" text="Zmat3 knockout" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="867~886" text="Zmat3 germline loss" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1042~1055" text="loss of Zmat3" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="997~1027" text="KrasG12D oncogenic  activation" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="988~993,1006~1027" text="c-MYC ... oncogenic  activation" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="730~734" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1082~1107" text="primary lung  tumor cells" species="not stated" experiment_type="transformed cell line" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="887~937" text="had little impact on the rate of tumor development" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1122~1140" text="induced senescence" phenotype="senescence" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1056~1072,1108~1112,1122~1140" text="failed to rescue ... from ... induced senescence" phenotype="senescence" activity="no effect" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="loss of Zmat3" contextID="C1" contextText="primary lung  tumor cells" effectID="E2" effectText="failed to rescue ... from ... induced senescence" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>