<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway induces autophagy-mediated 
temozolomide-resistance in human glioblastoma.

Temozolomide (TMZ) is widely used for treating glioblastoma multiforme (GBM), 
however, the treatment of such brain tumors remains a challenge due to the 
development of resistance. Increasing studies have found that TMZ treatment 
could induce autophagy that may link to therapeutic resistance in GBM, but, the 
precise mechanisms are not fully understood. Understanding the molecular 
mechanisms underlying the response of GBM to chemotherapy is paramount for 
developing improved cancer therapeutics. In this study, we demonstrated that the 
loss of DOC-2/DAB2 interacting protein (DAB2IP) is responsible for 
TMZ-resistance in GBM through ATG9B. DAB2IP sensitized GBM to TMZ and suppressed 
TMZ-induced autophagy by negatively regulating ATG9B expression. A higher level 
of ATG9B expression was associated with GBM compared to low-grade glioma. The 
knockdown of ATG9B expression in GBM cells suppressed TMZ-induced autophagy as 
well as TMZ-resistance. Furthermore, we showed that DAB2IP negatively regulated 
ATG9B expression by blocking the Wnt/β-catenin pathway. To enhance the benefit 
of TMZ and avoid therapeutic resistance, effective combination strategies were 
tested using a small molecule inhibitor blocking the Wnt/β-catenin pathway in 
addition to TMZ. The combination treatment synergistically enhanced the efficacy 
of TMZ in GBM cells. In conclusion, the present study identified the mechanisms 
of TMZ-resistance of GBM mediated by DAB2IP and ATG9B which provides insight 
into a potential strategy to overcome TMZ chemo-resistance.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="963~992" text="knockdown of ATG9B expression" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="776~779" text="GBM" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="996~1005" text="GBM cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1455~1464" text="GBM cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="791~801,807~824" text="suppressed ... induced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1006~1016,1021~1038" text="suppressed ... induced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of ATG9B expression" contextID="C1" contextText="GBM cells" effectID="E3" effectText="suppressed ... induced autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>