<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ASH2L drives proliferation and sensitivity to bleomycin and other genotoxins in 
Hodgkin's lymphoma and testicular cancer cells.

It is of clinical importance to identify biomarkers predicting the efficacy of 
DNA damaging drugs (genotoxins) so that nonresponders are not unduly exposed to 
the deleterious effects of otherwise inefficient drugs. Here, we initially 
focused on the bleomycin genotoxin because of the limited information about the 
genes implicated in the sensitivity or resistance to this compound. Using a 
whole-genome CRISPR/Cas9 gene knockout approach, we identified ASH2L, a core 
component of the H3K4 methyl transferase complex, as a protein required for 
bleomycin sensitivity in L1236 Hodgkin lymphoma. Knocking down ASH2L in these 
cells and in the NT2D1 testicular cancer cell line rendered them resistant to 
bleomycin, etoposide, and cisplatin but did not affect their sensitivity toward 
ATM or ATR inhibitors. ASH2L knockdown decreased cell proliferation and 
facilitated DNA repair via homologous recombination and nonhomologous 
end-joining mechanisms. Data from the Tumor Cancer Genome Atlas indicate that 
patients with testicular cancer carrying alterations in the ASH2L gene are more 
likely to relapse than patients with unaltered ASH2L genes. The cell models we 
have used are derived from cancers currently treated either partially (Hodgkin's 
lymphoma), or entirely (testicular cancer) with genotoxins. For such cancers, 
ASH2L levels could be used as a biomarker to predict the response to genotoxins. 
In situations where tumors are expressing low levels of ASH2L, which may allow 
them to resist genotoxic treatment, the use of ATR or ATM inhibitors may be more 
efficacious as our data indicate that ASH2L knockdown does not affect 
sensitivity to these inhibitors.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="729~748" text="Knocking down ASH2L" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="942~957" text="ASH2L knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1746~1761" text="ASH2L knockdown" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="759~764" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="776~809" text="NT2D1 testicular cancer cell line" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="968~972" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="958~967,973~986" text="decreased ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ASH2L knockdown" contextID="C2" contextText="cell" effectID="E0" effectText="decreased ... proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>