<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Targeting the NCOA3-SP1-TERT axis for tumor growth in hepatocellular carcinoma.

Hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) has a high mortality rate and lacks an effective 
therapeutic target. Elevated expression of human telomerase reverse 
transcriptase (TERT) is an important hallmark in cancers, but the mechanism by 
which TERT is activated differentially in cancers is poorly understood. Here, we 
have identified nuclear receptor coactivator-3 (NCOA3) as a new modulator of 
TERT expression and tumor growth in HCC. NACO3 specifically binds to the TERT 
promoter at the -234 to -144 region and transcriptionally activates TERT 
expression. NCOA3 promotes HCC cell growth and tumor progression in vitro and in 
vivo through upregulating the TERT signaling. Knockdown of NACO3 suppresses HCC 
cell viability and colony formation, whereas TERT overexpression rescues this 
suppression. NCOA3 interacts with and recruits SP1 binding on the TERT promoter. 
Knockdown of NCOA3 also inhibits the expression of the Wnt signaling-related 
genes but has no effect on the Notch signaling-targeting genes. Moreover, NCOA3 
is positively correlated with TERT expression in HCC tumor tissues, and high 
expression of both NCOA3 and TERT predicts a poor prognosis in HCC patients. Our 
findings indicate that targeting the NCOA3-SP1-TERT signaling axis may benefit 
HCC patients.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="752~770" text="Knockdown of NACO3" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="832~851" text="TERT overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="948~966" text="Knockdown of NCOA3" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="651~654,689~697" text="HCC ... in vitro" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="782~785" text="HCC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="651~654,702~710" text="HCC ... in  vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="642~650,655~666" text="promotes ... cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="771~781,787~801" text="suppresses ... cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="771~781,806~822" text="suppresses ... colony formation" phenotype="colony formation" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Knockdown of NACO3" contextID="C2" contextText="HCC" effectID="E3" effectText="suppresses ... cell viability" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Knockdown of NACO3" contextID="C2" contextText="HCC" effectID="E4" effectText="suppresses ... colony formation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>