<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Branched-chain amino acid aminotransferase 2 regulates ferroptotic cell death in 
cancer cells.

Ferroptosis, a form of iron-dependent cell death driven by cellular metabolism 
and iron-dependent lipid peroxidation, has been implicated as a tumor-suppressor 
function for cancer therapy. Recent advance revealed that the sensitivity to 
ferroptosis is tightly linked to numerous biological processes, including 
metabolism of amino acid and the biosynthesis of glutathione. Here, by using a 
high-throughput CRISPR/Cas9-based genetic screen in HepG2 hepatocellular 
carcinoma cells to search for metabolic proteins inhibiting ferroptosis, we 
identified a branched-chain amino acid aminotransferase 2 (BCAT2) as a novel 
suppressor of ferroptosis. Mechanistically, ferroptosis inducers (erastin, 
sorafenib, and sulfasalazine) activated AMPK/SREBP1 signaling pathway through 
iron-dependent ferritinophagy, which in turn inhibited BCAT2 transcription. We 
further confirmed that BCAT2 as the key enzyme mediating the metabolism of 
sulfur amino acid, regulated intracellular glutamate level, whose activation by 
ectopic expression specifically antagonize system Xc- inhibition and protected 
liver and pancreatic cancer cells from ferroptosis in vitro and in vivo. On the 
contrary, direct inhibition of BCAT2 by RNA interference, or indirect inhibition 
by blocking system Xc- activity, triggers ferroptosis. Finally, our results 
demonstrate the synergistic effect of sorafenib and sulfasalazine in 
downregulating BCAT2 expression and dictating ferroptotic death, where BCAT2 can 
also be used to predict the responsiveness of cancer cells to 
ferroptosis-inducing therapies. Collectively, these findings identify a novel 
role of BCAT2 in ferroptosis, suggesting a potential therapeutic strategy for 
overcoming sorafenib resistance.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="979~984,1098~1131" text="BCAT2 ... activation by  ectopic expression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1291~1330" text="inhibition of BCAT2 by RNA interference" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1193~1198,1214~1226" text="liver ... cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1203~1226" text="pancreatic cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1244~1252" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1257~1264" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1182~1191,1227~1243" text="protected ... from ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1389~1409" text="triggers ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="BCAT2 ... activation by  ectopic expression" contextID="C0" contextText="liver ... cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="protected ... from ferroptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="BCAT2 ... activation by  ectopic expression" contextID="C1" contextText="pancreatic cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="protected ... from ferroptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>