<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Drp1 modulates mitochondrial stress responses to mitotic arrest.

Antimitotic drugs are extensively used in the clinics to treat different types 
of cancer. They can retain cells in a prolonged mitotic arrest imposing two 
major fates, mitotic slippage, or mitotic cell death. While the former is 
molecularly well characterized, the mechanisms that control mitotic cell death 
remain poorly understood. Here, we performed quantitative proteomics of HeLa 
cells under mitotic arrest induced with paclitaxel, a microtubule-stabilizer 
drug, to identify regulators of such cell fate decision. We identified 
alterations in several apoptosis-related proteins, among which the mitochondrial 
fission protein Drp1 presented increased levels. We found that Drp1 depletion 
during prolonged mitotic arrest led to strong mitochondrial depolarization and 
faster mitotic cell death as well as enhanced mitophagy, a mechanism to remove 
damaged mitochondria. Our findings support a new role of Drp1 in orchestrating 
the cellular stress responses during mitosis, where mitochondrial function and 
distribution into the daughter cells need to be coordinated with cell fate. This 
novel function of Drp1 in the cell cycle becomes best visible under conditions 
of prolonged mitotic arrest.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="751~765" text="Drp1 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="450~461" text="HeLa  cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="854~866" text="mitotic cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="468~490" text="mitotic arrest induced" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="847~853,867~872" text="faster ... death" phenotype="cell death" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="884~902" text="enhanced mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Drp1 depletion" contextID="C1" contextText="mitotic cell" effectID="E1" effectText="faster ... death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>