<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[OTULIN protects the liver against cell death, inflammation, fibrosis, and 
cancer.

Methionine-1 (M1)-linked polyubiquitin chains conjugated by the linear ubiquitin 
chain assembly complex (LUBAC) control NF-κB activation, immune homoeostasis, 
and prevents tumour necrosis factor (TNF)-induced cell death. The deubiquitinase 
OTULIN negatively regulates M1-linked polyubiquitin signalling by removing the 
chains conjugated by LUBAC, and OTULIN deficiency causes OTULIN-related 
autoinflammatory syndrome (ORAS) in humans. However, the cellular pathways and 
physiological functions controlled by OTULIN remain poorly understood. Here, we 
show that OTULIN prevents development of liver disease in mice and humans. In an 
ORAS patient, OTULIN deficiency caused spontaneous and progressive steatotic 
liver disease at 10-13 months of age. Similarly, liver-specific deletion of 
OTULIN in mice leads to neonatally onset steatosis and hepatitis, akin to the 
ORAS patient. OTULIN deficiency triggers metabolic alterations, apoptosis, and 
inflammation in the liver. In mice, steatosis progresses to steatohepatitis, 
fibrosis and pre-malignant tumour formation by 8 weeks of age, and by the age of 
7-12 months the phenotype has advanced to malignant hepatocellular carcinoma. 
Surprisingly, the pathology in OTULIN-deficient livers is independent of TNFR1 
signalling. Instead, we find that steatohepatitis in OTULIN-deficient livers is 
associated with aberrant mTOR activation, and inhibition of mTOR by rapamycin 
administration significantly reduces the liver pathology. Collectively, our 
results reveal that OTULIN is critical for maintaining liver homoeostasis and 
suggest that M1-linked polyubiquitin chains may play a role in regulation of 
mTOR signalling and metabolism in the liver.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="850~884" text="liver-specific deletion of  OTULIN" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="971~988" text="OTULIN deficiency" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1307~1323" text="OTULIN-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1409~1425" text="OTULIN-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1483~1514,1516~1530" text="inhibition of mTOR by rapamycin ... administration" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="888~892" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1057~1062" text="liver" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1067~1071" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1324~1330" text="livers" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1426~1432" text="livers" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="989~997,1021~1030" text="triggers ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1128~1158" text="pre-malignant tumour formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1239~1273" text="malignant hepatocellular carcinoma" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="OTULIN deficiency" contextID="C1" contextText="liver" effectID="E0" effectText="triggers ... apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="OTULIN deficiency" contextID="C2" contextText="mice" effectID="E1" effectText="pre-malignant tumour formation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="OTULIN deficiency" contextID="C2" contextText="mice" effectID="E2" effectText="malignant hepatocellular carcinoma" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>