<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Ubiquitination of UVRAG by SMURF1 promotes autophagosome maturation and inhibits 
hepatocellular carcinoma growth.

UVRAG (UV radiation resistance associated) is an important regulator of 
mammalian macroautophagy/autophagy by interacting with BECN1, PIK3C3, and RUBCN. 
Phosphorylation of UVRAG by MTORC1 negatively regulates autophagosome maturation 
under nutrient-enriched conditions. However, how UVRAG ubiquitination is 
regulated is still unknown. Here we report that UVRAG is ubiquitinated by SMURF1 
at lysine residues 517 and 559, which decreases the association of UVRAG with 
RUBCN and promotes autophagosome maturation. However, the deubiquitinase ZRANB1 
specifically cleaves SMURF1-induced K29 and K33-linked polyubiquitin chains from 
UVRAG, thereby increasing the binding of UVRAG to RUBCN and inhibiting autophagy 
flux. We also demonstrate that CSNK1A1-mediated UVRAG phosphorylation at Ser522 
disrupts the binding of SMURF1 to UVRAG through PPxY motif and blocks UVRAG 
ubiquitination-mediated autophagosome maturation. Interestingly, ZRANB1 is 
phosphorylated at Thr35, and Ser209 residues by CSNK1A1, and this 
phosphorylation activates its deubiquitinating activity. Importantly, we provide 
in vitro and in vivo evidence that UVRAG ubiquitination at lysine residues 517 
and 559 or prevention of Ser522 phosphorylation by D4476, a CSNK1A1 inhibitor, 
enhances the lysosomal degradation of EGFR, which significantly inhibits 
hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) growth. Furthermore, UVRAG S522 phosphorylation 
levels correlate with ZRANB1 T35/S209 phosphorylation levels and poor prognosis 
in HCC patients. These findings identify a novel molecular mechanism by which 
ubiquitination and phosphorylation of UVRAG regulate its function in 
autophagosome maturation and HCC growth, encouraging further study of their 
potential therapeutic implications. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1347~1373" text="D4476, a CSNK1A1 inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1216~1224" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1229~1236" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1450~1480" text="hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC)" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1789~1792" text="HCC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="811~837" text="inhibiting autophagy  flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1793~1799" text="growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1440~1448,1481~1487" text="inhibits ... growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="D4476, a CSNK1A1 inhibitor" contextID="C2" contextText="hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC)" effectID="E3" effectText="inhibits ... growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>