<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Proteasome-dependent degradation of Smad7 is critical for lung cancer 
metastasis.

Lung cancer is one of the cancers with highest morbidity and mortality rates and 
the metastasis of lung cancer is a leading cause of death. Mechanisms of lung 
cancer metastasis are yet to be fully understood. Herein, we demonstrate that 
mice deficient for REGγ, a proteasome activator, exhibited a significant 
reduction in tumor size, numbers, and metastatic rate with prolonged survival in 
a conditional Kras/p53 mutant lung cancer model. REGγ enhanced the TGFβ-Smad 
signaling pathway by ubiquitin-ATP-independent degradation of Smad7, an 
inhibitor of the TGFβ pathway. Activated TGFβ signaling in REGγ-positive lung 
cancer cells led to diminished expression of E-cadherin, a biomarker of 
epithelial-mesenchymal transitions (EMT), and elevated mesenchymal markers 
compared with REGγ-deficient lung cancer cells. REGγ overexpression was found in 
lung cancer patients with metastasis, correlating with the reduction of 
E-Cadherin/Smad7 and a poor prognosis. Overall, our study indicates that REGγ 
promotes lung cancer metastasis by activating TGF-β signaling via degradation of 
Smad7. Thus, REGγ may serve as a novel therapeutic target for lung cancers with 
poor prognosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="329~347" text="deficient for REGγ" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="482~509" text="conditional Kras/p53 mutant" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="873~887" text="REGγ-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="324~328" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="510~527" text="lung cancer model" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="888~905" text="lung cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="398~410,436~451" text="reduction in ... metastatic rate" phenotype="metastasis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" contextID="C0" contextText="mice" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="deficient for REGγ" effectID="E0" effectText="reduction in ... metastatic rate" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>