<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Fate decision of satellite cell differentiation and self-renewal by miR-31-IL34 
axis.

Quiescent satellite cells (SCs) that are activated to produce numerous myoblasts 
underpin the complete healing of damaged skeletal muscle. How cell-autonomous 
regulatory mechanisms modulate the balance among cells committed to 
differentiation and those committed to self-renewal to maintain the stem cell 
pool remains poorly explored. Here, we show that miR-31 inactivation compromises 
muscle regeneration in adult mice by impairing the expansion of myoblasts. 
miR-31 is pivotal for SC proliferation, and its deletion promotes asymmetric 
cell fate segregation of proliferating cells, resulting in enhanced myogenic 
commitment and re-entry into quiescence. Further analysis revealed that miR-31 
posttranscriptionally suppresses interleukin 34 (IL34) mRNA, the protein product 
of which activates JAK-STAT3 signaling required for myogenic progression. IL34 
inhibition rescues the regenerative deficiency of miR-31 knockout mice. Our 
results provide evidence that targeting miR-31 or IL34 activities in SCs could 
be used to counteract the functional exhaustion of SCs in pathological 
conditions.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="555~561,603~611" text="miR-31 ... deletion" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1003~1018" text="miR-31 knockout" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="947~963" text="IL34  inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="502~512" text="adult mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="543~552" text="myoblasts" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="672~677" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1019~1023" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="679~691,726~750" text="resulting in ... re-entry into quiescence" phenotype="quiescence" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="miR-31 ... deletion" contextID="C2" contextText="cells" effectID="E0" effectText="resulting in ... re-entry into quiescence" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>