<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TXNDC12 promotes EMT and metastasis of hepatocellular carcinoma cells via 
activation of β-catenin.

Metastasis is one of the main contributors to the poor prognosis of 
hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC). However, the underlying mechanism of HCC 
metastasis remains largely unknown. Here, we showed that TXNDC12, a 
thioredoxin-like protein, was upregulated in highly metastatic HCC cell lines as 
well as in portal vein tumor thrombus and lung metastasis tissues of HCC 
patients. We found that the enforced expression of TXNDC12 promoted metastasis 
both in vitro and in vivo. Subsequent mechanistic investigations revealed that 
TXNDC12 promoted metastasis through upregulation of the ZEB1-mediated 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) process. We subsequently showed that 
TXNDC12 overexpression stimulated the nuclear translocation and activation of 
β-catenin, a positive transcriptional regulator of ZEB1. Accordingly, we found 
that TXNDC12 interacted with β-catenin and that the thioredoxin-like domain of 
TXNDC12 was essential for the interaction between TXNDC12 and β-catenin as well 
as for TXNDC12-mediated β-catenin activation. Moreover, high levels of TXNDC12 
in clinical HCC tissues correlated with elevated nuclear β-catenin levels and 
predicted worse overall and disease-free survival. In summary, our study 
demonstrated that TXNDC12 could activate β-catenin via protein-protein 
interaction and promote ZEB1-mediated EMT and HCC metastasis.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="497~527" text="enforced expression of TXNDC12" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="778~800" text="TXNDC12 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="554~562" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="567~574" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="528~547" text="promoted metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="enforced expression of TXNDC12" contextID="C0" contextText="in vitro" effectID="E0" effectText="promoted metastasis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="enforced expression of TXNDC12" contextID="C1" contextText="in vivo" effectID="E0" effectText="promoted metastasis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>