<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[GABPA is a master regulator of luminal identity and restrains aggressive 
diseases in bladder cancer.

TERT promoter mutations occur in the majority of glioblastoma, bladder cancer 
(BC), and other malignancies while the ETS family transcription factors GABPA 
and its partner GABPB1 activate the mutant TERT promoter and telomerase in these 
tumors. GABPA depletion or the disruption of the GABPA/GABPB1 complex by 
knocking down GABPB1 was shown to inhibit telomerase, thereby eliminating the 
tumorigenic potential of glioblastoma cells. GABPA/B1 is thus suggested as a 
cancer therapeutic target. However, it is unclear about its role in BC. Here we 
unexpectedly observed that GABPA ablation inhibited TERT expression, but 
robustly increased proliferation, stem, and invasive phenotypes and cisplatin 
resistance in BC cells, while its overexpression exhibited opposite effects, and 
inhibited in vivo metastasizing in a xenograft transplant model. 
Mechanistically, GABPA directly activates the transcription of FoxA1 and GATA3, 
key transcription factors driving luminal differentiation of urothelial cells. 
Consistently, TCGA/GEO dataset analyses show that GABPA expression is correlated 
positively with luminal while negatively with basal signatures. Luminal tumors 
express higher GABPA than do basal ones. Lower GABPA expression is associated 
with the GABPA gene methylation or deletion (especially in basal subtype of BC 
tumors), and predicted significantly shorter patient survival based on TCGA and 
our cohort of BC patient analyses. Taken together, GABPA dictates luminal 
identity of BC cells and inhibits aggressive diseases in BC by promoting 
cellular differentiation despite its stimulatory effect on telomerase/TERT 
activation. Given these biological functions and its frequent methylation and/or 
deletion, GABPA serves as a tumor suppressor rather than oncogenic factor in BC. 
The GABPA effect on oncogenesis is context-dependent and its targeting for 
telomerase inhibition in BC may promote disease metastasizing.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="682~696" text="GABPA ablation" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="682~687,842~856" text="GABPA ... overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="822~830" text="BC cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="900~907,922~953" text="in vivo ... in a xenograft transplant model" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="738~761" text="increased proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="738~747,773~792" text="increased ... invasive phenotypes" phenotype="invasion" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="890~899,908~921" text="inhibited ... metastasizing" phenotype="metastasis" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="GABPA ablation" contextID="C0" contextText="BC cells" effectID="E0" effectText="increased proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="GABPA ablation" contextID="C0" contextText="BC cells" effectID="E1" effectText="increased ... invasive phenotypes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="GABPA ... overexpression" contextID="C1" contextText="in vivo ... in a xenograft transplant model" effectID="E2" effectText="inhibited ... metastasizing" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>