<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The mitochondrial retrograde signaling regulates Wnt signaling to promote 
tumorigenesis in colon cancer.

Cancer cells are known to upregulate aerobic glycolysis to promote growth, 
proliferation, and survival. However, the role of mitochondrial respiration in 
tumorigenesis remains elusive. Here we report that inhibition of mitochondrial 
function by silencing TFAM, a key transcription factor essential for 
mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) replication and the transcription of mtDNA-encoded 
genes, markedly reduced tumor-initiating potential of colon cancer cells. 
Knockdown of TFAM significantly decreased mitochondrial respiration in colon 
cancer cells; however, the cellular levels of ATP remained largely unchanged as 
a result of increased glycolysis. This metabolic alteration rendered cancer 
cells highly susceptible to glucose deprivation. Interestingly, upregulation of 
glycolysis was independent of hypoxia-inducible factor-1 (HIF1) as TFAM 
knockdown cells fail to stabilize HIF1α under hypoxic conditions. Moreover, 
knockdown of TFAM results in decreased expression of genes-associated cancer 
stem cells downstream of Wnt/β-catenin signaling. Metabolic analysis reveals 
that the level of α-ketoglutarate (α-KG) was significantly upregulated in TFAM 
knockout cells. Silencing of prolyl hydroxylase domain-containing protein 2 
(PHD2), a α-KG-dependent dioxyenase, rescued the expression of target genes of 
both HIF1α and Wnt/β-catenin. Furthermore, intestinal-specific knockout of TFAM 
prevents tumor formation in Apc-mutant mouse models of colon cancer. Taken 
together, our findings identify a novel role of mitochondria-mediated retrograde 
signaling in regulating Wnt signaling and tumor initiation in colon cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="355~369" text="silencing TFAM" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="566~583" text="Knockdown of TFAM" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="950~965" text="TFAM  knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1033~1050" text="knockdown of TFAM" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1263~1277" text="TFAM  knockout" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1285~1352" text="Silencing of prolyl hydroxylase domain-containing protein 2  (PHD2)" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1469~1505" text="intestinal-specific knockout of TFAM" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="1535~1545" text="Apc-mutant" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="545~563" text="colon cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="637~656" text="colon  cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="966~971" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1278~1283" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1546~1574" text="mouse models of colon cancer" experiment_type="tumour" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1507~1531" text="prevents tumor formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P6" perturbing_actionText="intestinal-specific knockout of TFAM" effectID="E0" effectText="prevents tumor formation" contextID="C4" contextText="mouse models of colon cancer" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>