<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BAX-dependent mitochondrial pathway mediates the crosstalk between ferroptosis 
and apoptosis.

Ferroptosis is considered a distinctive form of cell death compared to other 
types of death such as apoptosis. It is known to result from iron-dependent 
accumulation of lipid peroxides rather than caspase activation. However, we 
reported recently that ferroptosis interplays with apoptosis. In this study, we 
investigated a possible mechanism of this interplay between ferroptosis and 
apoptosis. Results from our studies reveal that combined treatment of the 
ferroptotic agent erastin and the apoptotic agent TRAIL effectively disrupted 
mitochondrial membrane potential (ΔΨm) and subsequently promoted caspase 
activation. The alterations of mitochondrial membrane potential are probably due 
to an increase in oligomerization of BAX and its accumulation at the 
mitochondria during treatment with erastin and TRAIL. Interestingly, the 
combined treatment-promoted apoptosis was effectively inhibited in BAX-deficient 
HCT116 cells, but not BAK-deficient cells. These results indicate that the 
BAX-associated mitochondria-dependent pathway plays a pivotal role in 
erastin-enhanced TRAIL-induced apoptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1007~1020" text="BAX-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1044~1057" text="BAK-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1022~1034" text="HCT116 cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1058~1063" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="959~977" text="promoted apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="959~981,994~1003" text="promoted apoptosis was ... inhibited" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="BAX-deficient" contextID="C0" contextText="HCT116 cells" effectID="E1" effectText="promoted apoptosis was ... inhibited" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>