<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BST2 suppresses porcine epidemic diarrhea virus replication by targeting and 
degrading virus nucleocapsid protein with selective autophagy.

Interferon-induced BST2 (bone marrow stromal cell antigen 2) inhibits viral 
replication by tethering enveloped virions to the cell surface to restrict viral 
release and by inducing the NFKB-dependent antiviral immune response. However, 
the mechanism by which BST2 uses the selective autophagy pathway to inhibit 
viral replication is poorly understood. In this study, we showed that BST2 
expression was significantly increased during porcine epidemic diarrhea virus 
(PEDV) infection of Vero cells by IRF1 targeting its promoter. We also showed 
that BST2 suppressed PEDV replication by binding and degrading the PEDV-encoded 
nucleocapsid (N) protein. The downregulation of N protein was blocked by 
macroautophagy/autophagy inhibitors but not a proteasome inhibitor, implying 
that the N protein was degraded via the selective autophagy pathway. Both the 
BST2 and N protein interacted with the E3 ubiquitin ligase MARCHF8/MARCH8 and 
the cargo receptor CALCOCO2/NDP52, and the ubiquitination of N protein was 
necessary for the degradation of N mediated by the BST2-MARCHF8 axis. The 
knockdown of MARCHF8 or ATG5 with small interfering RNAs blocked the selective 
autophagy pathway, rescued the protein abundance of PEDV N in 293T cells, and 
prevented the inhibition of PEDV replication by BST2 in Vero cells. Together, 
our data demonstrate the novel mechanism of BST2-mediated virus restriction, in 
which BST2 recruits MARCHF8 to catalyze the ubiquitination of the PEDV N 
protein. The ubiquitinated N protein is then recognized by CALCOCO2/NDP52, which 
delivers it to autolysosome for degradation through the selective autophagy 
pathway.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1234~1254,1263~1290" text="knockdown of MARCHF8 ... with small interfering RNAs" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1234~1246,1258~1290" text="knockdown of ... ATG5 with small interfering RNAs" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="633~643" text="Vero cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1376~1386" text="293T cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1449~1459" text="Vero cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1291~1331" text="blocked the selective  autophagy pathway" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of MARCHF8 ... with small interfering RNAs" contextID="C1" contextText="293T cells" effectID="E0" effectText="blocked the selective  autophagy pathway" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of MARCHF8 ... with small interfering RNAs" contextID="C2" contextText="Vero cells" effectID="E0" effectText="blocked the selective  autophagy pathway" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of ... ATG5 with small interfering RNAs" contextID="C1" contextText="293T cells" effectID="E0" effectText="blocked the selective  autophagy pathway" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN3" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knockdown of ... ATG5 with small interfering RNAs" contextID="C2" contextText="Vero cells" effectID="E0" effectText="blocked the selective  autophagy pathway" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>