<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TNF-α-elicited miR-29b potentiates resistance to apoptosis in peripheral blood 
monocytes from patients with rheumatoid arthritis.

CD14-positive monocytes from patients with rheumatoid arthritis (RA) are more 
resistant to apoptosis, which promotes their persistence at the inflammatory 
site and thereby contributes crucially to immunopathology. We sought to 
elucidate one mechanism underlying this unique pathogenesis: resistance to 
apoptosis and the potential involvement of miR-29b in this process. 
CD14-positive peripheral blood monocytes (PBMs) from RA patients were observed 
to be resistant to spontaneous apoptosis compared to PBMs from healthy 
volunteers. Intriguingly, expression of miR-29b was significantly upregulated in 
PBMs from RA patients than those from healthy volunteers, and this upregulation 
was correlated with RA disease activity. Functionally, forced expression of the 
exogenous miR-29b in CD14-positive Ctrl PBMs conferred resistance to spontaneous 
apoptosis and Fas-induced death, thereafter enhancing the production of major 
proinflammatory cytokines in there cells. Following identification of the 
potential miR-29b target transcripts using bioinformatic algorithms, we showed 
that miR-29b could directly bind to the 3'-UTR of the high-mobility group 
box-containing protein 1 (HBP1) and inhibited its transcription in PBMs. 
Importantly, stable expression of the exogenous HBP1 in differentiated THP-1 
monocytes effectively abolished miR-29b-elicited resistance to Fas-induced 
apoptosis. Finally, among patients with RA and good clinical responses to 
immunotherapy, expression levels of miR-29b were significantly compromised in 
those treated with infliximab (a TNF-α inhibitor) but not in those treated with 
tocilizumab (a humanized mAb against the IL-6 receptor), pointing to a potential 
association between miR-29b activation and TNF-α induction. The available data 
collectively suggest that TNF-α-elicited miR-29b potentiates resistance to 
apoptosis in PBMs from RA patients via inhibition of HBP1 signaling, and testing 
patients for miR-29b/HBP1 expression ratios may provide more accurate prognostic 
information and could influence the recommended course of immunotherapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="877~920" text="forced expression of the  exogenous miR-29b" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1381~1420" text="stable expression of the exogenous HBP1" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="924~947" text="CD14-positive Ctrl PBMs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1099~1104" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1424~1455" text="differentiated THP-1  monocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="958~994" text="resistance to spontaneous  apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="958~971,1003~1016" text="resistance to ... induced death" phenotype="cell death" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1468~1477,1495~1508,1513~1531" text="abolished ... resistance to ... induced  apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="forced expression of the  exogenous miR-29b" contextID="C0" contextText="CD14-positive Ctrl PBMs" effectID="E0" effectText="resistance to spontaneous  apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="forced expression of the  exogenous miR-29b" contextID="C0" contextText="CD14-positive Ctrl PBMs" effectID="E1" effectText="resistance to ... induced death" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="stable expression of the exogenous HBP1" effectID="E2" effectText="abolished ... resistance to ... induced  apoptosis" contextID="C2" contextText="differentiated THP-1  monocytes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>