<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The pro-apoptotic ARTS protein induces neutrophil apoptosis, efferocytosis, and 
macrophage reprogramming to promote resolution of inflammation.

ARTS (Sept4_i2) is a pro-apoptotic protein and a product of the Sept4 gene. ARTS 
acts upstream of mitochondria to initiate caspase activation. ARTS induces 
apoptosis by specifically binding XIAP and allowing de-repression of active 
caspases required for Mitochondrial Outer Membrane Permeabilzation (MOMP). 
Moreover, ARTS promotes apoptosis by inducing ubiquitin-mediated degradation of 
both major anti-apoptotic proteins XIAP and Bcl-2. In the resolution phase of 
inflammation, the infiltrating leukocytes, which execute the acute innate 
response, undergo apoptosis and are subsequently cleared by phagocytic 
macrophages (i.e. efferocytosis). In this course, macrophages undergo 
reprogramming from inflammatory, to anti-inflammatory, and eventually to 
resolving macrophages that leave the injury sites. Since engulfment of apoptotic 
leukocytes is a key signaling step in macrophage reprogramming and resolution of 
inflammation, we hypothesized that a failed apoptosis in leukocytes in vivo 
would result in an impaired resolution process. To test this hypothesis, we 
utilized the Sept4/ARTS-/- mice, which exhibit resistance to apoptosis in many 
cell types. During zymosan A-induced peritonitis, Sept4/ARTS-/- mice exhibited 
impaired resolution of inflammation, characterized by reduced neutrophil 
apoptosis, macrophage efferocytosis and expression of pro-resolving mediators. 
This was associated with increased pro-inflammatory cytokines and reduced 
anti-inflammatory cytokines, secreted by resolution-phase macrophages. Moreover, 
ARTS overexpression in leukocytes in vitro promoted an anti-inflammatory 
behavior. Overall, our results suggest that ARTS is a key master-regulator 
necessary for neutrophil apoptosis, macrophage efferocytosis and reprogramming 
to the pro-resolving phenotype during the resolution of inflammation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1240~1253" text="Sept4/ARTS-/-" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1357~1370" text="Sept4/ARTS-/-" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1698~1717" text="ARTS overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1254~1258" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1301~1317" text="many  cell types" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1371~1375" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1449~1459" text="neutrophil" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1472~1482" text="macrophage" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1721~1740" text="leukocytes in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1274~1297" text="resistance to apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1441~1448,1461~1470" text="reduced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Sept4/ARTS-/-" contextID="C0" contextText="mice" effectID="E0" effectText="resistance to apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Sept4/ARTS-/-" contextID="C1" contextText="many  cell types" effectID="E0" effectText="resistance to apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Sept4/ARTS-/-" contextID="C2" contextText="mice" effectID="E1" effectText="reduced ... apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN3" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Sept4/ARTS-/-" contextID="C3" contextText="neutrophil" effectID="E1" effectText="reduced ... apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>