<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Accumulation of tissue factor in endothelial cells promotes cellular apoptosis 
through over-activation of Src1 and involves β1-integrin signalling.

Accumulation of tissue factor (TF) within cells leads to cellular apoptosis 
mediated through p38 and p53 pathways. In this study, the involvement of Src1 in 
the induction of TF-mediated cell apoptosis, and the mechanisms of Src1 
activation were investigated. Human coronary artery endothelial cell (HCAEC) 
were transfected with plasmids to express the wild-type TF (TFWt-tGFP), or a 
mutant (Ser253 → Ala) which is incapable of being released from cells 
(TFAla253-tGFP). The cells were then activated with PAR2-agonist peptide 
(SLIGKV-NH) and the phosphorylation of Src and Rac, and also the kinase activity 
of Src were assessed. Transfected cells were also pre-incubated with pp60c Src 
inhibitor, FAK inhibitor-14, or a blocking anti-β1-integrin antibody prior to 
activation and the phosphorylation of p38 as well as cellular apoptosis was 
examined. Finally, cells were co-transfected with the plasmids, together with a 
Src1-specific siRNA, activated as above and the cellular apoptosis measured. 
Activation of PAR2 lead to the phosphorylation of Src1 and Rac1 proteins at 
60 min regardless of TF expression. Moreover, Src phosphorylation and kinase 
activity was prolonged up to 100 min in the presence of TF, with a significantly 
higher magnitude when the non-releasable TFAla253-tGFP was expressed in HCAEC. 
Inhibition of Src with pp60c, or suppression of Src1 expression in cells, 
reduced p38 phosphorylation and prevented cellular apoptosis. In contrast, 
inhibition of FAK had no significant influence on Src kinase activity or 
cellular apoptosis. Finally, pre-incubation of cells with an inhibitory 
anti-β1-integrin antibody reduced both Src1 activation and cellular apoptosis. 
Our data show for the first time that the over-activation of Src1 is a mediator 
of TF-induced cellular apoptosis in endothelial cells through a mechanism that 
is dependent on its interaction with β1-integrin.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="465~530" text="transfected with plasmids to express the wild-type TF (TFWt-tGFP)" description="plasmid vector" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="465~501,538~544,609~624" text="transfected with plasmids to express ... mutant ... (TFAla253-tGFP)" description="plasmid vector" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="834~854" text="pp60c Src  inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="856~872" text="FAK inhibitor-14" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1082~1101" text="Src1-specific siRNA" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1477~1505" text="Inhibition of Src with pp60c" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1510~1540" text="suppression of Src1 expression" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="1628~1645" text="inhibition of FAK" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="412~458" text="Human coronary artery endothelial cell (HCAEC)" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="799~804" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="630~635" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1020~1025" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1469~1474" text="HCAEC" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1544~1549" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1749~1754" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1584~1593,1603~1612" text="prevented ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1650~1652,1665~1677,1711~1720" text="no ... influence on ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1801~1809,1843~1852" text="reduced  ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P5" perturbing_actionText="Inhibition of Src with pp60c" contextID="C5" contextText="cells" effectID="E0" effectText="prevented ... apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P6" perturbing_actionText="suppression of Src1 expression" contextID="C5" contextText="cells" effectID="C5" effectText="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>