<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Two-factor specification of apoptosis: TGF-β signaling acts cooperatively with 
ecdysone signaling to induce cell- and stage-specific apoptosis of larval 
neurons during metamorphosis in Drosophila melanogaster.

Developmentally regulated programmed cell death (PCD) is one of the key cellular 
events for precise controlling of neuronal population during postembryonic 
development of the central nervous system. Previously we have shown that a group 
of corazonin-producing peptidergic neurons (vCrz) undergo apoptosis in response 
to ecdysone signaling via ecdysone receptor (EcR)-B isoforms and Ultraspiracle 
during early phase of metamorphosis. Further utilizing genetic, transgenic, and 
mosaic analyses, we have found that TGF-β signaling mediated by a glia-produced 
ligand, Myoglianin, type-I receptor Baboon (particularly Babo-A isoform) and 
dSmad2, is also required autonomously for PCD of the vCrz neurons. Our studies 
show that TGF-β signaling is not acting epistatically to EcR or vice versa. We 
also show that ectopic expression of a constitutively active phosphomimetic form 
of dSmad2 (dSmad2PM) is capable of inducing premature death of vCrz neurons in 
larva but not other larval neurons. Intriguingly, the dSmad2PM-mediated killing 
is completely suppressed by coexpression of a dominant-negative form of EcR 
(EcRDN), suggesting that EcR function is required for the proapoptotic dSmad2PM 
function. Based on these data, we suggest that TGF-β and ecdysone signaling 
pathways act cooperatively to induce vCrz neuronal PCD. We propose that this 
type of two-factor authentication is a key developmental strategy to ensure the 
timely PCD of specific larval neurons during metamorphosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1029~1116" text="ectopic expression of a constitutively active phosphomimetic form  of dSmad2 (dSmad2PM)" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1285~1341" text="coexpression of a dominant-negative form of EcR  (EcRDN)" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1159~1181" text="vCrz neurons in  larva" experiment_type="cells" species="fly" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1131~1139,1150~1155" text="inducing ... death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="ectopic expression of a constitutively active phosphomimetic form  of dSmad2 (dSmad2PM)" contextID="C0" contextText="vCrz neurons in  larva" effectID="E0" effectText="inducing ... death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>