<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Combination of a p53-activating CP-31398 and an MDM2 or a FAK inhibitor produces 
growth suppressive effects in mesothelioma with wild-type p53 genotype.

A majority of mesothelioma had the wild-type p53 genotype but was defective of 
p53 functions primarily due to a genetic defect in INK4A/ARF region. We examined 
a growth suppressive activity of CP-31398 which was developed to restore the p53 
functions irrespective of the genotype in mesothelioma with wild-type or mutated 
p53. CP-31398 up-regulated p53 levels in cells with wild-type p53 genotype but 
induced cell growth suppression in a p53-independent manner. In contrasts, 
nutlin-3a, an MDM2 inhibitor, increased p53 and p21 levels in mesothelioma with 
the wild-type p53 genotype and produced growth suppressive effects. We 
investigated a combinatory effect of CP-31398 and nutlin-2a and found the 
combination produced synergistic growth inhibition in mesothelioma with the 
wild-type p53 but not with mutated p53. Western blot analysis showed that the 
combination increased p53 and the phosphorylation levels greater than treatments 
with the single agent, augmented cleavages of PARP and caspase-3, and decreased 
phosphorylated FAK levels. Combination of CP-31398 and defactinib, a FAK 
inhibitor, also achieved synergistic inhibitory effects and increased p53 with 
FAK dephosphorylation levels greater than the single treatment. These data 
indicated that a p53-activating CP-31398 achieved growth inhibitory effects in 
combination with a MDM2 or a FAK inhibitor and suggested a possible reciprocal 
pathway between p53 elevation and FAK inactivation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="637~665" text="nutlin-3a, an MDM2 inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="969~980" text="mutated p53" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1239~1267" text="defactinib, a FAK  inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1513~1517,1527~1536" text="MDM2 ... inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1523~1536" text="FAK inhibitor" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="522~527" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="699~711" text="mesothelioma" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="919~931" text="mesothelioma" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="561~592" text="induced cell growth suppression" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="749~784" text="produced growth suppressive effects" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="898~915" text="growth inhibition" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1464~1489" text="growth inhibitory effects" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="nutlin-3a, an MDM2 inhibitor" contextID="C1" contextText="mesothelioma" effectID="E1" effectText="produced growth suppressive effects" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>