<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Deubiquitylatinase inhibitor b-AP15 induces c-Myc-Noxa-mediated apoptosis in 
esophageal squamous cell carcinoma.

Esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC) is one of the most malignant tumors in 
east Asia. However, the molecular mechanism underlying its progression remains 
unclear. The ubiquitin-proteasome system (UPS) is a central mechanism for 
protein degradation and turnover. Accumulating evidence showed that more and 
more deubiquitinases could serve as attractive anti-cancer target. The 
expression of USP14 and UCH37 in esophagus squamous cell carcinoma tissues were 
examined by immunohistochemistry and western blot assays. Effect of b-AP15, a 
USP14 and UCH37 inhibitor, on ESCC cell growth was evaluated by cell viability 
assay. After cell lines being treated with b-AP15, cell cycle, apoptosis and the 
expression of related proteins were further explored to investigate the 
anti-ESCC mechanism of b-AP15. Results showed that deubiquitinating enzymes 
(DUBs) USP14 and UCH37 expressed at higher levels in ESCC tissues than in 
adjacent tissues. b-AP15 could inhibit cell proliferation and induce G2/M cell 
cycle arrest and apoptosis in ESCC cells. Mechanistically, b-AP15 treatment 
triggered Noxa-dependent apoptosis, which was regulated by c-Myc. Silencing Noxa 
and c-Myc could reduce b-AP15-induced apoptosis in ESCC cells. Our results 
revealed a novel mechanism of anti-tumor activity of b-AP15 in ESCC, and b-AP15 
could be used as a potential therapeutic agent in ESCC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1272~1297" text="Silencing Noxa  and c-Myc" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="755~765" text="cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1088~1092" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1159~1169" text="ESCC cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1339~1349" text="ESCC cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1080~1087,1093~1106" text="inhibit ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1111~1141" text="induce G2/M cell  cycle arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1111~1117,1146~1155" text="induce ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1206~1215,1231~1240" text="triggered ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1304~1310,1318~1335" text="reduce ... induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Silencing Noxa  and c-Myc" contextID="C3" contextText="ESCC cells" effectID="C3" effectText="ESCC cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>