<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Differential regulation of autophagy during metabolic stress in astrocytes and 
neurons.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is a key homeostatic process that targets cytoplasmic 
components to the lysosome for breakdown and recycling. Autophagy plays critical 
roles in glia and neurons that affect development, functionality, and viability 
of the nervous system. The mechanisms that regulate autophagy in glia and 
neurons, however, are poorly understood. Here, we define the molecular 
underpinnings of autophagy in primary cortical astrocytes in response to 
metabolic stress, and perform a comparative study in primary hippocampal 
neurons. We find that inducing metabolic stress by nutrient deprivation or 
pharmacological inhibition of MTOR (mechanistic target of rapamycin kinase) 
robustly activates autophagy in astrocytes. While both paradigms of metabolic 
stress dampen MTOR signaling, they affect the autophagy pathway differently. 
Further, we find that starvation-induced autophagic flux is dependent on the 
buffering system of the starvation solution. Lastly, starvation conditions that 
strongly activate autophagy in astrocytes have less pronounced effects on 
autophagy in neurons. Combined, our study reveals the complexity of regulating 
autophagy in different paradigms of metabolic stress, as well as in different 
cell types of the brain. Our findings raise important implications for how 
neurons and glia may collaborate to maintain homeostasis in the brain.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="704~779" text="pharmacological inhibition of MTOR (mechanistic target of rapamycin kinase)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="510~536" text="primary cortical astrocyte" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="607~635" text="primary hippocampal  neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="813~823" text="astrocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1128~1138" text="astrocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1185~1192" text="neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="790~809" text="activates autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="971~994" text="induced autophagic flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1106~1124" text="activate autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1160~1181" text="effects on  autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="regulates" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="pharmacological inhibition of MTOR (mechanistic target of rapamycin kinase)" contextID="C2" contextText="astrocytes" effectID="E0" effectText="activates autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>