<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[
PAQR3 suppresses the growth of non-small cell lung cancer cells via modulation 
of EGFR-mediated autophagy.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is an evolutionarily conserved intracellular process 
that recycles and degrades intracellular components to sustain homeostasis in 
response to deficiency of nutrients or growth factors. PAQR3 is a newly 
discovered tumor suppressor that also regulates autophagy induced by nutrient 
starvation via AMPK and MTORC1 signaling pathways. In this study, we 
investigated whether PAQR3 modulates EGFR-mediated autophagy and whether such 
regulation is associated with the tumor suppressive activity of PAQR3. PAQR3 is 
able to inhibit the in vitro and in vivo growth of non-small cell lung cancer 
(NSCLC) cells. PAQR3 potentiates autophagy induced by EGFR inhibitor erlotinib. 
Knockdown of PAQR3 abrogates erlotinib-mediated reduction of BECN1 interaction 
with autophagy inhibitory proteins RUBCN/Rubicon and BCL2. PAQR3 blocks the 
interaction of BECN1 with the activated form of EGFR and inhibits tyrosine 
phosphorylation of BECN1. Furthermore, inhibition of autophagy by knocking down 
ATG7 abrogates the tumor suppressive activity of PAQR3 in NSCLC cells. 
Collectively, these data indicate that PAQR3 suppresses tumor progression of 
NSCLC cells through modulating EGFR-regulated autophagy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="810~828" text="Knockdown of PAQR3" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1109~1128" text="knocking down  ATG7" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="670~678,701~742" text="in vitro ... non-small cell lung cancer  (NSCLC) cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="683~690,701~742" text="in vivo ... non-small cell lung cancer  (NSCLC) cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1182~1193" text="NSCLC cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1274~1285" text="NSCLC cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="658~665,691~697" text="inhibit ... growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1082~1105" text="inhibition of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1241~1269" text="suppresses tumor progression" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="knocking down  ATG7" contextID="C2" contextText="NSCLC cells" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibition of autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>