<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[AMPK activation does not enhance autophagy in neurons in contrast to MTORC1 
inhibition: different impact on β-amyloid clearance.

The physiological AKT-MTORC1 and AMPK signaling pathways are considered key 
nodes in the regulation of anabolism-catabolism, and particularly of 
macroautophagy/autophagy. Indeed, it is reported that these are altered 
processes in neurodegenerative proteinopathies such as Alzheimer disease (AD), 
mainly characterized by deposits of β-amyloid (Aβ) and hyperphosphorylated MAPT. 
These accumulations disrupt the optimal neuronal proteostasis, and hence, the 
recovery/enhancement of autophagy has been proposed as a therapeutic approach 
against these proteinopathies. The purpose of the present study was to 
characterize the modulation of autophagy by MTORC1 and AMPK signaling pathways 
in the highly specialized neurons, as well as their repercussions on Aβ 
production. Using a double transgenic mice model of AD, we demonstrated that 
MTORC1 inhibition, either in vivo or ex vivo (primary neuronal cultures), was 
able to reduce amyloid secretion through moderate autophagy induction in 
neurons. The pharmacological prevention of autophagy in neurons augmented the Aβ 
secretion and reversed the effect of rapamycin, confirming the 
anti-amyloidogenic effects of autophagy in neurons. Inhibition of AMPK with 
compound C generated the expected decrease in autophagy induction, though 
surprisingly did not increase the Aβ secretion. In contrast, increased activity 
of AMPK with metformin, AICAR, 2DG, or by gene overexpression did not enhance 
autophagy but had different effects on Aβ secretion: whereas metformin and 2DG 
diminished the secreted Aβ levels, AICAR and PRKAA1/AMPK gene overexpression 
increased them. We conclude that AMPK has a significantly different role in 
primary neurons than in other reported cells, lacking a direct effect on 
autophagy-dependent amyloidosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="974~991" text="MTORC1 inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1325~1360" text="Inhibition of AMPK with  compound C" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1509~1513,1548~1567" text="AMPK ... gene overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1710~1741" text="PRKAA1/AMPK gene overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="934~944" text="mice model" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1000~1007" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1011~1046" text="ex vivo (primary neuronal cultures)" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1127~1134" text="neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1316~1323" text="neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1820~1835" text="primary neurons" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1103~1122" text="autophagy induction" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1384~1415" text="decrease in autophagy induction" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1568~1594" text="did not enhance  autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="no effect" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="MTORC1 inhibition" contextID="C1" contextText="in vivo" effectID="E0" effectText="autophagy induction" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="MTORC1 inhibition" contextID="C2" contextText="ex vivo (primary neuronal cultures)" effectID="E0" effectText="autophagy induction" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="MTORC1 inhibition" contextID="C3" contextText="neurons" effectID="E0" effectText="autophagy induction" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>