<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Podocytes maintain high basal levels of autophagy independent of mtor signaling.

While constant basal levels of macroautophagy/autophagy are a prerequisite to 
preserve long-lived podocytes at the filtration barrier, MTOR regulates at the 
same time podocyte size and compensatory hypertrophy. Since MTOR is known to 
generally suppress autophagy, the apparently independent regulation of these two 
key pathways of glomerular maintenance remained puzzling. We now report that 
long-term genetic manipulation of MTOR activity does in fact not influence high 
basal levels of autophagy in podocytes either in vitro or in vivo. Instead we 
present data showing that autophagy in podocytes is mainly controlled by 
AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) and ULK1 (unc-51 like kinase 1). 
Pharmacological inhibition of MTOR further shows that the uncoupling of MTOR 
activity and autophagy is time dependent. Together, our data reveal a novel and 
unexpected cell-specific mechanism, which permits concurrent MTOR activity as 
well as high basal autophagy rates in podocytes. Thus, these data indicate 
manipulation of the AMPK-ULK1 axis rather than inhibition of MTOR as a promising 
therapeutic intervention to enhance autophagy and preserve podocyte homeostasis 
in glomerular diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="489~526" text="genetic manipulation of MTOR activity" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="783~817" text="Pharmacological inhibition of MTOR" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="589~598,606~614" text="podocytes ... in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="588~598,618~625" text=" podocytes ... in vivo" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="527~531,540~553,576~585" text="does ... not influence ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="no effect" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="genetic manipulation of MTOR activity" contextID="C0" contextText="podocytes ... in vitro" effectID="E0" effectText="does ... not influence ... autophagy" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="genetic manipulation of MTOR activity" contextID="C1" contextText=" podocytes ... in vivo" effectID="E0" effectText="does ... not influence ... autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>