<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[De novo phosphatidylcholine synthesis is required for autophagosome membrane 
formation and maintenance during autophagy.

Macroautophagy/autophagy can enable cancer cells to withstand cellular stress 
and maintain bioenergetic homeostasis by sequestering cellular components into 
newly formed double-membrane vesicles destined for lysosomal degradation, 
potentially affecting the efficacy of anti-cancer treatments. Using 13C-labeled 
choline and 13C-magnetic resonance spectroscopy and western blotting, we show 
increased de novo choline phospholipid (ChoPL) production and activation of 
PCYT1A (phosphate cytidylyltransferase 1, choline, alpha), the rate-limiting 
enzyme of phosphatidylcholine (PtdCho) synthesis, during autophagy. We also 
discovered that the loss of PCYT1A activity results in compromised autophagosome 
formation and maintenance in autophagic cells. Direct tracing of ChoPLs with 
fluorescence and immunogold labeling imaging revealed the incorporation of newly 
synthesized ChoPLs into autophagosomal membranes, endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and 
mitochondria during anticancer drug-induced autophagy. Significant increase in 
the colocalization of fluorescence signals from the newly synthesized ChoPLs and 
mCherry-MAP1LC3/LC3 (microtubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3) was also 
found on autophagosomes accumulating in cells treated with autophagy-modulating 
compounds. Interestingly, cells undergoing active autophagy had an altered ChoPL 
profile, with longer and more unsaturated fatty acid/alcohol chains detected. 
Our data suggest that de novo synthesis may be required to increase 
autophagosomal ChoPL content and alter its composition, together with replacing 
phospholipids consumed from other organelles during autophagosome formation and 
turnover. This addiction to de novo ChoPL synthesis and the critical role of 
PCYT1A may lead to development of agents targeting autophagy-induced drug 
resistance. In addition, fluorescence imaging of choline phospholipids could 
provide a useful way to visualize autophagosomes in cells and tissues.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="769~792" text="loss of PCYT1A activity" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="871~876" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1354~1359" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="804~840" text="compromised autophagosome  formation" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1109~1126" text="induced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="loss of PCYT1A activity" contextID="C0" contextText="cells" effectID="E0" effectText="compromised autophagosome  formation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>