<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[USP33 deubiquitinates PRKN/parkin and antagonizes its role in mitophagy.

PRKN/parkin activation through phosphorylation of its ubiquitin and 
ubiquitin-like domain by PINK1 is critical in mitophagy induction for 
eliminating the damaged mitochondria. Deubiquitinating enzymes (DUBs) 
functionally reversing PRKN ubiquitination are critical in controlling the 
magnitude of PRKN-mediated mitophagy process. However, potential DUBs that 
directly target PRKN and antagonize its pro-mitophagy effect remains to be 
identified and characterized. Here, we demonstrated that USP33/VDU1 is localized 
at the outer membrane of mitochondria and serves as a PRKN DUB through their 
interaction. Cellular and in vitro assays illustrated that USP33 deubiquitinates 
PRKN in a DUB activity-dependent manner. USP33 prefers to remove K6, K11, K48 
and K63-linked ubiquitin conjugates from PRKN, and deubiquitinates PRKN mainly 
at Lys435. Mutation of this site leads to a significantly decreased level of 
K63-, but not K48-linked PRKN ubiquitination. USP33 deficiency enhanced both 
K48- and K63-linked PRKN ubiquitination, but only K63-linked PRKN ubiquitination 
was significantly increased under mitochondrial depolarization. Further, USP33 
knockdown increased both PRKN protein stabilization and its translocation to 
depolarized mitochondria leading to the enhancement of mitophagy. Moreover, 
USP33 silencing protects SH-SY5Y human neuroblastoma cells from the neurotoxin 
MPTP-induced apoptotic cell death. Our findings convincingly demonstrate that 
USP33 is a novel PRKN deubiquitinase antagonizing its regulatory roles in 
mitophagy and SH-SY5Y neuron-like cell survival. Thus, USP33 inhibition may 
represents an attractive new therapeutic strategy for PD patients.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1038~1054" text="USP33 deficiency" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1225~1241" text="USP33  knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1387~1402" text="USP33 silencing" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1412~1445" text="SH-SY5Y human neuroblastoma cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1350~1374" text="enhancement of mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1403~1411,1446~1450,1480~1500" text="protects ... from ... apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="USP33 silencing" effectID="E1" effectText="protects ... from ... apoptotic cell death" contextID="C0" contextText="SH-SY5Y human neuroblastoma cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>