<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Multiomic Analysis of Subtype Evolution and Heterogeneity in High-Grade Serous 
Ovarian Carcinoma.

Multiple studies have identified transcriptome subtypes of high-grade serous 
ovarian carcinoma (HGSOC), but their interpretation and translation are 
complicated by tumor evolution and polyclonality accompanied by extensive 
accumulation of somatic aberrations, varying cell type admixtures, and different 
tissues of origin. In this study, we examined the chronology of HGSOC subtype 
evolution in the context of these factors using a novel integrative analysis of 
absolute copy-number analysis and gene expression in The Cancer Genome Atlas 
complemented by single-cell analysis of six independent tumors. Tumor purity, 
ploidy, and subclonality were reliably inferred from different genomic 
platforms, and these characteristics displayed marked differences between 
subtypes. Genomic lesions associated with HGSOC subtypes tended to be subclonal, 
implying subtype divergence at later stages of tumor evolution. Subclonality of 
recurrent HGSOC alterations was evident for proliferative tumors, characterized 
by extreme genomic instability, absence of immune infiltration, and greater 
patient age. In contrast, differentiated tumors were characterized by largely 
intact genome integrity, high immune infiltration, and younger patient age. 
Single-cell sequencing of 42,000 tumor cells revealed widespread heterogeneity 
in tumor cell type composition that drove bulk subtypes but demonstrated a lack 
of intrinsic subtypes among tumor epithelial cells. Our findings prompt the 
dismissal of discrete transcriptome subtypes for HGSOC and replacement by a more 
realistic model of continuous tumor development that includes mixtures of 
subclones, accumulation of somatic aberrations, infiltration of immune and 
stromal cells in proportions correlated with tumor stage and tissue of origin, 
and evolution between properties previously associated with discrete subtypes. 
SIGNIFICANCE: This study infers whether transcriptome-based groupings of tumors 
differentiate early in carcinogenesis and are, therefore, appropriate targets 
for therapy and demonstrates that this is not the case for HGSOC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>