<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A Tissue-Engineered 3D Microvessel Model Reveals the Dynamics of Mosaic Vessel 
Formation in Breast Cancer.

In solid tumors, vascular structure and function varies from the core to the 
periphery. This structural heterogeneity has been proposed to influence the 
mechanisms by which tumor cells enter the circulation. Blood vessels exhibit 
regional defects in endothelial coverage, which can result in cancer cells 
directly exposed to flow and potentially promoting intravasation. Consistent 
with prior reports, we observed in human breast tumors and in a mouse model of 
breast cancer that approximately 6% of vessels consisted of both endothelial 
cells and tumor cells, so-called mosaic vessels. Due, in part, to the challenges 
associated with observing tumor-vessel interactions deep within tumors in 
real-time, the mechanisms by which mosaic vessels form remain incompletely 
understood. We developed a tissue-engineered model containing a physiologically 
realistic microvessel in coculture with mammary tumor organoids. This approach 
allows real-time and quantitative assessment of tumor-vessel interactions under 
conditions that recapitulate many in vivo features. Imaging revealed that tumor 
organoids integrate into the endothelial cell lining, resulting in mosaic 
vessels with gaps in the basement membrane. While mosaic vessel formation was 
the most frequently observed interaction, tumor organoids also actively 
constricted and displaced vessels. Furthermore, intravasation of cancer cell 
clusters was observed following the formation of a mosaic vessel. Taken 
together, our data reveal that cancer cells can rapidly reshape, destroy, or 
integrate into existing blood vessels, thereby affecting oxygenation, perfusion, 
and systemic dissemination. Our novel assay also enables future studies to 
identify targetable mechanisms of vascular recruitment and intravasation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>