<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Caspase-3 and caspase-8 expression in breast cancer: caspase-3 is associated 
with survival.

Impaired apoptosis is one of the hallmarks of cancer. Caspase-3 and -8 are key 
regulators of the apoptotic response and have been shown to interact with the 
calpain family, a group of cysteine proteases, during tumorigenesis. The current 
study sought to investigate the prognostic potential of caspase-3 and -8 in 
breast cancer, as well as the prognostic value of combinatorial caspase and 
calpain expression. A large cohort (n = 1902) of early stage invasive breast 
cancer patients was used to explore the expression of caspase-3 and -8. Protein 
expression was examined using standard immunohistochemistry on tissue 
microarrays. High caspase-3 expression, but not caspase-8, is significantly 
associated with adverse breast cancer-specific survival (P = 0.008 and 
P = 0.056, respectively). Multivariate analysis showed that caspase-3 remained 
an independent factor when confounding factors were included (hazard ratio (HR) 
1.347, 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.086-1.670; P = 0.007). The analyses in 
individual subgroups demonstrated the significance of caspase-3 expression in 
clinical outcomes in receptor positive (ER, PR or HER2) subgroups (P = 0.001) 
and in non-basal like subgroup (P = 0.029). Calpain expression had been 
previously assessed. Significant association was also found between high 
caspase-3/high calpain-1 and breast cancer-specific survival in the total 
patient cohort (P = 0.005) and basal-like subgroup (P = 0.034), as indicated by 
Kaplan-Meier analysis. Caspase-3 expression is associated with adverse breast 
cancer-specific survival in breast cancer patients, and provides additional 
prognostic values in distinct phenotypes. Combinatorial caspase and calpain 
expression can predict worse prognosis, especially in basal-like phenotypes. The 
findings warrant further validation studies in independent multi-centre patient 
cohorts.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>