<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Extracellular Vesicles from Cancer-Associated Fibroblasts Containing Annexin A6 
Induces FAK-YAP Activation by Stabilizing β1 Integrin, Enhancing Drug 
Resistance.

Extracellular vesicles (EV) from cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAF) are 
composed of diverse payloads. Although CAFs impact the aggressive 
characteristics of gastric cancer cells, the contribution of CAF-EV to gastric 
cancer progression has not been elucidated. Here, we investigated the molecular 
mechanism of the changes in gastric cancer characteristics induced by CAF-EV. 
CAF abundance in gastric cancer tissues was associated with poor prognosis of 
patients with gastric cancer receiving chemotherapy. Moreover, CAF-EV induced 
tubular network formation and drug resistance of gastric cancer cells in the 
extracellular matrix (ECM). Comprehensive proteomic analysis of CAF-EV 
identified that Annexin A6 plays a pivotal role in network formation and drug 
resistance of gastric cancer cells in the ECM via activation of β1 
integrin-focal adhesion kinase (FAK)-YAP. A peritoneal metastasis mouse model 
revealed that CAF-EV induced drug resistance in peritoneal tumors, and 
inhibition of FAK or YAP efficiently attenuated gastric cancer drug resistance 
in vitro and in vivo. These findings demonstrate that drug resistance is 
conferred by Annexin A6 in CAF-EV and provide a potential avenue for overcoming 
gastric cancer drug resistance through the inhibition of FAK-YAP signaling in 
combination with conventional chemotherapeutics.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1152~1169" text="inhibition of FAK" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1152~1165,1173~1176" text="inhibition of ... YAP" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="753~773" text="gastric cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1045~1078" text="peritoneal metastasis mouse model" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1128~1145" text="peritoneal tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1200~1214,1232~1240" text="gastric cancer ... in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1200~1214,1245~1252" text="gastric cancer ... in vivo" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>