<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Replication Gaps Underlie BRCA Deficiency and Therapy Response.

Defects in DNA repair and the protection of stalled DNA replication forks are 
thought to underlie the chemosensitivity of tumors deficient in the hereditary 
breast cancer genes BRCA1 and BRCA2 (BRCA). Challenging this assumption are 
recent findings that indicate chemotherapies, such as cisplatin used to treat 
BRCA-deficient tumors, do not initially cause DNA double-strand breaks (DSB). 
Here, we show that ssDNA replication gaps underlie the hypersensitivity of 
BRCA-deficient cancer and that defects in homologous recombination (HR) or fork 
protection (FP) do not. In BRCA-deficient cells, ssDNA gaps developed because 
replication was not effectively restrained in response to stress. Gap 
suppression by either restoration of fork restraint or gap filling conferred 
therapy resistance in tissue culture and BRCA patient tumors. In contrast, 
restored FP and HR could be uncoupled from therapy resistance when gaps were 
present. Moreover, DSBs were not detected after therapy when apoptosis was 
inhibited, supporting a framework in which DSBs are not directly induced by 
genotoxic agents, but rather are induced from cell death nucleases and are not 
fundamental to the mechanism of action of genotoxic agents. Together, these data 
indicate that ssDNA replication gaps underlie the BRCA cancer phenotype, 
"BRCAness," and we propose they are fundamental to the mechanism of action of 
genotoxic chemotherapies.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="643~657" text="BRCA-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="658~663" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="866~880" text="tissue culture" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="885~904" text="BRCA patient tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="human" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>