<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SUMOylation of E2F1 Regulates Expression of EZH2.

Elevated expression of EZH2, the enzymatic subunit of polycomb repressive 
complex 2 (PRC2), often occurs in cancer. EZH2 expression results in the 
silencing of genes that suppress tumor formation and metastasis through 
trimethylation of histone H3 at lysine 27 (H3K27me3) at their promoters. 
However, inhibitors of EZH2 enzymatic activity have not shown the expected 
efficacy against cancer in clinical trials, suggesting a need for other 
strategies to address EZH2 overexpression. Here, we show that SUMOylation, a 
posttranslational modification characterized by covalent attachment of small 
ubiquitin-like modifier (SUMO) proteins to a lysine (Lys) residue on target 
proteins, enhances EZH2 transcription. Either knockdown of the SUMO-activating 
enzyme SAE2 or pharmacologic inhibition of SUMOylation resulted in decreased 
levels of EZH2 mRNA and protein as well as reduced H3K27me3 levels. SUMOylation 
regulated EZH2 expression by enhancing binding of the E2F1 transcriptional 
activator to the EZH2 promoter. Inhibition of SUMOylation not only resulted in 
reduced EZH2 mRNA and protein levels but also increased expression of genes 
silenced by EZH2, such as E-cadherin, which suppresses epithelial-mesenchymal 
transition and metastasis. In more than 6,500 patient tumor samples across 
different cancer types, expression of UBA2 and EZH2 was positively correlated. 
Taken together, our findings suggest that inhibition of SUMOylation may serve as 
a potential strategy to address EZH2 overexpression and improve current cancer 
therapeutic approaches. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="775~820" text="knockdown of the SUMO-activating  enzyme SAE2" description="knock down" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1245~1290" text="suppresses epithelial-mesenchymal  transition" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1245~1255,1295~1305" text="suppresses ... metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>