<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[UBR5 Is Coamplified with MYC in Breast Tumors and Encodes an Ubiquitin Ligase 
That Limits MYC-Dependent Apoptosis.

For maximal oncogenic activity, cellular MYC protein levels need to be tightly 
controlled so that they do not induce apoptosis. Here, we show how ubiquitin 
ligase UBR5 functions as a molecular rheostat to prevent excess accumulation of 
MYC protein. UBR5 ubiquitinates MYC and its effects on MYC protein stability are 
independent of FBXW7. Silencing of endogenous UBR5 induced MYC protein 
expression and regulated MYC target genes. Consistent with the tumor suppressor 
function of UBR5 (HYD) in Drosophila, HYD suppressed dMYC-dependent overgrowth 
of wing imaginal discs. In contrast, in cancer cells, UBR5 suppressed 
MYC-dependent priming to therapy-induced apoptosis. Of direct cancer relevance, 
MYC and UBR5 genes were coamplified in MYC-driven human cancers. Functionally, 
UBR5 suppressed MYC-mediated apoptosis in p53-mutant breast cancer cells with 
UBR5/MYC coamplification. Furthermore, single-cell immunofluorescence analysis 
demonstrated reciprocal expression of UBR5 and MYC in human basal-type breast 
cancer tissues. In summary, UBR5 is a novel MYC ubiquitin ligase and an 
endogenous rheostat for MYC activity. In MYC-amplified, and p53-mutant breast 
cancer cells, UBR5 has an important role in suppressing MYC-mediated apoptosis 
priming and in protection from drug-induced apoptosis. SIGNIFICANCE: These 
findings identify UBR5 as a novel MYC regulator, the inactivation of which could 
be very important for understanding of MYC dysregulation on cancer cells. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="460~488" text="Silencing of endogenous UBR5" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="945~955" text="p53-mutant" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="982~1006" text="UBR5/MYC coamplification" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1255~1284" text="MYC-amplified, and p53-mutant" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="711~723" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="956~975" text="breast cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1285~1305" text="breast  cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="775~792" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="908~918,932~941" text="suppressed ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1388~1403,1417~1426" text="protection from ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>