<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The Interplay between Slow-Cycling, Chemoresistant Cancer Cells and Fibroblasts 
Creates a Proinflammatory Niche for Tumor Progression.

Quiescent cancer cells are believed to cause cancer progression after 
chemotherapy through unknown mechanisms. We show here that human non-small cell 
lung cancer (NSCLC) cell line-derived, quiescent-like, slow-cycling cancer cells 
(SCC) and residual patient-derived xenograft (PDX) tumors after chemotherapy 
experience activating transcription factor 6 (ATF6)-mediated upregulation of 
various cytokines, which acts in a paracrine manner to recruit fibroblasts. 
Cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAF) underwent transcriptional upregulation of 
COX2 and type I collagen (Col-I), which subsequently triggered a slow-to-active 
cycling switch in SCC through prostaglandin E2 (PGE2)- and integrin/Src-mediated 
signaling pathways, leading to cancer progression. Both antagonism of ATF6 and 
cotargeting of Src/COX2 effectively suppressed cytokine production and 
slow-to-active cell cycling transition in SCC, withholding cancer progression. 
Expression of COX2 and Col-I and activation of Src were observed in patients 
with NSCLC who progressed while receiving chemotherapy. Public data analysis 
revealed significant association between COL1A1 and SRC expression and NSCLC 
relapse. Overall, these findings indicate that a proinflammatory niche created 
by the interplay between SCC and CAF triggers tumor progression. SIGNIFICANCE: 
Cotargeting COX2 and Src may be an effective strategy to prevent cancer 
progression after chemotherapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="902~920" text="antagonism of ATF6" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="926~949" text="cotargeting of Src/COX2" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="267~326" text="human non-small cell  lung cancer (NSCLC) cell line-derived" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="328~376" text="quiescent-like, slow-cycling cancer cells  (SCC)" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="390~428" text="patient-derived xenograft (PDX) tumors" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="604~639" text="Cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAF)" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="782~785" text="SCC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1040~1043" text="SCC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>