<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mitochondrial respiratory chain deficiency inhibits lysosomal hydrolysis.

Mitochondria are key organelles for cellular metabolism, and regulate several 
processes including cell death and macroautophagy/autophagy. Here, we show that 
mitochondrial respiratory chain (RC) deficiency deactivates AMP-activated 
protein kinase (AMPK, a key regulator of energy homeostasis) signaling in tissue 
and in cultured cells. The deactivation of AMPK in RC-deficiency is due to 
increased expression of the AMPK-inhibiting protein FLCN (folliculin). AMPK is 
found to be necessary for basal lysosomal function, and AMPK deactivation in 
RC-deficiency inhibits lysosomal function by decreasing the activity of the 
lysosomal Ca2+ channel MCOLN1 (mucolipin 1). MCOLN1 is regulated by 
phosphoinositide kinase PIKFYVE and its product PtdIns(3,5)P2, which is also 
decreased in RC-deficiency. Notably, reactivation of AMPK, in a 
PIKFYVE-dependent manner, or of MCOLN1 in RC-deficient cells, restores lysosomal 
hydrolytic capacity. Building on these data and the literature, we propose that 
downregulation of the AMPK-PIKFYVE-PtdIns(3,5)P2-MCOLN1 pathway causes lysosomal 
Ca2+ accumulation and impaired lysosomal catabolism. Besides unveiling a novel 
role of AMPK in lysosomal function, this study points to the mechanism that 
links mitochondrial malfunction to impaired lysosomal catabolism, underscoring 
the importance of AMPK and the complexity of organelle cross-talk in the 
regulation of cellular homeostasis. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="887~907" text="reactivation of AMPK" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="887~899,944~953" text="reactivation ... of MCOLN1" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="399~413" text="cultured cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="957~975" text="RC-deficient cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>