<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[IL33 Is a Key Driver of Treatment Resistance of Cancer.

Recurrence and treatment resistance are major causes of cancer-associated death. 
There has been a growing interest in better understanding epithelial-mesenchymal 
transition, stemness of cancer cells, and exhaustion and dysfunction of the 
immune system for which numerous genomic, proteomic, microenvironmental, and 
immunologic mechanisms have been demonstrated. However, practical treatments for 
such patients have not yet been established. Here we identified IL33 as a key 
driver of polyploidy, followed by rapid proliferation after treatment. IL33 
induction transformed tumor cells into polyploid giant cells, showing abnormal 
cell cycle without cell division accompanied by Snail deregulation and p53 
inactivation; small progeny cells were generated in response to treatment 
stress. Simultaneously, soluble IL33 was released from tumor cells, leading to 
expansion of receptor ST2-expressing cells including IL17RB+GATA3+ cells, which 
promoted tumor progression and metastasis directly and indirectly via induction 
of immune exhaustion and dysfunction. Blocking IL33 with a specific mAb in 
murine IL33+ metastatic tumor models abrogated negative consequences and 
successfully elicited antitumor efficacy induced by other combined treatments. 
Ex vivo assays using tumor tissues and peripheral blood mononuclear cells of 
patients with cancer validated the clinical relevancy of these findings. 
Together, these data suggest that targeting the IL33-ST2 axis is a promising 
strategy for diagnosis and treatment of patients likely to be resistant to 
treatments in the clinical settings.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="636~647" text="tumor cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="938~997" text="receptor ST2-expressing cells including IL17RB+GATA3+ cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="624~635,648~674" text="transformed ... into polyploid giant cells" phenotype="transformation" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="705~726" text="without cell division" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1006~1032" text="promoted tumor progression" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1006~1014,1037~1047" text="promoted ... metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="913~934" text="leading to  expansion" phenotype="proliferation" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>