<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A Wnt-Induced Phenotypic Switch in Cancer-Associated Fibroblasts Inhibits EMT in 
Colorectal Cancer.

Tumor progression is recognized as a result of an evolving cross-talk between 
tumor cells and their surrounding nontransformed stroma. Although Wnt signaling 
has been intensively studied in colorectal cancer, it remains unclear whether 
activity in the tumor-associated stroma contributes to malignancy. To 
specifically interfere with stromal signals, we generated Wnt-independent tumor 
organoids that secrete the Wnt antagonist Sfrp1. Subcutaneous transplantation 
into immunocompetent as well as immunodeficient mice resulted in a strong 
reduction of tumor growth. Histologic and transcriptomic analyses revealed that 
Sfrp1 induced an epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) phenotype in tumor 
cells without affecting tumor-intrinsic Wnt signaling, suggesting involvement of 
nonimmune stromal cells. Blockage of canonical signaling using Sfrp1, Dkk1, or 
fibroblast-specific genetic ablation of β-catenin strongly decreased the number 
of cancer-associated myofibroblasts (myCAF). Wnt activity in CAFs was linked 
with distinct subtypes, where low and high levels induced an inflammatory-like 
CAF (iCAF) subtype or contractile myCAFs, respectively. Coculture of tumor 
organoids with iCAFs resulted in significant upregulation of EMT markers, while 
myCAFs reverted this phenotype. In summary, we show that tumor growth and 
malignancy are differentially regulated via distinct fibroblast subtypes under 
the influence of juxtacrine Wnt signals.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="967~1016" text="fibroblast-specific genetic ablation of β-catenin" description="conditional knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="577~592,620~624" text="immunocompetent ... mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="604~624" text="immunodeficient mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="798~810" text="tumor  cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1051~1091" text="cancer-associated myofibroblasts (myCAF)" species="not stated" experiment_type="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1275~1291" text="tumor  organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="647~672" text="reduction of tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="734~794" text="induced an epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) phenotype" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1327~1354" text="upregulation of EMT markers" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>