<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ERK1/2 Signaling Induces Upregulation of ANGPT2 and CXCR4 to Mediate Liver 
Metastasis in Colon Cancer.

Carcinoma development in colorectal cancer is driven by genetic alterations in 
numerous signaling pathways. Alterations in the RAS-ERK1/2 pathway are 
associated with the shortest overall survival for patients after diagnosis of 
colorectal cancer metastatic disease, yet how RAS-ERK signaling regulates 
colorectal cancer metastasis remains unknown. In this study, we used an unbiased 
screening approach based on selection of highly liver metastatic colorectal 
cancer cells in vivo to determine genes associated with metastasis. From this, 
an ERK1/2-controlled metastatic gene set (EMGS) was defined. EMGS was associated 
with increased recurrence and reduced survival in patients with colorectal 
cancer tumors. Higher levels of EMGS expression were detected in the colorectal 
cancer subsets consensus molecular subtype (CMS)1 and CMS4. ANGPT2 and CXCR4, 
two genes within the EMGS, were subjected to gain-of-function and 
loss-of-function studies in several colorectal cancer cell lines and then tested 
in clinical samples. The RAS-ERK1/2 axis controlled expression of the cytokine 
ANGPT2 and the cytokine receptor CXCR4 in colorectal cancer cells, which 
facilitated development of liver but not lung metastases, suggesting that ANGPT2 
and CXCR4 are important for metastatic outgrowth in the liver. CXCR4 controlled 
the expression of cytokines IL10 and CXCL1, providing evidence for a causal role 
of IL10 in supporting liver colonization. In summary, these studies demonstrate 
that amplification of ERK1/2 signaling in KRAS-mutated colorectal cancer cells 
affects the cytokine milieu of the tumors, possibly affecting tumor-stroma 
interactions and favoring liver metastasis formation. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1071~1099" text="colorectal cancer cell lines" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1652~1675" text="colorectal cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1271~1303,1317~1327" text="facilitated development of liver ... metastases" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1770~1805" text="favoring liver metastasis formation" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>