<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MEF2c-Dependent Downregulation of Myocilin Mediates Cancer-Induced Muscle 
Wasting and Associates with Cachexia in Patients with Cancer.

Skeletal muscle wasting is a devastating consequence of cancer that contributes 
to increased complications and poor survival, but is not well understood at the 
molecular level. Herein, we investigated the role of Myocilin (Myoc), a skeletal 
muscle hypertrophy-promoting protein that we showed is downregulated in multiple 
mouse models of cancer cachexia. Loss of Myoc alone was sufficient to induce 
phenotypes identified in mouse models of cancer cachexia, including muscle fiber 
atrophy, sarcolemmal fragility, and impaired muscle regeneration. By 18 months 
of age, mice deficient in Myoc showed significant skeletal muscle remodeling, 
characterized by increased fat and collagen deposition compared with wild-type 
mice, thus also supporting Myoc as a regulator of muscle quality. In cancer 
cachexia models, maintaining skeletal muscle expression of Myoc significantly 
attenuated muscle loss, while mice lacking Myoc showed enhanced muscle wasting. 
Furthermore, we identified the myocyte enhancer factor 2 C (MEF2C) transcription 
factor as a key upstream activator of Myoc whose gain of function significantly 
deterred cancer-induced muscle wasting and dysfunction in a preclinical model of 
pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC). Finally, compared with noncancer 
control patients, MYOC was significantly reduced in skeletal muscle of patients 
with PDAC defined as cachectic and correlated with MEF2c. These data therefore 
identify disruptions in MEF2c-dependent transcription of Myoc as a novel 
mechanism of cancer-associated muscle wasting that is similarly disrupted in 
muscle of patients with cachectic cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="497~509" text="Loss of Myoc" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="717~734" text="deficient in Myoc" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1054~1066" text="lacking Myoc" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1131~1166,1231~1247" text="myocyte enhancer factor 2 C (MEF2C) ... gain of function" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="712~716" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="932~955" text="cancer  cachexia models" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1049~1053" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1323~1384" text="preclinical model of  pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC)" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>