<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Hypoxia Induces Transcriptional and Translational Downregulation of the Type I 
IFN Pathway in Multiple Cancer Cell Types.

Hypoxia is a common phenomenon in solid tumors and is strongly linked to 
hallmarks of cancer. Recent evidence has shown that hypoxia promotes local 
immune suppression. Type I IFN supports cytotoxic T lymphocytes by stimulating 
the maturation of dendritic cells and enhancing their capacity to process and 
present antigens. However, little is known about the relationship between 
hypoxia and the type I IFN pathway, which comprises the sensing of 
double-stranded RNA and DNA (dsRNA/dsDNA) followed by IFNα/β secretion and 
transcriptional activation of IFN-stimulated genes (ISG). In this study, we 
determined the effects of hypoxia on the type I IFN pathway in breast cancer and 
the mechanisms involved. In cancer cell lines and xenograft models, mRNA and 
protein expressions of the type I IFN pathway were downregulated under hypoxic 
conditions. This pathway was suppressed at each level of signaling, from the 
dsRNA sensors RIG-I and MDA5, the adaptor MAVS, transcription factors IRF3, 
IRF7, and STAT1, and several ISG including RIG-I, IRF7, STAT1, and ADAR-p150. 
Importantly, IFN secretion was reduced under hypoxic conditions. HIF1α- and 
HIF2α-mediated regulation of gene expression did not explain most of the 
effects. However, ATAC-seq data revealed in hypoxia that peaks with STAT1 and 
IRF3 motifs had decreased accessibility. Collectively, these results indicate 
that hypoxia leads to an overall downregulation of the type I IFN pathway due to 
repressed transcription and lower chromatin accessibility in an 
HIF1/2α-independent manner, which could contribute to immunosuppression in 
hypoxic tumors. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="839~856" text="cancer cell lines" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="861~877" text="xenograft models" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>