<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DMDRMR-Mediated Regulation of m(6)A-Modified CDK4 by m(6)A Reader IGF2BP3 Drives 
ccRCC Progression.

Aberrant N 6-methyladenosine (m6A) modification has emerged as a driver of tumor 
initiation and progression, yet how long noncoding RNAs (lncRNA) are involved in 
the regulation of m6A remains unknown. Here we utilize data from 12 cancer types 
from The Cancer Genome Atlas to comprehensively map lncRNAs that are potentially 
deregulated by DNA methylation. A novel DNA methylation-deregulated and RNA m6A 
reader-cooperating lncRNA (DMDRMR) facilitated tumor growth and metastasis in 
clear cell renal cell carcinoma (ccRCC). Mechanistically, DMDRMR bound 
insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA-binding protein 3 (IGF2BP3) to stabilize 
target genes, including the cell-cycle kinase CDK4 and three extracellular 
matrix components (COL6A1, LAMA5, and FN1), by specifically enhancing IGF2BP3 
activity on them in an m6A-dependent manner. Consequently, DMDRMR and IGF2BP3 
enhanced the G1-S transition, thus promoting cell proliferation in ccRCC. In 
patients with ccRCC, high coexpression of DMDRMR and IGF2BP3 was associated with 
poor outcomes. Our findings reveal that DMDRMR cooperates with IGF2BP3 to 
regulate target genes in an m6A-dependent manner and may represent a potential 
diagnostic, prognostic, and therapeutic target in ccRCC. SIGNIFICANCE: This 
study demonstrates that the lncRNA DMDRMR acts as a cofactor for IGF2BP3 to 
stabilize target genes in an m6A-dependent manner, thus exerting essential 
oncogenic roles in ccRCC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="590~629" text="clear cell renal cell carcinoma (ccRCC)" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1039~1044" text="ccRCC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1017~1021" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="546~570" text="facilitated tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="546~557,575~585" text="facilitated ... metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1007~1016,1022~1035" text="promoting ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>