<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Allosteric Inhibition of SHP2 Stimulates Antitumor Immunity by Transforming the 
Immunosuppressive Environment.

The protein tyrosine phosphatase SHP2 binds to phosphorylated signaling motifs 
on regulatory immunoreceptors including PD-1, but its functional role in tumor 
immunity is unclear. Using preclinical models, we show that RMC-4550, an 
allosteric inhibitor of SHP2, induces antitumor immunity, with effects 
equivalent to or greater than those resulting from checkpoint blockade. In the 
tumor microenvironment, inhibition of SHP2 modulated T-cell infiltrates similar 
to checkpoint blockade. In addition, RMC-4550 drove direct, selective depletion 
of protumorigenic M2 macrophages via attenuation of CSF1 receptor signaling and 
increased M1 macrophages via a mechanism independent of CD8+ T cells or IFNγ. 
These dramatic shifts in polarized macrophage populations in favor of antitumor 
immunity were not seen with checkpoint blockade. Consistent with a pleiotropic 
mechanism of action, RMC-4550 in combination with either checkpoint or CSF1R 
blockade caused additive antitumor activity with complete tumor regressions in 
some mice; tumors intrinsically sensitive to SHP2 inhibition or checkpoint 
blockade were particularly susceptible. Our preclinical findings demonstrate 
that SHP2 thus plays a multifaceted role in inducing immune suppression in the 
tumor microenvironment, through both targeted inhibition of RAS 
pathway-dependent tumor growth and liberation of antitumor immune responses. 
Furthermore, these data suggest that inhibition of SHP2 is a promising 
investigational therapeutic approach.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="333~375" text="RMC-4550, an  allosteric inhibitor of SHP2" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="523~541" text="inhibition of SHP2" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1145~1149" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>