<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Perineural Invasion Reprograms the Immune Microenvironment through Cholinergic 
Signaling in Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma.

Perineural invasion is a common feature of pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma 
(PDAC). Here, we investigated the effect of perineural invasion on the 
microenvironment and how this affects PDAC progression. Transcriptome expression 
profiles of PDAC tissues with different perineural invasion status were 
compared, and the intratumoral T-cell density and levels of neurotransmitters in 
these tissues were assessed. Perineural invasion was associated with impaired 
immune responses characterized by decreased CD8+ T and Th1 cells, and increased 
Th2 cells. Acetylcholine levels were elevated in severe perineural invasion. 
Acetylcholine impaired the ability of PDAC cells to recruit CD8+ T cells via 
HDAC1-mediated suppression of CCL5. Moreover, acetylcholine directly inhibited 
IFNγ production by CD8+ T cells in a dose-dependent manner and favored Th2 over 
Th1 differentiation. Furthermore, hyperactivation of cholinergic signaling 
enhanced tumor growth by suppressing the intratumoral T-cell response in an 
orthotopic PDAC model. Conversely, blocking perineural invasion with bilateral 
subdiaphragmatic vagotomy in tumor-bearing mice was associated with an increase 
in CD8+ T cells, an elevated Th1/Th2 ratio, and improved survival. In 
conclusion, perineural invasion-triggered cholinergic signaling favors tumor 
growth by promoting an immune-suppressive microenvironment characterized by 
impaired CD8+ T-cell infiltration and a reduced Th1/Th2 ratio.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="790~800" text="PDAC cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="929~941" text="CD8+ T cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="812~824" text="CD8+ T cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1144~1165" text="orthotopic PDAC model" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1253~1271" text="tumor-bearing mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1067~1088" text="enhanced tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1440~1460" text="favors tumor  growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>