<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BRD4 Levels Determine the Response of Human Lung Cancer Cells to BET Degraders 
That Potently Induce Apoptosis through Suppression of Mcl-1.

Lung cancer consists of approximately 80% non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) and 
20% small cell lung cancer (SCLC) and remains the leading cause of 
cancer-related deaths worldwide despite advances in early diagnosis, targeted 
therapy, and immunotherapy. Thus, novel therapies are still urgently needed. 
Bromodomain and extraterminal (BET) proteins, primarily comprised of BRD2, BRD3, 
and BRD4 proteins, function as epigenetic readers and master transcription 
coactivators and are now recognized cancer therapeutic targets. BET degraders 
such as ZBC260 and dBET represent a novel class of BET inhibitors that act by 
inducing BET degradation. The current study demonstrates the therapeutic 
efficacies of BET degraders, particularly ZBC260, against lung cancer, as well 
as understanding the underlying mechanisms and identifying molecular markers 
that determine cell sensitivity to BET degraders. A panel of NSCLC cell lines 
possessed similar response patterns to ZBC260 and dBET but different responses 
to BET inhibitor JQ-1. BRD levels, particularly BRD4, correlated positively with 
high sensitivity to BET degraders but not to JQ-1. BET degraders potently 
induced apoptosis in sensitive NSCLC cells and were accompanied by reduction of 
Mcl-1 and c-FLIP levels, which are critical for mediating induction of apoptosis 
and enhancement of TRAIL-induced apoptosis. Accordingly, ZBC260 exerted more 
potent activity than JQ-1 in vivo against the growth of NSCLC xenografts and 
patient-derived xenografts. These findings warrant future clinical validation of 
the efficacy of BET degraders in NSCLC, particularly those with high levels of 
BRD proteins, especially BRD4. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1047~1074" text="A panel of NSCLC cell lines" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1344~1355" text="NSCLC cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1580~1587,1610~1626" text="in vivo ... NSCLC xenografts" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1580~1587,1632~1658" text="in vivo ... patient-derived xenografts" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1313~1330" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1588~1606" text="against the growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>