<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Exploiting Preexisting Immunity to Enhance Oncolytic Cancer Immunotherapy.

Because of the high coverage of international vaccination programs, most people 
worldwide have been vaccinated against common pathogens, leading to acquired 
pathogen-specific immunity with a robust memory T-cell repertoire. Although CD8+ 
antitumor cytotoxic T lymphocytes (CTL) are the preferred effectors of cancer 
immunotherapy, CD4+ T-cell help is also required for an optimal antitumor immune 
response to occur. Hence, we investigated whether the pathogen-related CD4+ 
T-cell memory populations could be reengaged to support the CTLs, converting a 
weak primary antitumor immune response into a stronger secondary one. To this 
end, we used our PeptiCRAd technology that consists of an oncolytic adenovirus 
coated with MHC-I-restricted tumor-specific peptides and developed it further by 
introducing pathogen-specific MHC-II-restricted peptides. Mice preimmunized with 
tetanus vaccine were challenged with B16.OVA tumors and treated with the newly 
developed hybrid TT-OVA-PeptiCRAd containing both tetanus toxoid- and 
tumor-specific peptides. Treatment with the hybrid PeptiCRAd significantly 
enhanced antitumor efficacy and induced TT-specific, CD40 ligand-expressing CD4+ 
T helper cells and maturation of antigen-presenting cells. Importantly, this 
approach could be extended to naturally occurring tumor peptides (both 
tumor-associated antigens and neoantigens), as well as to other pathogens beyond 
tetanus, highlighting the usefulness of this technique to take full advantage of 
CD4+ memory T-cell repertoires when designing immunotherapeutic treatment 
regimens. Finally, the antitumor effect was even more prominent when combined 
with the immune checkpoint inhibitor anti-PD-1, str]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="934~938" text="Mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>