<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RNF168-Mediated Ubiquitin Signaling Inhibits the Viability of BRCA1-Null 
Cancers.

BRCA1 gene mutations impair homologous recombination (HR) DNA repair, resulting 
in cellular senescence and embryonic lethality in mice. Therefore, 
BRCA1-deficient cancers require adaptations that prevent excessive genomic 
alterations from triggering cell death. RNF168-mediated ubiquitination of γH2AX 
at K13/15 (ub-H2AX) serves as a recruitment module for the localization of 53BP1 
to DNA break sites. Here, we found multiple BRCA1-mutant cancer cell lines and 
primary tumors with low levels of RNF168 protein expression. Overexpression of 
ectopic RNF168 or a ub-H2AX fusion protein induced cell death and delayed 
BRCA1-mutant tumor formation. Cell death resulted from the recruitment of 53BP1 
to DNA break sites and inhibition of DNA end resection. Strikingly, 
reintroduction of BRCA1 or 53BP1 depletion restored HR and rescued the ability 
of cells to maintain RNF168 and ub-H2AX overexpression. Thus, downregulation of 
RNF168 protein expression is a mechanism for providing BRCA1-null cancer cell 
lines with a residual level of HR that is essential for viability. Overall, our 
work identifies loss of RNF168 ubiquitin signaling as a proteomic alteration 
that supports BRCA1-mutant carcinogenesis. We propose that restoring 
RNF168-ub-H2AX signaling, potentially through inhibition of deubiquitinases, 
could represent a new therapeutic approach.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="613~646" text="Overexpression of  ectopic RNF168" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="857~899" text="reintroduction of BRCA1 or 53BP1 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="940~945" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="698~735" text="delayed  BRCA1-mutant tumor formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="675~693" text="induced cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>