<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Long-Term Gemcitabine Treatment Reshapes the Pancreatic Tumor Microenvironment 
and Sensitizes Murine Carcinoma to Combination Immunotherapy.

Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is a leading cause of cancer-related 
death with a median survival time of 6-12 months. Most patients present with 
disseminated disease and the majority are offered palliative chemotherapy. With 
no approved treatment modalities for patients who progress on chemotherapy, we 
explored the effects of long-term gemcitabine administration on the tumor 
microenvironment to identify potential therapeutic options for chemorefractory 
PDAC. Using a combination of mouse models, primary cell line-derived xenografts, 
and established tumor cell lines, we first evaluated chemotherapy-induced 
alterations in the tumor secretome and immune surface proteins by high 
throughput proteomic arrays. In addition to enhancing antigen presentation and 
immune checkpoint expression, gemcitabine consistently increased the synthesis 
of CCL/CXCL chemokines and TGFβ-associated signals. These secreted factors 
altered the composition of the tumor stroma, conferring gemcitabine resistance 
to cancer-associated fibroblasts in vitro and further enhancing TGFβ1 
biosynthesis. Combined gemcitabine and anti-PD-1 treatment in transgenic models 
of murine PDAC failed to alter disease course unless mice also underwent genetic 
or pharmacologic ablation of TGFβ signaling. In the setting of TGFβ signaling 
deficiency, gemcitabine and anti-PD-1 led to a robust CD8+ T-cell response and 
decrease in tumor burden, markedly enhancing overall survival. These results 
suggest that gemcitabine successfully primes PDAC tumors for immune checkpoint 
inhibition by enhancing antigen presentation only following disruption of the 
immunosuppressive cytokine barrier. Given the current lack of third-line 
treatment options, this approach warrants consideration in the clinical 
management of gemcitabine-refractory PDAC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1385~1392,1411~1437" text="genetic ... ablation of TGFβ signaling" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1397~1437" text="pharmacologic ablation of TGFβ signaling" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1457~1483" text="TGFβ signaling  deficiency" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1163~1201" text="cancer-associated fibroblasts in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1293~1326" text="transgenic models  of murine PDAC" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1365~1369" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1565~1570" text="tumor" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1527~1538" text="CD8+ T-cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>