<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[p300-Mediated Acetylation of Histone Demethylase JMJD1A Prevents Its Degradation 
by Ubiquitin Ligase STUB1 and Enhances Its Activity in Prostate Cancer.

The androgen receptor (AR) pathway plays a central role in the development of 
castration-resistant prostate cancer (CRPC). The histone demethylase JMJD1A has 
been shown to regulate activities of AR and c-Myc transcription factors and 
promote prostate cancer progression. Here, we report that JMJD1A protein 
stability is controlled by the ubiquitin ligase STUB1. High levels of JMJD1A 
were strongly correlated with low STUB1 levels in human CRPC specimens. STUB1 
inhibited AR activity, AR-V7 levels, and prostate cancer cell growth partly 
through degradation of JMJD1A. Furthermore, the acetyltransferase p300 
acetylated JMJD1A at lysine (K) 421, a modification that recruits the BET family 
member BRD4 to block JMJD1A degradation and promote JMJD1A recruitment to AR 
targets. Increased levels of both total and K421-acetylated JMJD1A were observed 
in prostate cancer cells as they developed resistance to the AR antagonist 
enzalutamide. Treatment of prostate cancer cells with either p300 or BET 
inhibitors destabilized JMJD1A, and enzalutamide-resistant prostate cancer cells 
were more sensitive than parental cells to these inhibitors. Together, our 
findings identify a critical role for acetylation of JMJD1A in regulating JMJD1A 
stability and AR activity in CRPC. These newly identified mechanisms controlling 
JMJD1A protein stability provide potential druggable targets to encourage the 
development of additional therapies for advanced prostate cancer. SIGNIFICANCE: 
Identification of mechanisms regulating JMJD1A protein stability reveals new 
strategies to destabilize JMJD1A and concomitantly inhibit AR activities as 
potential prostate cancer therapy.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="664~679" text="prostate cancer" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1117~1138" text="prostate cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="623~632,680~691" text="inhibited ... cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>