<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MYC promotes tryptophan uptake and metabolism by the kynurenine pathway in colon 
cancer.

Tumors display increased uptake and processing of nutrients to fulfill the 
demands of rapidly proliferating cancer cells. Seminal studies have shown that 
the proto-oncogene MYC promotes metabolic reprogramming by altering glutamine 
uptake and metabolism in cancer cells. How MYC regulates the metabolism of other 
amino acids in cancer is not fully understood. Using high-performance liquid 
chromatography (HPLC)-tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS), we found that MYC 
increased intracellular levels of tryptophan and tryptophan metabolites in the 
kynurenine pathway. MYC induced the expression of the tryptophan transporters 
SLC7A5 and SLC1A5 and the enzyme arylformamidase (AFMID), involved in the 
conversion of tryptophan into kynurenine. SLC7A5, SLC1A5, and AFMID were 
elevated in colon cancer cells and tissues, and kynurenine was significantly 
greater in tumor samples than in the respective adjacent normal tissue from 
patients with colon cancer. Compared with normal human colonic epithelial cells, 
colon cancer cells were more sensitive to the depletion of tryptophan. Blocking 
enzymes in the kynurenine pathway caused preferential death of established colon 
cancer cells and transformed colonic organoids. We found that only kynurenine 
and no other tryptophan metabolite promotes the nuclear translocation of the 
transcription factor aryl hydrocarbon receptor (AHR). Blocking the interaction 
between AHR and kynurenine with CH223191 reduced the proliferation of colon 
cancer cells. Therefore, we propose that limiting cellular kynurenine or its 
downstream targets could present a new strategy to reduce the proliferation of 
MYC-dependent cancer cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1109~1127" text="colon cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1069~1106" text="normal human colonic epithelial cells" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1253~1284" text="established colon  cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1289~1318" text="transformed colonic organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1579~1598" text="colon  cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1224~1230,1244~1249" text="caused ... death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1550~1557,1562~1575" text="reduced ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>