<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Autophagy inhibition prevents glucocorticoid-increased adiposity via suppressing 
BAT whitening.

The mechanisms underlying glucocorticoid (GC)-increased adiposity are poorly 
understood. Brown adipose tissue (BAT) acquires white adipose tissue (WAT) cell 
features defined as BAT whitening under certain circumstances. The aim of our 
current study was to investigate the possibility and mechanisms of GC-induced 
BAT whitening. Here, we showed that one-week dexamethasone (Dex) treatment 
induced BAT whitening, characterized by lipid droplet accumulation, in vitro and 
in vivo. Furthermore, autophagy and ATG7 (autophagy related 7) expression was 
induced in BAT by Dex, and treatment with the autophagy inhibitor chloroquine or 
adenovirus-mediated ATG7 knockdown prevented Dex-induced BAT whitening and fat 
mass gain. Moreover, Dex-increased ATG7 expression and autophagy was mediated by 
enhanced expression of BTG1 (B cell translocation gene 1, anti-proliferative) 
that stimulated activity of CREB1 (cAMP response element binding protein 1). The 
importance of BTG1 in this regulation was further demonstrated by the observed 
BAT whitening in adipocyte-specific BTG1-overexpressing mice and the attenuated 
Dex-induced BAT whitening and fat mass gain in mice with BTG1 knockdown in BAT. 
Taken together, we showed that Dex induces a significant whitening of BAT via 
BTG1- and ATG7-dependent autophagy, which might contribute to Dex-increased 
adiposity. These results provide new insights into the mechanisms underlying 
GC-increased adiposity and possible strategy for preventing GC-induced side 
effects via the combined use of an autophagy inhibitor.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="734~768" text="adenovirus-mediated ATG7 knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1154~1192" text="adipocyte-specific BTG1-overexpressing" description="conditional knock in" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1275~1296" text="BTG1 knockdown in BAT" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="559~567" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="573~580" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1193~1197" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1265~1269" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="595~604,647~659" text="autophagy ... was  induced" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="869~891" text="autophagy was mediated" phenotype="autophagy" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1403~1412" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>