<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Context-dependent functional compensation between Ythdf m(6)A reader proteins.

The N6-methyladenosine (m6A) modification is the most prevalent 
post-transcriptional mRNA modification, regulating mRNA decay and splicing. It 
plays a major role during normal development, differentiation, and disease 
progression. The modification is regulated by a set of writer, eraser, and 
reader proteins. The YTH domain family of proteins consists of three homologous 
m6A-binding proteins, Ythdf1, Ythdf2, and Ythdf3, which were suggested to have 
different cellular functions. However, their sequence similarity and their 
tendency to bind the same targets suggest that they may have overlapping roles. 
We systematically knocked out (KO) the Mettl3 writer, each of the Ythdf readers, 
and the three readers together (triple-KO). We then estimated the effect in vivo 
in mouse gametogenesis, postnatal viability, and in vitro in mouse embryonic 
stem cells (mESCs). In gametogenesis, Mettl3-KO severity is increased as the 
deletion occurs earlier in the process, and Ythdf2 has a dominant role that 
cannot be compensated by Ythdf1 or Ythdf3, due to differences in readers' 
expression pattern across different cell types, both in quantity and in spatial 
location. Knocking out the three readers together and systematically testing 
viable offspring genotypes revealed a redundancy in the readers' role during 
early development that is Ythdf1/2/3 gene dosage-dependent. Finally, in mESCs 
there is compensation between the three Ythdf reader proteins, since the 
resistance to differentiate and the significant effect on mRNA decay occur only 
in the triple-KO cells and not in the single KOs. Thus, we suggest a new model 
for the Ythdf readers function, in which there is profound dosage-dependent 
redundancy when all three readers are equivalently coexpressed in the same cell 
types.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="713~747" text="knocked out (KO) the Mettl3 writer" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="712~729,757~774" text=" knocked out (KO) ... the Ythdf readers" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="975~984" text="Mettl3-KO" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="850~857" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="908~955" text="in vitro in mouse embryonic  stem cells (mESCs)" experiment_type="cells" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1476~1481" text="mESCs" experiment_type="cells" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1655~1660" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1557~1584" text="resistance to differentiate" phenotype="differentiation" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>