<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Rationale for targeting BCL6 in MLL-rearranged acute lymphoblastic leukemia.

Chromosomal rearrangements of the mixed lineage leukemia (MLL) gene occur in 
∼10% of B-cell acute lymphoblastic leukemia (B-ALL) and define a group of 
patients with dismal outcomes. Immunohistochemical staining of bone marrow 
biopsies from most of these patients revealed aberrant expression of BCL6, a 
transcription factor that promotes oncogenic B-cell transformation and drug 
resistance in B-ALL. Our genetic and ChIP-seq (chromatin immunoprecipitation 
[ChIP] combined with high-throughput sequencing) analyses showed that MLL-AF4 
and MLL-ENL fusions directly bound to the BCL6 promoter and up-regulated BCL6 
expression. While oncogenic MLL fusions strongly induced aberrant BCL6 
expression in B-ALL cells, germline MLL was required to up-regulate Bcl6 in 
response to physiological stimuli during normal B-cell development. Inducible 
expression of Bcl6 increased MLL mRNA levels, which was reversed by genetic 
deletion and pharmacological inhibition of Bcl6, suggesting a positive feedback 
loop between MLL and BCL6. Highlighting the central role of BCL6 in 
MLL-rearranged B-ALL, conditional deletion and pharmacological inhibition of 
BCL6 compromised leukemogenesis in transplant recipient mice and restored 
sensitivity to vincristine chemotherapy in MLL-rearranged B-ALL patient samples. 
Oncogenic MLL fusions strongly induced transcriptional activation of the 
proapoptotic BH3-only molecule BIM, while BCL6 was required to curb MLL-induced 
expression of BIM. Notably, peptide (RI-BPI) and small molecule (FX1) BCL6 
inhibitors derepressed BIM and synergized with the BH3-mimetic ABT-199 in 
eradicating MLL-rearranged B-ALL cells. These findings uncover MLL-dependent 
transcriptional activation of BCL6 as a previously unrecognized requirement of 
malignant transformation by oncogenic MLL fusions and identified BCL6 as a novel 
target for the treatment of MLL-rearranged B-ALL.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="915~944" text="Inducible  expression of Bcl6" description="conditional knock in" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="994~1011,1043~1050" text="genetic  deletion ... of Bcl6" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1016~1050" text="pharmacological inhibition of Bcl6" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1175~1195,1227~1235" text="conditional deletion ... of  BCL6" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1200~1235" text="pharmacological inhibition of  BCL6" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1571~1587,1613~1629" text="peptide (RI-BPI) ... BCL6  inhibitors" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1592~1629" text="small molecule (FX1) BCL6  inhibitors" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="784~795" text="B-ALL cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1266~1291" text="transplant recipient mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1721~1732" text="B-ALL cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>