<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Autophagy promotes mammalian survival by suppressing oxidative stress and p53.

Autophagy captures intracellular components and delivers them to lysosomes for 
degradation and recycling. Conditional autophagy deficiency in adult mice causes 
liver damage, shortens life span to 3 mo due to neurodegeneration, and is lethal 
upon fasting. As autophagy deficiency causes p53 induction and cell death in 
neurons, we sought to test whether p53 mediates the lethal consequences of 
autophagy deficiency. Here, we conditionally deleted Trp53 (p53 hereafter) 
and/or the essential autophagy gene Atg7 throughout adult mice. Compared with 
Atg7 Δ/Δ mice, the life span of Atg7 Δ/Δ p53 Δ/Δ mice was extended due to 
delayed neurodegeneration and resistance to death upon fasting. Atg7 also 
suppressed apoptosis induced by p53 activator Nutlin-3, suggesting that 
autophagy inhibited p53 activation. To test whether increased oxidative stress 
in Atg7 Δ/Δ mice was responsible for p53 activation, Atg7 was deleted in the 
presence or absence of the master regulator of antioxidant defense nuclear 
factor erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2). Nrf2-/-Atg7 Δ/Δ mice died rapidly 
due to small intestine damage, which was not rescued by p53 codeletion. Thus, 
Atg7 limits p53 activation and p53-mediated neurodegeneration. In turn, NRF2 
mitigates lethal intestine degeneration upon autophagy loss. These findings 
illustrate the tissue-specific roles for autophagy and functional dependencies 
on the p53 and NRF2 stress response mechanisms.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="509~552" text="conditionally deleted Trp53 (p53 hereafter)" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="509~530,590~594" text="conditionally deleted ... Atg7" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="509~552,554~557,590~594" text="conditionally deleted Trp53 (p53 hereafter) ... and ... Atg7" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="633~641" text="Atg7 Δ/Δ" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="665~681" text="Atg7 Δ/Δ p53 Δ/Δ" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="939~947" text="Atg7 Δ/Δ" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="1134~1149" text="Nrf2-/-Atg7 Δ/Δ" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P8" spans="989~1022,1034~1036,1097~1132" text="Atg7 was deleted in the  presence ... of ... erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2)" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P9" spans="988~1012,1026~1036,1097~1132" text=" Atg7 was deleted in the ... absence of ... erythroid 2-related factor 2 (Nrf2)" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="606~616" text="adult mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="642~646" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="682~686" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="948~952" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1150~1154" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="783~803" text="suppressed apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>