<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Autophagy regulates glucose-mediated root meristem activity by modulating ROS 
production in Arabidopsis.

Glucose produced from photosynthesis is a key nutrient signal regulating root 
meristem activity in plants; however, the underlying mechanisms remain poorly 
understood. Here, we show that, by modulating reactive oxygen species (ROS) 
levels, the conserved macroautophagy/autophagy degradation pathway contributes 
to glucose-regulated root meristem maintenance. In Arabidopsis thaliana roots, a 
short exposure to elevated glucose temporarily suppresses constitutive 
autophagosome formation. The autophagy-defective autophagy-related gene (atg) 
mutants have enhanced tolerance to glucose, established downstream of the 
glucose sensors, and accumulate less glucose-induced ROS in the root tips. 
Moreover, the enhanced root meristem activities in the atg mutants are 
associated with improved auxin gradients and auxin responses. By acting with 
AT4G39850/ABCD1 (ATP-binding cassette D1; Formerly PXA1/peroxisomal ABC 
transporter 1), autophagy plays an indispensable role in the glucose-promoted 
degradation of root peroxisomes, and the atg mutant phenotype is partially 
rescued by the overexpression of ABCD1. Together, our findings suggest that 
autophagy is an essential mechanism for glucose-mediated maintenance of the root 
meristem. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="625~662" text="autophagy-related gene (atg)  mutants" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="861~872" text="atg mutants" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1149~1159" text="atg mutant" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1199~1222" text="overexpression of ABCD1" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="473~499" text="Arabidopsis thaliana roots" experiment_type="organism" species="other" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="551~561,576~599" text="suppresses ... autophagosome formation" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>