<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RNA m(6) A modification enzymes shape innate responses to DNA by regulating 
interferon β.

Modification of mRNA by N 6-adenosine methylation (m6A) on internal bases 
influences gene expression in eukaryotes. How the dynamic genome-wide landscape 
of m6A-modified mRNAs impacts virus infection and host immune responses remains 
poorly understood. Here, we show that type I interferon (IFN) production 
triggered by dsDNA or human cytomegalovirus (HCMV) is controlled by the cellular 
m6A methyltrasferase subunit METTL14 and ALKBH5 demethylase. While METTL14 
depletion reduced virus reproduction and stimulated dsDNA- or HCMV-induced IFNB1 
mRNA accumulation, ALKBH5 depletion had the opposite effect. Depleting METTL14 
increased both nascent IFNB1 mRNA production and stability in response to dsDNA. 
In contrast, ALKBH5 depletion reduced nascent IFNB1 mRNA production without 
detectably influencing IFN1B mRNA decay. Genome-wide transcriptome profiling 
following ALKBH5 depletion identified differentially expressed genes regulating 
antiviral immune responses, while METTL14 depletion altered pathways impacting 
metabolic reprogramming, stress responses, and aging. Finally, we determined 
that IFNB1 mRNA was m6A-modified within both the coding sequence and the 3' 
untranslated region (UTR). This establishes that the host m6A modification 
machinery controls IFNβ production triggered by HCMV or dsDNA. Moreover, it 
demonstrates that responses to nonmicrobial dsDNA in uninfected cells, which 
shape host immunity and contribute to autoimmune disease, are regulated by 
enzymes controlling m6A epitranscriptomic changes.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="552~570" text="METTL14  depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="662~678" text="ALKBH5 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="704~721" text="Depleting METTL14" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="818~834" text="ALKBH5 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="970~986" text="ALKBH5 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1075~1092" text="METTL14 depletion" description="decreased expression level" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>