<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Hippo pathway deletion in adult resting cardiac fibroblasts initiates a cell 
state transition with spontaneous and self-sustaining fibrosis.

Cardiac fibroblasts (CFs) respond to injury by transitioning through multiple 
cell states, including resting CFs, activated CFs, and myofibroblasts. We report 
here that Hippo signaling cell-autonomously regulates CF fate transitions and 
proliferation, and non-cell-autonomously regulates both myeloid and CF 
activation in the heart. Conditional deletion of Hippo pathway kinases, Lats1 
and Lats2, in uninjured CFs initiated a self-perpetuating fibrotic response in 
the adult heart that was exacerbated by myocardial infarction (MI). Single cell 
transcriptomics showed that uninjured Lats1/2 mutant CFs spontaneously 
transitioned to a myofibroblast cell state. Through gene regulatory network 
reconstruction, we found that Hippo-deficient myofibroblasts deployed a network 
of transcriptional regulators of endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress, and the 
unfolded protein response (UPR) consistent with elevated secretory activity. We 
observed an expansion of myeloid cell heterogeneity in uninjured Lats1/2 CKO 
hearts with similarity to cells recovered from control hearts post-MI. 
Integrated genome-wide analysis of Yap chromatin occupancy revealed that Yap 
directly activates myofibroblast cell identity genes, the proto-oncogene Myc, 
and an array of genes encoding pro-inflammatory factors through 
enhancer-promoter looping. Our data indicate that Lats1/2 maintain the resting 
CF cell state through restricting the Yap-induced injury response.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="480~543" text="Conditional deletion of Hippo pathway kinases, Lats1  and Lats2" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="733~747" text="Lats1/2 mutant" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="874~889" text="Hippo-deficient" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1148~1159" text="Lats1/2 CKO" description="conditional knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="358~360" text="CF" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="439~446" text="myeloid" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="451~453" text="CF" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="548~561" text="uninjured CFs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="618~629" text="adult heart" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="723~732,748~751" text="uninjured ... CFs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="890~904" text="myofibroblasts" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1138~1147,1161~1167" text="uninjured ... hearts" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1108~1120" text="myeloid cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="348~357,383~396" text="regulates ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>