<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ALS-FTLD-linked mutations of SQSTM1/p62 disrupt selective autophagy and 
NFE2L2/NRF2 anti-oxidative stress pathway.

Macroautophagy (autophagy) is a key catabolic pathway for the maintenance of 
proteostasis through constant digestion of selective cargoes. The selectivity of 
autophagy is mediated by autophagy receptors that recognize and recruit cargoes 
to autophagosomes. SQSTM1/p62 is a prototype autophagy receptor, which is 
commonly found in protein aggregates associated with major neurodegenerative 
diseases. While accumulation of SQSTM1 implicates a disturbance of selective 
autophagy pathway, the pathogenic mechanism that contributes to impaired 
autophagy degradation remains poorly characterized. Herein we show that 
amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (ALS) and frontotemporal lobar degeneration 
(FTLD)-linked mutations of TBK1 and SQSTM1 disrupt selective autophagy and cause 
neurotoxicity. Our data demonstrates that proteotoxic stress activates 
serine/threonine kinase TBK1, which coordinates with autophagy kinase ULK1 to 
promote concerted phosphorylation of autophagy receptor SQSTM1 at the UBA domain 
and activation of selective autophagy. In contrast, ALS-FTLD-linked mutations of 
TBK1 or SQSTM1 reduce SQSTM1 phosphorylation and compromise ubiquitinated cargo 
binding and clearance. Moreover, disease mutation SQSTM1G427R abolishes 
phosphorylation of Ser351 and impairs KEAP1-SQSTM1 interaction, thus diminishing 
NFE2L2/Nrf2-targeted gene expression and increasing TARDBP/TDP-43 associated 
stress granule formation under oxidative stress. Furthermore, expression of 
SQSTM1G427R in neurons impairs dendrite morphology and KEAP1-NFE2L2 signaling. 
Therefore, our results reveal a mechanism whereby pathogenic SQSTM1 mutants 
inhibit selective autophagy and disrupt NFE2L2 anti-oxidative stress response 
underlying the neurotoxicity in ALS-FTLD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1178~1212" text="ALS-FTLD-linked mutations of  TBK1" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1178~1206,1216~1222" text="ALS-FTLD-linked mutations of ... SQSTM1" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="811~842" text="(FTLD)-linked mutations of TBK1" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="811~837,847~853" text="(FTLD)-linked mutations of ... SQSTM1" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1322~1350" text="disease mutation SQSTM1G427R" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="1584~1610" text="expression of  SQSTM1G427R" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P8" spans="1740~1754" text="SQSTM1 mutants" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1614~1621" text="neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="854~881" text="disrupt selective autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1130~1163" text="activation of selective autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1756~1783" text="inhibit selective autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>