<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The HGF-MET axis coordinates liver cancer metabolism and autophagy for 
chemotherapeutic resistance.

Notwithstanding the numerous drugs available for liver cancer, emerging evidence 
suggests that chemotherapeutic resistance is a significant issue. HGF and its 
receptor MET play critical roles in liver carcinogenesis and metastasis, mainly 
dependent on the activity of receptor tyrosine kinase. However, for unknown 
reasons, all HGF-MET kinase activity-targeted drugs have failed or have been 
suspended in clinical trials thus far. Macroautophagy/autophagy is a protective 
'self-eating' process for resisting metabolic stress by recycling obsolete 
components, whereas the impact of autophagy-mediated reprogrammed metabolism on 
therapeutic resistance is largely unclear, especially in liver cancer. In the 
present study, we first observed that HGF stimulus facilitated the Warburg 
effect and glutaminolysis to promote biogenesis in multiple liver cancer cells. 
We then identified the pyruvate dehydrogenase complex (PDHC) and GLS/GLS1 as 
crucial substrates of HGF-activated MET kinase; MET-mediated phosphorylation 
inhibits PDHC activity but activates GLS to promote cancer cell metabolism and 
biogenesis. We further found that the key residues of kinase activity in MET 
(Y1234/1235) also constitute a conserved LC3-interacting region motif 
(Y1234-Y1235-x-V1237). Therefore, on inhibiting HGF-mediated MET kinase 
activation, Y1234/1235-dephosphorylated MET induced autophagy to maintain 
biogenesis for cancer cell survival. Moreover, we verified that 
Y1234/1235-dephosphorylated MET correlated with autophagy in clinical liver 
cancer. Finally, a combination of MET inhibitor and autophagy suppressor 
significantly improved the therapeutic efficiency of liver cancer in vitro and 
in mice. Together, our findings reveal an HGF-MET axis-coordinated functional 
interaction between tyrosine kinase signaling and autophagy, and establish a 
MET-autophagy double-targeted strategy to overcome chemotherapeutic resistance 
in liver cancer. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="952~970" text="liver cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1181~1192" text="cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1521~1532" text="cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1775~1796" text="liver cancer in vitro" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1775~1787,1802~1809" text="liver cancer ... in mice" experiment_type="tumour" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1475~1492" text="induced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>