<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SMARCB1 loss interacts with neuronal differentiation state to block maturation 
and impact cell stability.

Atypical teratoid rhabdoid tumors (ATRTs) are challenging pediatric brain 
cancers that are predominantly associated with inactivation of the gene SMARCB1, 
a conserved subunit of the chromatin remodeling BAF complex, which has known 
contributions to developmental processes. To identify potential interactions 
between SMARCB1 loss and the process of neural development, we introduced an 
inducible SMARCB1 loss-of-function system into human induced pluripotent stem 
cells (iPSCs) that were subjected to either directed neuronal differentiation or 
differentiation into cerebral organoids. Using this system, we identified 
substantial differences in the downstream effects of SMARCB1 loss depending on 
differentiation state and identified an interaction between SMARCB1 loss and 
neural differentiation pressure that causes a resistance to terminal 
differentiation and a defect in maintenance of a normal cell state. Our results 
provide insight into how SMARCB1 loss might interact with neural development in 
the process of ATRT tumorigenesis.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="499~540" text="inducible SMARCB1 loss-of-function system" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="788~800" text="SMARCB1 loss" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="875~887" text="SMARCB1 loss" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="546~614,622~655" text="human induced pluripotent stem  cells (iPSCs) that were subjected to ... directed neuronal differentiation" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="546~614,660~699" text="human induced pluripotent stem  cells (iPSCs) that were subjected to ... differentiation into cerebral organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="930~978" text="causes a resistance to terminal  differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>