<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p regulate ferroptosis in I/R-induced renal injury.

Renal tubular cell death is the key factor of the pathogenesis of 
ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) kidney injury. Ferroptosis is a type of regulated 
cell death (RCD) found in various diseases. However, the underlying molecular 
mechanisms related to ferroptosis in renal I/R injury remain unclear. In the 
present study, we investigated the regulatory role of microRNAs on ferroptosis 
in I/R-induced renal injury. We established the I/R-induced renal injury model 
in rats, and H/R induced HK-2 cells injury in vitro. CCK-8 was used to measure 
cell viability. Fe2+ and ROS levels were assayed to evaluate the activation of 
ferroptosis. We performed RNA sequencing to profile the miRNAs expression in 
H/R-induced injury and ferroptosis. Western blot analysis was used to detect the 
protein expression. qRT-PCR was used to detect the mRNA and miRNA levels in 
cells and tissues. We further used luciferase reporter assay to verify the 
direct targeting effect of miRNA. We found that ischemia/reperfusion-induced 
ferroptosis in rat's kidney. We identified that miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p were 
upregulated in the ferroptosis and H/R-induced injury, and correlates reversely 
with glutathione peroxidases 4 (GPX4) and solute carrier family 7 member 11 
(SLC7A11) expression in renal I/R injury tissues, respectively. In vitro studies 
showed that miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p induced ferroptosis in cells. We further 
found that miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p regulated the expression of GPX4 and 
SLC7A11 negatively by directly binding to the 3'UTR of GPX4 and SLC7A11 mRNA. In 
vivo study showed that silencing miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p alleviated the 
I/R-induced renal injury in rats. In conclusion, we demonstrated that I/R 
induced upregulation of miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p, leading to activation of 
ferroptosis in renal injury through downregulation of GPX4 and SLC7A11.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1674~1710" text="silencing miR-182-5p and miR-378a-3p" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1106~1118" text="rat&apos;s kidney" experiment_type="organism" species="rat" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1394~1402,1474~1479" text="In vitro ... cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1647~1655,1755~1759" text="In  vivo ... rats" experiment_type="organism" species="rat" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1082~1102" text="induced  ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1451~1470" text="induced ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1865~1891" text="activation of  ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>