<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Circular RNA GLIS2 promotes colorectal cancer cell motility via activation of 
the NF-κB pathway.

Circular RNAs (circRNAs) are a newly discovered type of biological molecule that 
belongs to the noncoding RNA family. Abundant evidence has shown that circRNAs 
are involved in the progression of various cancers. However, the particular 
functions of circRNAs in colorectal cancer (CRC) remain elusive. In this study, 
we investigated the differentially expressed circRNAs in three pairs of cancer 
tissue and adjacent normal tissue of CRC. We revealed that circGLIS2 expression 
was higher in CRC tissue and cell lines. Gain-and-loss function assays showed 
that circGLIS2 was involved in the regulation of cell migration. Moreover, 
overexpressing circGLIS2 in CRC cells activated the NF-κB pathway and induced 
pro-inflammatory chemokine production, which evoked tumor-associated 
inflammation through recruiting leukocytes. In turn, when the cancer cells were 
exposed to the supernatant of circGLIS2 overexpressed cancer cells, they were 
endowed with the ability of migration and chemokines production. Furthermore, 
the rescue assay confirmed that circGLIS2 activated NF-κB signaling and promoted 
cell migration by sponging miR-671. Overall, our study reveals that circGLIS2, 
acting as a potential oncogene, maintains the abnormal activation state of the 
NF-κB signaling pathway via the miR-671 sponge mechanism in CRC cells. This 
study provides a scientific basis for targeting circGLIS2 in colorectal cancer 
interventions.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="735~759" text="overexpressing circGLIS2" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="995~1018" text="circGLIS2 overexpressed" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="763~772" text="CRC cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="946~958" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1019~1031" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1205~1209" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="694~722" text="regulation of cell migration" phenotype="migration" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1044~1081" text="endowed with the ability of migration" phenotype="migration" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1195~1203,1210~1219" text="promoted ... migration" phenotype="migration" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>