<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PERK controls bone homeostasis through the regulation of osteoclast 
differentiation and function.

Osteoclasts are multinucleated giant cells with the ability to degrade bone 
tissue, and are closely related to abnormal bone metabolic diseases. Endoplasmic 
reticulum (ER) is an organelle responsible for protein modification, quality 
control, and transportation. The accumulation of unfolded or misfolded proteins 
in ER cavity induces ER stress. Double-stranded RNA-dependent protein 
kinase-like ER kinase (PERK) is an ER stress-sensing protein, which is 
ubiquitous in eukaryotic cells. Systemic PERK knockout mice show severe bone 
loss, suggesting that PERK is of great significance for maintaining the normal 
growth and development of bone tissue, but the role of PERK in 
osteoclastogenesis is still unclear. In this study, we found that PERK was 
significantly activated during RANKL-induced osteoclast differentiation; 
knockdown of PERK by siRNA and inhibition of PERK by GSK2606414, respectively, 
had significant negative regulatory effects on the formation and bone resorption 
of osteoclasts. PERK inhibitor GSK2606414 down-regulated the mRNA levels and 
protein expression of osteoclast differentiation marker genes, and inhibited 
RANKL-induced activation of Mitogen-activated protein kinase (MAPK) and nuclear 
factor κB (NF-κB) pathways. Treatment with PERK inhibitor GSK2606414 in 
ovariectomized mouse model significantly suppressed bone loss and osteoclast 
formation. Thapsigargin activated ER stress to enhance autophagy, while 
GSK2606414 had a significant inhibitory effect on autophagy flux and 
autophagosome formation. Antioxidant N-acetylcysteine (NAC) could inhibit the 
expression of PERK phosphorylation, osteoclast-related proteins and 
autophagy-related proteins, but the use of PERK activator CCT020312 can reverse 
inhibition effect of NAC. Our findings demonstrate a key role for PERK in 
osteoclast differentiation and suggest its therapeutic potential.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="933~959" text="knockdown of PERK by siRNA" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="964~996" text="inhibition of PERK by GSK2606414" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1111~1136" text="PERK inhibitor GSK2606414" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1360~1400" text="Treatment with PERK inhibitor GSK2606414" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1817~1841" text="PERK activator CCT020312" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="904~914" text="osteoclast" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1098~1109" text="osteoclasts" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1405~1431" text="ovariectomized mouse model" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="896~903,915~930" text="induced ... differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1585~1649" text="inhibitory effect on autophagy flux and  autophagosome formation" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>