<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A cross-talk between epithelium and endothelium mediates human 
alveolar-capillary injury during SARS-CoV-2 infection.

COVID-19, caused by SARS-CoV-2, is an acute and rapidly developing pandemic, 
which leads to a global health crisis. SARS-CoV-2 primarily attacks human 
alveoli and causes severe lung infection and damage. To better understand the 
molecular basis of this disease, we sought to characterize the responses of 
alveolar epithelium and its adjacent microvascular endothelium to viral 
infection under a co-culture system. SARS-CoV-2 infection caused massive virus 
replication and dramatic organelles remodeling in alveolar epithelial cells, 
alone. While, viral infection affected endothelial cells in an indirect manner, 
which was mediated by infected alveolar epithelium. Proteomics analysis and TEM 
examinations showed viral infection caused global proteomic modulations and 
marked ultrastructural changes in both epithelial cells and endothelial cells 
under the co-culture system. In particular, viral infection elicited global 
protein changes and structural reorganizations across many sub-cellular 
compartments in epithelial cells. Among the affected organelles, mitochondrion 
seems to be a primary target organelle. Besides, according to EM and proteomic 
results, we identified Daurisoline, a potent autophagy inhibitor, could inhibit 
virus replication effectively in host cells. Collectively, our study revealed an 
unrecognized cross-talk between epithelium and endothelium, which contributed to 
alveolar-capillary injury during SARS-CoV-2 infection. These new findings will 
expand our understanding of COVID-19 and may also be helpful for targeted drug 
development.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="632~657" text="alveolar epithelial cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="938~1005" text="epithelial cells and endothelial cells  under the co-culture system" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1144~1160" text="epithelial cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1407~1412" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>