<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The miR-30a-5p/CLCF1 axis regulates sorafenib resistance and aerobic glycolysis 
in hepatocellular carcinoma.

HCC (hepatocellular carcinoma) is a major health threat for the Chinese 
population and has poor prognosis because of strong resistance to chemotherapy 
in patients. For instance, a considerable challenge for the treatment of HCC is 
sorafenib resistance. The aberrant glucose metabolism in cancer cells aerobic 
glycolysis is associated with resistance to chemotherapeutic agents. 
Drug-resistance cells and tumors were exposed to sorafenib to establish 
sorafenib-resistance cell lines and tumors. Western blotting and real-time PCR 
or IHC staining were used to analyze the level of CLCF1 in the sorafenib 
resistance cell lines or tumors. The aerobic glycolysis was analyzed by ECAR 
assay. The mechanism mediating the high expression of CLCF1 in 
sorafenib-resistant cells and its relationships with miR-130-5p was determined 
by bioinformatic analysis, dual luciferase reporter assays, real-time PCR, and 
western blotting. The in vivo effect was evaluated by xenografted with nude 
mice. The relation of CLCF1 and miR-30a-5p was determined in patients' samples. 
In this study, we report the relationship between sorafenib resistance and 
increased glycolysis in HCC cells. We also show the vital role of CLCF1 in 
promoting glycolysis by activating PI3K/AKT signaling and its downstream genes, 
thus participating in glycolysis in sorafenib-resistant HCC cells. Furthermore, 
we also show that miR-30a-5p directly targets CLCF1 and that sorafenib-mediated 
suppression of miR-30a-5p results in the upregulation of CLCF1 in HCC cells 
resistant to sorafenib. We also found that when a cholesterol modified 
agomiR-30a-5p was delivered systemically to mice harboring sorafenib-resistant 
HCC tumors, tumor growth decreased significantly. There is an uncharacterized 
mechanism of biochemical resistance to hormone therapies orchestrated by the 
miR-30a-5p/CLCF1 axis to mediate sorafenib resistance and aerobic glycolysis in 
HCC. Therefore, this study indicates that targeting the miR-30a-5p/CLCF1 axis 
may hold promise for therapeutic intervention in HCC sorafenib resistance 
patients.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1769~1815" text="mice harboring sorafenib-resistant  HCC tumors" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1642~1675" text="HCC cells  resistant to sorafenib" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1817~1839" text="tumor growth decreased" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>