<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Long non-coding RNA CASC9 promotes gefitinib resistance in NSCLC by epigenetic 
repression of DUSP1.

Resistance to epidermal growth factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitors 
(EGFR-TKIs), such as gefitinib, has greatly affected clinical outcomes in 
non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients. The long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) 
are known to regulate tumorigenesis and cancer progression, but their 
contributions to NSCLC gefitinib resistance remain poorly understood. In this 
study, by analyzing the differentially expressed lncRNAs in gefitinib-resistant 
cells and gefitinib-sensitive cells in the National Institute of Health GEO 
dataset, we found that lncRNA CASC9 expression was upregulated, and this was 
also verified in resistant tissues. Gain and loss of function studies showed 
that CASC9 inhibition restored gefitinib sensitivity both in vitro and in vivo, 
whereas CASC9 overexpression promoted gefitinib resistance. Mechanistically, 
CASC9 repressed the tumor suppressor DUSP1 by recruiting histone 
methyltransferase EZH2, thereby increasing the resistance to gefitinib. 
Furthermore, ectopic expression of DUSP1 increased gefitinib sensitivity by 
inactivating the ERK pathway. Our results highlight the essential role of CASC9 
in gefitinib resistance, suggesting that the CASC9/EZH2/DUSP1 axis might be a 
novel target for overcoming EGFR-TKI resistance in NSCLC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="801~817" text="CASC9 inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="885~905" text="CASC9 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1107~1134" text="ectopic expression of DUSP1" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="854~862" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="867~874" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>