<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[High-fat diet promotes renal injury by inducing oxidative stress and 
mitochondrial dysfunction.

Obesity has been recognized as a major risk factor for chronic kidney disease, 
but the underlying mechanism remains elusive. Here, we investigated the 
mechanism whereby long-term high-fat diet (HFD) feeding induces renal injury in 
mice. The C57BL/6 mice fed HFD for 16 weeks developed obesity, diabetes, and 
kidney dysfunction manifested by albuminuria and blood accumulation of BUN and 
creatinine. The HFD-fed kidney showed marked glomerular and tubular injuries, 
including prominent defects in the glomerular filtration barrier and increased 
tubular cell apoptosis. Mechanistically, HFD feeding markedly increased 
triglyceride and cholesterol contents in the kidney and activated lipogenic 
pathways for cholesterol and triglyceride synthesis. HFD feeding also increased 
oxidative stress and induced mitochondrial fission in tubular cells, thereby 
activating the pro-apoptotic pathway. In HK-2 and mesangial cell cultures, high 
glucose, fatty acid, and TNF-α combination was able to activate the lipogenic 
pathways, increase oxidative stress, promote mitochondrial fission, and activate 
the pro-apoptotic pathway, all of which could be attenuated by an inhibitor that 
depleted reactive oxygen species. Taken together, these observations suggest 
that long-term HFD feeding causes kidney injury at least in part as a result of 
tissue lipid accumulation, increased oxidative stress, and mitochondrial 
dysfunction, which promote excess programmed cell death.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="342~354" text="C57BL/6 mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="514~520" text="kidney" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="649~661" text="tubular cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="767~773" text="kidney" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="934~947" text="tubular cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="999~1031" text="HK-2 and mesangial cell cultures" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="638~647,662~671" text="increased ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>