<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Molecular subtype-specific responses of colon cancer cells to the SMAC mimetic 
Birinapant.

Colorectal cancer is a molecularly heterogeneous disease. Responses to genotoxic 
chemotherapy in the adjuvant or palliative setting vary greatly between 
patients, and colorectal cancer cells often resist chemotherapy by evading 
apoptosis. Antagonists of an inhibitor of apoptosis proteins (IAPs) can restore 
defective apoptosis signaling by degrading cIAP1 and cIAP2 proteins and by 
inhibition of XIAP. Due to the multiple molecular mechanisms-of-action of these 
targets, responses to IAP antagonist may differ between molecularly distinct 
colon cancer cells. In this study, responses to the IAP antagonist Birinapant 
and oxaliplatin/5-fluorouracil (5-FU) were investigated in 14 colon cancer cell 
lines, representing the consensus molecular subtypes (CMS). Treatment with 
Birinapant alone did not result in a substantial increase in apoptotic cells in 
this cell line panel. Annexin-V/PI assays quantified by flow cytometry and 
high-content screening showed that Birinapant increased responses of CMS1 and 
partially CMS3 cell lines to oxaliplatin/5-FU, whereas CMS2 cells were not 
effectively sensitized. FRET-based imaging of caspase-8 and -3 activation 
validated these differences at the single-cell level, with CMS1 cells displaying 
sustained activation of caspase-8-like activity during Birinapant and 
oxaliplatin/5-FU co-treatment, ultimately activating the intrinsic mitochondrial 
apoptosis pathway. In CMS2 cell lines, Birinapant exhibited synergistic effects 
in combination with TNFα, suggesting that Birinapant can restore extrinsic 
apoptosis signaling in the context of inflammatory signals in this subtype. To 
explore this further, we co-cultured CMS2 and CMS1 colon cancer cells with 
peripheral blood mononuclear cells. We observed increased cell death during 
Birinapant single treatment in these co-cultures, which was abrogated by 
anti-TNFα-neutralizing antibodies. Collectively, our study demonstrates that IAP 
inhibition is a promising modulator of response to oxaliplatin/5-FU in 
colorectal cancers of the CMS1 subtype, and may show promise as in the CMS2 
subtype, suggesting that molecular subtyping may aid as a patient stratification 
tool for IAP antagonists in this disease.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="778~805" text="14 colon cancer cell  lines" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="962~977" text="cell line panel" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1102~1110,1122~1137" text="CMS1 and ... CMS3 cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1167~1177" text="CMS2 cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1322~1332" text="CMS1 cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1520~1535" text="CMS2 cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1760~1845" text="co-cultured CMS2 and CMS1 colon cancer cells with  peripheral blood mononuclear cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="893~910,925~952" text="did not result in ... increase in apoptotic cells" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1859~1879" text="increased cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>