<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Prohibitin, STAT3 and SH2D4A physically and functionally interact in tumor cell 
mitochondria.

Chromosome 8p is frequently deleted in various cancer entities and has been 
shown to correlate with poor patient survival. SH2D4A is located on chromosome 
8p and prevents the nuclear translocation of the pro-tumorigenic transcription 
factor STAT3. Here, we investigated the interaction of SH2D4A and STAT3 to shed 
light on the non-canonical functions of STAT3 in cooperation with the tumor 
suppressor SH2D4A. Using an immunoprecipitation-mass spectrometry (IP-MS) 
approach, we identified the mitochondrial scaffold proteins prohibitin 1 (PHB1) 
and prohibitin 2 (PHB2) among other proteins to potentially bind to SH2D4A. 
Co-immunoprecipitation and proximity ligation assays confirmed direct 
interactions of STAT3, PHB1, and SH2D4A in situ and in vitro. In addition, cell 
fractionation and immunofluorescence staining revealed co-localization of these 
proteins with mitochondria. These interactions were selectively interrupted by 
the small molecule and PHB ligand FL3. Furthermore, FL3 led to a reduction of 
STAT3 protein levels, STAT3 transcriptional activity, and HIF1α protein 
stabilization upon dimethyloxalylglycine (DMOG) treatment. Besides, 
mitochondrial fusion and fission markers, L-OPA1, Mfn1, and FIS1, were 
dysregulated upon FL3 treatment. This dysregulated morphology was accompanied by 
significant reduction of mitochondrial respiration, thus, FL3 significantly 
diminished mitochondrial respirational capacity. In contrast, SH2D4A knockout 
increased mitochondrial respiration, whereas FL3 reversed the effect of SH2D4A 
knockout. The here described results indicate that the interaction of SH2D4A and 
PHB1 is involved in the mitochondrial function and integrity. The demonstrated 
interaction with STAT3, accompanied by its reduction of transcriptional 
activity, further suggests that SH2D4A is linking STAT3 to its mitochondrial 
functions, and inhibition of PHB-interaction may have therapeutic effects in 
tumor cells with STAT3 activation.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1551~1566" text="SH2D4A knockout" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1640~1656" text="SH2D4A  knockout" description="knock out" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>