<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The antitumour drug ABTL0812 impairs neuroblastoma growth through endoplasmic 
reticulum stress-mediated autophagy and apoptosis.

Neuroblastoma is the leading cause of cancer death in children aged 1 to 4 
years. Particularly, five-year overall survival for high-risk neuroblastoma is 
below 50% with no curative options when refractory or relapsed. Most of current 
therapies target cell division and proliferation, thereby inducing DNA damage 
and programmed cell death. However, aggressive tumours often present alterations 
of these processes and are resistant to therapy. Therefore, exploring 
alternative pathways to induce tumour cell death will provide new therapeutic 
opportunities for these patients. In this study we aimed at testing the 
therapeutic potential of ABTL0812, a novel anticancer drug that induces 
cytotoxic autophagy to eliminate cancer cells, which is currently in phase II 
clinical trials of adult tumours. Here, we show that ABTL0812 impaired the 
viability of clinical representative neuroblastoma cell lines regardless of 
genetic alterations associated to bad prognosis and resistance to therapy. Oral 
administration of ABTL0812 to mice bearing neuroblastoma xenografts impaired 
tumour growth. Furthermore, our findings revealed that, in neuroblastoma, 
ABTL0812 induced cancer cell death via induction of endoplasmic reticulum 
stress, activation of the unfolded protein response, autophagy and apoptosis. 
Remarkably, ABTL0812 potentiated the antitumour activity of chemotherapies and 
differentiating agents such as irinotecan and 13-cis-retinoic acid. In 
conclusion, ABTL0812 distinctive mechanism of action makes it standout to be 
used alone or in combination in high-risk neuroblastoma patients.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1017~1041" text="neuroblastoma cell lines" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1168~1205" text="mice bearing neuroblastoma xenografts" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1308~1319" text="cancer cell" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="966~989" text="impaired the  viability" phenotype="cell survival" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1206~1229" text="impaired  tumour growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1300~1307,1320~1325" text="induced ... death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1374~1387,1419~1428" text="activation of ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1374~1387,1433~1442" text="activation of ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>