<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Soluble PD-L1 improved direct ARDS by reducing monocyte-derived macrophages.

Acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) is common in intensive care units 
(ICUs), although it is associated with high mortality, no effective 
pharmacological treatments are currently available. Despite being poorly 
understood, the role of programmed cell death protein 1 (PD-1) and PD-ligand 1 
(PD-L1) axis in ARDS may provide significant insights into the immunosuppressive 
mechanisms that occur after ARDS. In the present study, we observed that the 
level of soluble PD-L1 (sPD-L1), a potential activator of the PD-1 pathway, was 
upregulated in survivors of direct ARDS than in non-survivors. Administration of 
sPD-L1 in mice with direct ARDS relieved inflammatory lung injury and improved 
the survival rate, indicating the protective role of sPD-L1 in direct ARDS. 
Using high-throughput mass cytometry, we found a marked decrease in the number 
of lung monocyte-derived macrophages (MDMs) with proinflammatory markers, and 
the protective role of sPD-L1 diminished in ARDS mice with monocyte/macrophage 
depletion. Furthermore, PD-1 expression increased in the MDMs of patients and 
mice with direct ARDS. Finally, we showed that sPD-L1 induced MDM apoptosis in 
patients with direct ARDS. Taken together, our results demonstrated that the 
engagement of sPD-L1 on PD-1 expressing macrophages resulted in a decrease in 
pro-inflammatory macrophages and eventually improved direct ARDS. Our study 
identified a prognostic indicator for patients with direct ARDS and a potential 
target for therapeutic development in direct ARDS.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="712~733" text="mice with direct ARDS" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1062~1071" text="ARDS mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1239~1242" text="MDM" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1257~1282" text="patients with direct ARDS" experiment_type="organism" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1155~1171,1182~1198" text="MDMs of patients ... with direct ARDS" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C9" spans="1155~1162,1177~1198" text="MDMs of ... mice with direct ARDS" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1231~1238,1243~1252" text="induced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>