<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Suppression of poised oncogenes by ZMYND8 promotes chemo-sensitization.

The major challenge in chemotherapy lies in the gain of therapeutic resistance 
properties of cancer cells. The relatively small fraction of chemo-resistant 
cancer cells outgrows and are responsible for tumor relapse, with acquired 
invasiveness and stemness. We demonstrate that zinc-finger MYND type-8 (ZMYND8), 
a putative chromatin reader, suppresses stemness, drug resistance, and 
tumor-promoting genes, which are hallmarks of cancer. Reinstating ZMYND8 
suppresses chemotherapeutic drug doxorubicin-induced tumorigenic potential (at a 
sublethal dose) and drug resistance, thereby resetting the transcriptional 
program of cells to the epithelial state. The ability of ZMYND8 to 
chemo-sensitize doxorubicin-treated metastatic breast cancer cells by 
downregulating tumor-associated genes was further confirmed by transcriptome 
analysis. Interestingly, we observed that ZMYND8 overexpression in 
doxorubicin-treated cells stimulated those involved in a good prognosis in 
breast cancer. Consistently, sensitizing the cancer cells with ZMYND8 followed 
by doxorubicin treatment led to tumor regression in vivo and revert back the 
phenotypes associated with drug resistance and stemness. Intriguingly, ZMYND8 
modulates the bivalent or poised oncogenes through its association with KDM5C 
and EZH2, thereby chemo-sensitizing the cells to chemotherapy for better 
disease-free survival. Collectively, our findings indicate that poised chromatin 
is instrumental for the acquisition of chemo-resistance by cancer cells and 
propose ZMYND8 as a suitable epigenetic tool that can re-sensitize the 
chemo-refractory breast carcinoma.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="952~973" text="ZMYND8 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="797~827" text="metastatic breast cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="998~1003" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1099~1111" text="cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1183~1190" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>