<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mutant CFTR Drives TWIST1 mediated epithelial-mesenchymal transition.

Cystic fibrosis (CF) is a monogenetic disease resulting from mutations in the 
Cystic Fibrosis Transmembrane conductance Regulator (CFTR) gene encoding an 
anion channel. Recent evidence indicates that CFTR plays a role in other 
cellular processes, namely in development, cellular differentiation and wound 
healing. Accordingly, CFTR has been proposed to function as a tumour suppressor 
in a wide range of cancers. Along these lines, CF was recently suggested to be 
associated with epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT), a latent developmental 
process, which can be re-activated in fibrosis and cancer. However, it is 
unknown whether EMT is indeed active in CF and if EMT is triggered by 
dysfunctional CFTR itself or a consequence of secondary complications of CF. In 
this study, we investigated the occurrence of EMT in airways native tissue, 
primary cells and cell lines expressing mutant CFTR through the expression of 
epithelial and mesenchymal markers as well as EMT-associated transcription 
factors. Transepithelial electrical resistance, proliferation and regeneration 
rates, and cell resistance to TGF-β1induced EMT were also measured. CF 
tissues/cells expressing mutant CFTR displayed several signs of active EMT, 
namely: destructured epithelial proteins, defective cell junctions, increased 
levels of mesenchymal markers and EMT-associated transcription factors, 
hyper-proliferation and impaired wound healing. Importantly, we found evidence 
that the mutant CFTR triggered EMT was mediated by EMT-associated transcription 
factor TWIST1. Further, our data show that CF cells are over-sensitive to EMT 
but the CF EMT phenotype can be reversed by CFTR modulator drugs. Altogether, 
these results identify for the first time that EMT is intrinsically triggered by 
the absence of functional CFTR through a TWIST1 dependent mechanism and indicate 
that CFTR plays a direct role in EMT protection. This mechanistic link is a 
plausible explanation for the high incidence of fibrosis and cancer in CF, as 
well as for the role of CFTR as tumour suppressor protein.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="955~977" text="expressing mutant CFTR" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1247~1269" text="expressing mutant CFTR" description="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1551~1562" text="mutant CFTR" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="944~954" text="cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1241~1246" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1462~1481" text="hyper-proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1563~1576" text="triggered EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>