<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Arsenic trioxide induces macrophage autophagy and atheroprotection by regulating 
ROS-dependent TFEB nuclear translocation and AKT/mTOR pathway.

Inducing autophagy and inhibiting apoptosis may provide a therapeutic treatment 
for atherosclerosis (AS). For the treatment of progressive AS, arsenic trioxide 
(ATO) has been used to coat vascular stents. However, the effect of ATO on 
autophagy of macrophages is still unknown. Therefore, the aims of this study 
were to characterize the effects and the mechanism of actions of ATO on 
autophagy in macrophages. Our results showed that ATO-induced activation of 
autophagy was an earlier event than ATO-induced inhibition of the expression of 
apoptosis markers in macrophages and foam cells. Nuclear transcription factor EB 
(TFEB) prevents atherosclerosis by activating macrophage autophagy and promoting 
lysosomal biogenesis. Here, we report that ATO triggered the nuclear 
translocation of TFEB, which in turn promoted autophagy and 
autophagosome-lysosome fusion. Both the latter events were prevented by TFEB 
knockdown. Moreover, ATO decreased the p-AKT and p-mTOR in the PI3K/AKT/mTOR 
signaling pathway, thus inducing autophagy. Correspondingly, treatment with the 
autophagy inhibitor 3-methyladenine (3-MA) abolished the autophagy-inducing 
effects of ATO. Meanwhile, PI3K inhibitor (LY294002) and mTOR inhibitor 
(rapamycin) cooperated with ATO to induce autophagy. Furthermore, reactive 
oxygen species (ROS) were generated in macrophages after treatment with ATO. The 
ROS scavenger N-acetyl-1-cysteine (NAC) abolished ATO-induced nuclear 
translocation of TFEB, as well as changes in key molecules of the AKT/mTOR 
signaling pathway and downstream autophagy. More importantly, ATO promoted 
autophagy in the aorta of ApoE-/- mice and reduced atherosclerotic lesions in 
early AS, which were reversed by 3-MA treatment. In summary, our data indicated 
that ATO promoted ROS induction, which resulted in nuclear translocation of TFEB 
and inhibition of the PI3K/AKT/mTOR pathway. These actions ultimately promoted 
macrophage autophagy and reduced atherosclerotic lesions at early stages. These 
findings may provide a new perspective for the clinical treatment of early-stage 
atherosclerosis and should be further studied.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1060~1075" text="TFEB  knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1359~1386" text="mTOR inhibitor  (rapamycin)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1782~1789" text="ApoE-/-" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="714~725" text="macrophages" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="730~740" text="foam cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1490~1501" text="macrophages" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1773~1781,1790~1794" text="aorta of ... mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="2078~2088" text="macrophage" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="964~982" text="promoted autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="597~621" text="activation of  autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1168~1186" text="inducing autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1410~1426" text="induce autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1746~1765" text="promoted  autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E7" spans="2068~2076,2089~2098" text="promoted ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>