<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Targeted interplay between bacterial pathogens and host autophagy.

Due to the critical role played by autophagy in pathogen clearance, pathogens 
have developed diverse strategies to subvert it. Despite previous key findings 
of bacteria-autophagy interplay, asystems-level insight into selective targeting 
by the host and autophagy modulation by the pathogens is lacking. We predicted 
potential interactions between human autophagy proteins and effector proteins 
from 56 pathogenic bacterial species by identifying bacterial proteins predicted 
to have recognition motifs for selective autophagy receptors SQSTM1/p62, 
CALCOCO2/NDP52 and MAP1LC3/LC3. Using structure-based interaction prediction, we 
identified bacterial proteins capable to modify core autophagy components. Our 
analysis revealed that autophagy receptors in general potentially target mostly 
genus-specific proteins, and not those present in multiple genera. The 
complementarity between the predicted SQSTM1/p62 and CALCOCO2/NDP52 targets, 
which has been shown for Salmonella, Listeria and Shigella, could be observed 
across other pathogens. This complementarity potentially leaves the host more 
susceptible to chronic infections upon the mutation of autophagy receptors. 
Proteins derived from enterotoxigenic and non-toxigenic Bacillus outer membrane 
vesicles indicated that autophagy targets pathogenic proteins rather than 
non-pathogenic ones. We also observed apathogen-specific pattern as to which 
autophagy phase could be modulated by specific genera. We found intriguing 
examples of bacterial proteins that could modulate autophagy, and in turn being 
targeted by autophagy as ahost defense mechanism. We confirmed experimentally an 
interplay between a Salmonella protease, YhjJ and autophagy. Our comparative 
meta-analysis points out key commonalities and differences in how pathogens 
could affect autophagy and how autophagy potentially recognizes these pathogenic 
effectors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1604~1622" text="modulate autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1886~1902" text="affect autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>