<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cellular senescence contributes to radiation-induced hyposalivation by affecting 
the stem/progenitor cell niche.

Radiotherapy for head and neck cancer is associated with impairment of salivary 
gland function and consequent xerostomia, which has a devastating effect on the 
quality of life of the patients. The mechanism of radiation-induced salivary 
gland damage is not completely understood. Cellular senescence is a permanent 
state of cell cycle arrest accompanied by a secretory phenotype which 
contributes to inflammation and tissue deterioration. Genotoxic stresses, 
including radiation-induced DNA damage, are known to induce a senescence 
response. Here, we show that radiation induces cellular senescence 
preferentially in the salivary gland stem/progenitor cell niche of mouse models 
and patients. Similarly, salivary gland-derived organoids show increased 
expression of senescence markers and pro-inflammatory senescence-associated 
secretory phenotype (SASP) factors after radiation exposure. Clearance of 
senescent cells by selective removal of p16Ink4a-positive cells by the drug 
ganciclovir or the senolytic drug ABT263 lead to increased stem cell 
self-renewal capacity as measured by organoid formation efficiency. 
Additionally, pharmacological treatment with ABT263 in mice irradiated to the 
salivary glands mitigates tissue degeneration, thus preserving salivation. Our 
data suggest that senescence in the salivary gland stem/progenitor cell niche 
contributes to radiation-induced hyposalivation. Pharmacological targeting of 
senescent cells may represent a therapeutic strategy to prevent 
radiotherapy-induced xerostomia.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="744~801" text="salivary gland stem/progenitor cell niche of mouse models" experiment_type="cells" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="744~788,807~815" text="salivary gland stem/progenitor cell niche of ... patients" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="828~860" text="salivary gland-derived organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1165~1174" text="stem cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1213~1221" text="organoid" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1300~1304" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1029~1044" text="senescent cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="693~720" text="induces cellular senescence" phenotype="senescence" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1155~1164,1176~1197" text="increased ... self-renewal capacity" phenotype="self-renewal" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>