<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[CircCNTNAP3-TP53-positive feedback loop suppresses malignant progression of 
esophageal squamous cell carcinoma.

Mutation or downregulation of p53 (encoded by TP53) accelerates tumorigenesis 
and malignant progression in esophageal squamous cell carcinoma (ESCC). However, 
it is still unknown whether circular RNAs (circRNAs), a novel class of 
endogenous noncoding RNAs, participate in the regulation of this progress. In 
this study, we explored the expression profiles of circRNAs in three paired 
samples of ESCC and identified cCNTNAP3, which is a circRNA that originates from 
the CNTNAP3 gene transcript and is highly expressed in normal human esophageal 
tissue. However, we found that the cCNTNAP3 expression level was significantly 
downregulated in ESCC tissues. In vitro and in vivo studies revealed that 
cCNTNAP3 inhibited proliferation and increased apoptosis in p53 wild-type ESCC 
cells, but not in mutant cells. Mechanistically, we found that cCNTNAP3 promotes 
the expression of p53 by sponging miR-513a-5p. Rescue assay confirmed that the 
suppressive function of cCNTNAP3 was dependent on miR-513a-5p. We also observed 
that p53/RBM25 participated in the formation of cCNTNAP3, which implied the 
existence of a positive feedback loop between cCNTNAP3 and p53. Furthermore, the 
downregulation of cCNTNAP3 was significantly correlated with later T stage and 
thus can serve as an independent risk factor for the overall survival of 
patients with p53 wild-type ESCC. In conclusion, the cCNTNAP3-TP53 positive 
feedback loop may provide a potential target for the management of ESCC, which 
also reveals the important role of circRNAs in the regulation of p53.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="925~930" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="776~784" text="In vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="789~796" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="894~905" text="ESCC  cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="829~852" text="inhibited proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="857~876" text="increased apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>