<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Intravenous injection of the oncolytic virus M1 awakens antitumor T cells and 
overcomes resistance to checkpoint blockade.

Reversing the highly immunosuppressive tumor microenvironment (TME) is essential 
to achieve long-term efficacy with cancer immunotherapy. Despite the impressive 
clinical response to checkpoint blockade in multiple types of cancer, only a 
minority of patients benefit from this approach. Here, we report that the 
oncolytic virus M1 induces immunogenic tumor cell death and subsequently 
restores the ability of dendritic cells to prime antitumor T cells. Intravenous 
injection of M1 disrupts immune tolerance in the privileged TME, reprogramming 
immune-silent (cold) tumors into immune-inflamed (hot) tumors. M1 elicits potent 
CD8+ T cell-dependent therapeutic effects and establishes long-term antitumor 
immune memory in poorly immunogenic tumor models. Pretreatment with M1 
sensitizes refractory tumors to subsequent checkpoint blockade by boosting 
T-cell recruitment and upregulating the expression of PD-L1. These findings 
reveal the antitumor immunological mechanism of the M1 virus and indicated that 
oncolytic viruses are ideal cotreatments for checkpoint blockade immunotherapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="468~485" text="immunogenic tumor" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="539~554" text="dendritic cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="676~703" text="immune-silent (cold) tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="854~885" text="poorly immunogenic tumor models" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="920~937" text="refractory tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="460~467,486~496" text="induces ... cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>