<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Ischemia-induced ACSL4 activation contributes to ferroptosis-mediated tissue 
injury in intestinal ischemia/reperfusion.

Ferroptosis is a recently identified form of regulated cell death defined by the 
iron-dependent accumulation of lipid reactive oxygen species. Ferroptosis has 
been studied in various diseases such as cancer, Parkinson's disease, and 
stroke. However, the exact function and mechanism of ferroptosis in 
ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) injury, especially in the intestine, remains unknown. 
Considering the unique conditions required for ferroptosis, we hypothesize that 
ischemia promotes ferroptosis immediately after intestinal reperfusion. In 
contrast to conventional strategies employed in I/R studies, we focused on the 
ischemic phase. Here we verified ferroptosis by assessing proferroptotic changes 
after ischemia along with protein and lipid peroxidation levels during 
reperfusion. The inhibition of ferroptosis by liproxstatin-1 ameliorated 
I/R-induced intestinal injury. Acyl-CoA synthetase long-chain family member 4 
(ACSL4), which is a key enzyme that regulates lipid composition, has been shown 
to contribute to the execution of ferroptosis, but its role in I/R needs 
clarification. In the present study, we used rosiglitazone (ROSI) and siRNA to 
inhibit ischemia/hypoxia-induced ACSL4 in vivo and in vitro. The results 
demonstrated that ACSL4 inhibition before reperfusion protected against 
ferroptosis and cell death. Further investigation revealed that special protein 
1 (Sp1) was a crucial transcription factor that increased ACSL4 transcription by 
binding to the ACSL4 promoter region. Collectively, this study demonstrates that 
ferroptosis is closely associated with intestinal I/R injury, and that ACSL4 has 
a critical role in this lethal process. Sp1 is an important factor in promoting 
ACSL4 expression. These results suggest a unique and effective mechanistic 
approach for intestinal I/R injury prevention and treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1278~1286,1288~1295,1321~1326" text="siRNA to ... inhibit ... ACSL4" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1380~1396" text="ACSL4 inhibition" description="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1327~1334" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1339~1347" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="917~942" text="inhibition of ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1416~1446" text="protected against  ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1416~1433,1451~1461" text="protected against ... cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>