<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cell cycle arrest in mitosis promotes interferon-induced necroptosis.

Resistance to apoptosis is a hallmark of cancer and deregulation of apoptosis 
often leads to chemoresistance. Therefore, new approaches to target 
apoptosis-resistant cancer cells are crucial for the development of directed 
cancer therapies. In the present study, we investigated the effect of cell cycle 
regulators on interferon (IFN)-induced necroptosis as an alternative cell death 
mechanism to overcome apoptosis resistance. Here, we report a novel combination 
treatment of IFNs with cell cycle arrest-inducing compounds that induce 
necroptosis in apoptosis-resistant cancer cells and elucidate the underlying 
molecular mechanisms. Combination treatment of IFNs (i.e. IFNβ) with inhibitors 
of the cell cycle (e.g. vinorelbine (VNR), nocodazole (Noc), polo-like kinase-1 
(Plk-1) inhibitor BI 6727) co-operate to induce necroptotic cell death upon 
caspase inactivation. The mode of cell death was confirmed by pharmacological 
inhibition and siRNA-mediated downregulation of the key necroptotic factors 
receptor-interacting protein (RIP) kinase 3 (RIP3) and mixed-lineage kinase-like 
(MLKL) in various cell lines. Mechanistically, we show that necroptosis upon 
VNR/IFNβ/zVAD.fmk treatment is RIP1-independent but relies on IFNβ-induced gene 
expression of Z-DNA-binding protein 1 (ZBP1) as shown by quantitative RT-PCR and 
genetic knockdown experiments. Interestingly, we find that RIP3 is 
phosphorylated in response to compounds that trigger mitotic arrest, even in the 
absence of IFNβ signaling and necroptosis induction. Together, the 
identification of a novel combination treatment that triggers necroptosis has 
implications for the development of molecular-targeted therapies to circumvent 
apoptosis resistance and point to an underestimated role of cell cycle 
regulation in cell death signaling.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="993~1020,1116~1175" text="pharmacological  inhibition ... (RIP) kinase 3 (RIP3) and mixed-lineage kinase-like  (MLKL)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1025~1054,1116~1175" text="siRNA-mediated downregulation ... (RIP) kinase 3 (RIP3) and mixed-lineage kinase-like  (MLKL)" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="629~661" text="apoptosis-resistant cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1187~1197" text="cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="606~625" text="induce  necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="895~924" text="induce necroptotic cell death" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1229~1240" text="necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1523~1545" text="trigger mitotic arrest" activity="causes" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>