<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Macrophage-derived CCL5 facilitates immune escape of colorectal cancer cells via 
the p65/STAT3-CSN5-PD-L1 pathway.

Infiltrated macrophages are an important constituent of the tumor 
microenvironment and play roles in tumor initiation and progression by promoting 
immune evasion. However, the molecular mechanism by which macrophage-derived 
cytokines foster immune escape of colorectal cancer (CRC) is unclear. Here, we 
demonstrated that macrophage infiltration induced by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) or 
a high-cholesterol diet (HCD) significantly promoted CRC growth. Similarly, LPS 
and poly (I:C) remarkably increased the volume of CT26 cell allograft tumors. 
C-C motif chemokine ligand 5 (CCL5), which is secreted by macrophages, inhibited 
T-cell-mediated killing of HT29 cells and promoted immune escape by stabilizing 
PD-L1 in vitro and in vivo. Mechanistically, CCL5 resulted in formation of 
nuclear factor kappa-B p65/STAT3 complexes, which bound to the COP9 signalosome 
5 (CSN5) promoter, leading to its upregulation. Moreover, CSN5 modulated the 
deubiquitination and stability of PD-L1. High expression of CSN5 in CRC was 
associated with significantly shorter survival. Furthermore, compound-15 was 
identified as an inhibitor of CSN5, and destabilized PD-L1 to alleviate the 
tumor burden. Our results suggest that the novel CCL5-p65/STAT3-CSN5-PD-L1 
signaling axis is significantly activated by LPS or HCD-driven macrophage 
infiltration in an animal model of CRC, which likely has therapeutic and 
prognostic implications for human cancers.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="559~562" text="CRC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="637~663" text="CT26 cell allograft tumors" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="775~785" text="HT29 cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="835~843" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="848~855" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1466~1485" text="animal model of CRC" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="550~558,563~569" text="promoted ... growth" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>