<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[STAT3 dictates β-cell apoptosis by modulating PTEN in streptozocin-induced 
hyperglycemia.

Insufficient pancreatic β-cell mass or insulin-producing β-cells are implicated 
in all forms of diabetes mellitus. However, the molecular mechanisms underlying 
β-cell destruction are complex and not fully defined. Here we observed that 
activation of STAT3 is intensely and specifically inhibited in β-cells under 
hyperglycemic conditions. By knocking out STAT3 specifically in mouse β-cells, 
we found that the loss of STAT3 sensitized mice to three low doses of STZ 
stimulation resulting in hyperglycemia. Mechanistically, accumulating PTEN, 
induced by STAT3 deficiency, directly represses phosphorylation of AKT, which 
negatively modulates transcription factor activation, dysregulates β-cell 
function, positively promotes apoptotic signaling, and finally induces β-cell 
apoptosis. Notably, the defective secretion of insulin and β-cells apoptosis was 
completely rescued by PTEN ablation in STAT3-null islets or PTEN inhibitor 
bpv(phen) treatment. Thus our data suggest that STAT3 is a vital modulator of 
β-cell survival and function, highlighting a critical role for STAT3 in the 
negative regulation of PTEN-AKT signaling pathway associated with β-cell 
dysfunction and apoptosis.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="438~486" text="knocking out STAT3 specifically in mouse β-cells" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="507~520" text="loss of STAT3" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="978~991" text="PTEN ablation" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="995~1005" text="STAT3-null" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1016~1051" text="PTEN inhibitor  bpv(phen) treatment" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="532~536" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="866~872" text="β-cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="933~940" text="β-cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1006~1012" text="islets" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="858~865,874~883" text="induces ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="941~974" text="apoptosis was  completely rescued" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>