<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[LZTR1 facilitates polyubiquitination and degradation of RAS-GTPases.

Leucine zipper-like transcriptional regulator 1 (LZTR1) encodes a member of the 
BTB-Kelch superfamily, which interacts with the Cullin3 (CUL3)-based E3 
ubiquitin ligase complex. Mutations in LZTR1 have been identified in 
glioblastoma, schwannomatosis, and Noonan syndrome. However, the functional role 
of LZTR1 in carcinogenesis or human development is not fully understood. Here, 
we demonstrate that LZTR1 facilitates the polyubiquitination and degradation of 
RAS via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway, leading to the inhibition of the 
RAS/MAPK signaling. The polyubiquitination and degradation of RAS was also 
observed in cells expressing MRAS, HRAS, NRAS, and KRAS as well as oncogenic RAS 
mutants and inhibited the activation of ERK1/2 and cell growth. In vivo 
ubiquitination assays showed that MRAS-K127 and HRAS-K170 were ubiquitinated by 
LZTR1 and that the polyubiquitinated-chains contained mainly Ub-K48, K63, and 
K33-linked chains, suggesting its possible involvement in autophagy. 
Immunoprecipitation analyses showed the interaction of LZTR1 and RAS-GTPases 
with autophagy-related proteins, including LC3B and SQSTM1/p62. Co-expression of 
LZTR1 and RAS increased the expression of lipidated form of LC3B. However, 
long-term treatment with chloroquine had little effect on RAS protein levels, 
suggesting that the contribution of autophagy to LZTR1-mediated RAS degradation 
is minimal. Taken together, these results show that LZTR1 functions as a "RAS 
killer protein" mainly via the ubiquitin-proteasome pathway regardless of the 
type of RAS GTPase, controlling downstream signal transduction. Our results also 
suggest a possible association of LZTR1 and RAS-GTPases with the autophagy. 
These findings provide clues for the elucidation of the mechanisms of RAS 
degradation and regulation of the RAS/MAPK signaling cascade.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1216~1247" text="Co-expression of  LZTR1 and RAS" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="701~706" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="783~792,822~833" text="inhibited ... cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>