<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Membrane-bound TNF mediates microtubule-targeting chemotherapeutics-induced 
cancer cytolysis via juxtacrine inter-cancer-cell death signaling.

Microtubule-targeting agents (MTAs) are a class of most widely used 
chemotherapeutics and their mechanism of action has long been assumed to be 
mitotic arrest of rapidly dividing tumor cells. In contrast to such notion, here 
we show-in many cancer cell types-MTAs function by triggering membrane TNF 
(memTNF)-mediated cancer-cell-to-cancer-cell killing, which differs greatly from 
other non-MTA cell-cycle-arresting agents. The killing is through programmed 
cell death (PCD), either in way of necroptosis when RIP3 kinase is expressed, or 
of apoptosis in its absence. Mechanistically, MTAs induce memTNF transcription 
via the JNK-cJun signaling pathway. With respect to chemotherapy regimens, our 
results establish that memTNF-mediated killing is significantly augmented by IAP 
antagonists (Smac mimetics) in a broad spectrum of cancer types, and with their 
effects most prominently manifested in patient-derived xenograft (PDX) models in 
which cell-cell contacts are highly reminiscent of human tumors. Therefore, our 
finding indicates that memTNF can serve as a marker for patient responsiveness, 
and Smac mimetics will be effective adjuvants for MTA chemotherapeutics. The 
present study reframes our fundamental biochemical understanding of how MTAs 
take advantage of the natural tight contact of tumor cells and utilize 
memTNF-mediated death signaling to induce the entire tumor regression.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="966~996" text="broad spectrum of cancer types" experiment_type="tumour" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1053~1091" text="patient-derived xenograft (PDX) models" experiment_type="xenotransplantation" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="389~400" text="cancer cell" species="not stated" experiment_type="transformed cell line" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="609~619" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="644~655" text="necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="694~703" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>