<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Fenretinide induces a new form of dynamin-dependent cell death in pediatric 
sarcoma.

Alveolar rhabdomyosarcoma (aRMS) is a highly malicious childhood malignancy 
characterized by specific chromosomal translocations mostly encoding the 
oncogenic transcription factor PAX3-FOXO1 and therefore also referred to as 
fusion-positive RMS (FP-RMS). Previously, we have identified fenretinide 
(retinoic acid p-hydroxyanilide) to affect PAX3-FOXO1 expression levels as well 
as FP-RMS cell viability. Here, we characterize the mode of action of 
fenretinide in more detail. First, we demonstrate that fenretinide-induced 
generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS) depends on complex II of the 
mitochondrial respiratory chain, since ROS scavenging as well as complexing of 
iron completely abolished cell death. Second, we co-treated cells with a range 
of pharmacological inhibitors of specific cell death pathways including z-vad 
(apoptosis), necrostatin-1 (necroptosis), 3-methyladenine (3-MA) (autophagy), 
and ferrostatin-1 (ferroptosis) together with fenretinide. Surprisingly, none of 
these inhibitors was able to prevent cell death. Also genetic depletion of key 
players in the apoptotic and necroptotic pathway (BAK, BAX, and RIPK1) confirmed 
the pharmacological data. Interestingly however, electron microscopy of 
fenretinide-treated cells revealed an excessive accumulation of cytoplasmic 
vacuoles, which were distinct from autophagosomes. Further flow cytometry and 
fluorescence microscopy experiments suggested a hyperstimulation of 
macropinocytosis, leading to an accumulation of enlarged early and late 
endosomes. Surprisingly, pharmacological inhibition as well as genetic depletion 
of large dynamin GTPases completely abolished fenretinide-induced vesicle 
formation and subsequent cell death, suggesting a new form of dynamin-dependent 
programmed cell death. Taken together, our data identify a new form of cell 
death mediated through the production of ROS by fenretinide treatment, 
highlighting the value of this compound for treatment of sarcoma patients 
including FP-RMS.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1145~1165,1221~1224" text="genetic depletion of ... BAK" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1145~1165,1226~1229" text="genetic depletion of ... BAX" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1145~1165,1235~1240" text="genetic depletion of ... RIPK1" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="831~836" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1346~1351" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="787~807" text="abolished cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1082~1086,1108~1138" text="none ... was able to prevent cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1742~1751,1806~1816" text="abolished ... cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>