<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SIRT3 promotes lipophagy and chaperon-mediated autophagy to protect hepatocytes 
against lipotoxicity.

Lipophagy is a lysosomal lipolytic pathway that complements the actions of 
cytosolic neutral lipases. Chaperon-mediated autophagy (CMA) triggers lipid 
droplets (LDs) breakdown, to initiate lipolysis via either cytosolic lipases or 
macroautophagy. SIRT3, a mitochondrial NAD+-dependent deacetylase, regulates the 
acetylation status and activity of many substrates involving in energy 
metabolism. However, the role of SIRT3 in regulating lipophagy is controversial. 
The current study showed that SIRT3 expression was decreased and the 
macroautophagy flux was blocked in the primary hepatocytes from high-fat diet 
fed mice and P/O (palmitic acid and oleic acid mixture) treated AML12 mouse 
hepatocytes, compared with the corresponding controls. SIRT3 overexpression 
promoted macroautophagy in LDs from P/O-treated hepatocytes through activating 
AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) and unc-51-like kinase 1, to boost LDs 
digestion. Gain of SIRT3 expression stimulated the formation of 
lysosome-associated membrane protein 2A (LAMP-2A)-heat shock cognate 71 kDa 
protein (HSC70)-perilipin-2 (PLN2) complex, to promote CMA process and reduce 
the stability of LDs in hepatocytes. Moreover, SIRT3 reduced the expression of 
stearoyl-CoA desaturase 1, to suppress lipogenesis. In addition, SIRT3 
overexpression promoted LDs dispersion on detyrosinated microtubules, and 
directly deacetylated long-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase to enhance mitochondrial 
energetics. Taken together, SIRT3 ameliorates lipotoxicity in hepatocytes, which 
might be a potential target for the treatment of nonalcoholic fatty liver 
disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="855~875" text="SIRT3 overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1044~1068" text="Gain of SIRT3 expression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1399~1420" text="SIRT3  overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="683~702" text="primary hepatocytes" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="727~731" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="787~811" text="AML12 mouse  hepatocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="925~936" text="hepatocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1278~1289" text="hepatocytes" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>