<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Resolvin D1 promotes the targeting and clearance of necroptotic cells.

Inflammation-resolution is a protective response that is mediated by specialized 
pro-resolving mediators (SPMs). The clearance of dead cells or efferocytosis is 
a critical cellular program of inflammation-resolution. Impaired efferocytosis 
can lead to tissue damage in prevalent human diseases, like atherosclerosis. 
Therefore understanding mechanisms associated with swift clearance of dead cells 
is of utmost clinical importance. Recently, the accumulation of necroptotic 
cells (NCs) was observed in human plaques and we postulated that this is due to 
defective clearance programs. Here we present evidence that NCs are 
inefficiently taken up by macrophages because they have increased surface 
expression of a well-known "don't eat me" signal called CD47. High levels of 
CD47 on NCs stimulated RhoA-pMLC signaling in macrophages that promoted 
"nibbling", rather than whole-cell engulfment of NCs. Anti-CD47 blocking 
antibodies limited RhoA-p-MLC signaling and promoted whole-cell NC engulfment. 
Treatment with anti-CD47 blocking antibodies to Ldlr-/- mice with established 
atherosclerosis decreased necrotic cores, limited the accumulation of plaque NCs 
and increased lesional SPMs, including Resolvin D1 (RvD1) compared with IgG 
controls. Mechanistically, RvD1 promoted whole-cell engulfment of NCs by 
decreasing RhoA signaling and activating CDC42. RvD1 specifically targeted NCs 
for engulfment by facilitating the release of the well-known "eat me signal" 
called calreticulin from macrophages in a CDC42 dependent manner. Lastly, RvD1 
enhanced the clearance of NCs in advanced murine plaques. Together, these 
results suggest new molecules and signaling associated with the clearance of 
NCs, provide a new paradigm for the regulation of inflammation-resolution, and 
offer a potential treatment strategy for diseases where NCs underpin the 
pathology.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1130~1137" text="Ldlr-/-" description="knock out" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1138~1142" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>