<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Lactobacillus accelerates ISCs regeneration to protect the integrity of 
intestinal mucosa through activation of STAT3 signaling pathway induced by LPLs 
secretion of IL-22.

The regeneration of intestinal epithelial are maintained by continuous 
differentiation and proliferation of intestinal stem cells (ISCs) under 
physiological and pathological conditions. However, little is known about the 
regulatory effect of intestinal microbiota on its recovery ability to repair 
damaged mucosal barrier. In this study, we established intestinal organoids and 
lamina propria lymphocytes (LPLs) co-cultured system, plus mice experiments, to 
explore the protective effect of Lactobacillus reuteri D8 on integrity of 
intestinal mucosa. We found that only live L. reuteri D8 was effective in 
protecting the morphology of intestinal organoids and normal proliferation of 
epithelial stained with EdU under TNF-α treatment, which was also further 
verified in mice experiments. L. reuteri D8 colonized in the intestinal mucosa 
and ameliorated intestinal mucosa damage caused by DSS treatment, including 
improvement of body weight, colon length, pathological change, and proliferation 
level. The repair process stimulated by L. reuteri D8 was also accompanied with 
increased numbers of Lgr5+ and lysozyme+ cells both in intestinal organoids and 
mice intestine. Furthermore, we demonstrated that D8 metabolite 
indole-3-aldehyde stimulated LPLs to secret IL-22 through aryl hydrocarbon 
receptor (AhR) and then induced phosphorylation of STAT3 to accelerate 
proliferation of intestinal epithelial, thus recovering damaged intestinal 
mucosa. Our findings indicate L. reuteri protects intestinal barrier and 
activates intestinal epithelial proliferation, which sheds light on treatment 
approaches for intestinal inflammation based on ISCs with probiotics 
Lactobacillus and daily probiotic consumption in heath foods.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="818~838" text="intestinal organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="868~878" text="epithelial" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="955~959" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1039~1056" text="intestinal mucosa" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1318~1338" text="intestinal organoids" experiment_type="organoid culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1344~1358" text="mice intestine" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1284~1309" text="Lgr5+ and lysozyme+ cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1438~1442" text="LPLs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1574~1595" text="intestinal epithelial" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C9" spans="1621~1639" text="intestinal  mucosa" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C10" spans="1717~1738" text="intestinal epithelial" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="789~799,850~863" text="protecting ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1100~1114,1167~1180" text="improvement of ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1545~1570" text="accelerate  proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1707~1716,1739~1752" text="activates ... proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>