<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Microglial autophagy defect causes parkinson disease-like symptoms by 
accelerating inflammasome activation in mice.

Microglial activation-induced neuroinflammation is closely associated with the 
development of Parkinson disease (PD). Macroautophagy/autophagy regulates many 
biological processes, but the role of autophagy in microglial activation during 
PD development remains largely unclear. In this study, we showed that deletion 
of microglial Atg5 caused PD-like symptoms in mice, characterized by impairment 
in motor coordination and cognitive learning, loss of tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) 
neurons, enhancement of neuroinflammation and reduction in dopamine levels in 
the striatum. Mechanistically, we found that inhibition of autophagy led to 
NLRP3 (NLR family pyrin domain containing 3) inflammasome activation via PDE10A 
(phosphodiesterase 10A)-cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) signaling in 
microglia, and the sequential upregulation of downstream IL1B/IL-1β in turn 
increased the expression of MIF (macrophage migration inhibitory factor 
[glycosylation-inhibiting factor]), a pro-inflammatory cytokine. Inhibition of 
NLRP3 inflammasome activation by administration of MCC950, a specific inhibitor 
for NLRP3, decreased MIF expression and neuroinflammatory levels, and rescued 
the loss of TH neurons in the substantial nigra (SN). Interestingly, we found 
that serum MIF levels in PD patients were significantly elevated. Taken 
together, our results reveal an important role of autophagy in microglial 
activation-driven PD-like symptoms, thus providing potential targets for the 
clinical treatment of PD. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="429~457" text="deletion  of microglial Atg5" description="conditional knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1177~1234" text="administration of MCC950, a specific inhibitor  for NLRP3" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="485~489" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>