<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Defective endoplasmic reticulum-mitochondria contacts and bioenergetics in 
SEPN1-related myopathy.

SEPN1-related myopathy (SEPN1-RM) is a muscle disorder due to mutations of the 
SEPN1 gene, which is characterized by muscle weakness and fatigue leading to 
scoliosis and life-threatening respiratory failure. Core lesions, focal areas of 
mitochondria depletion in skeletal muscle fibers, are the most common 
histopathological lesion. SEPN1-RM underlying mechanisms and the precise role of 
SEPN1 in muscle remained incompletely understood, hindering the development of 
biomarkers and therapies for this untreatable disease. To investigate the 
pathophysiological pathways in SEPN1-RM, we performed metabolic studies, calcium 
and ATP measurements, super-resolution and electron microscopy on in vivo and in 
vitro models of SEPN1 deficiency as well as muscle biopsies from SEPN1-RM 
patients. Mouse models of SEPN1 deficiency showed marked alterations in 
mitochondrial physiology and energy metabolism, suggesting that SEPN1 controls 
mitochondrial bioenergetics. Moreover, we found that SEPN1 was enriched at the 
mitochondria-associated membranes (MAM), and was needed for calcium transients 
between ER and mitochondria, as well as for the integrity of ER-mitochondria 
contacts. Consistently, loss of SEPN1 in patients was associated with 
alterations in body composition which correlated with the severity of muscle 
weakness, and with impaired ER-mitochondria contacts and low ATP levels. Our 
results indicate a role of SEPN1 as a novel MAM protein involved in 
mitochondrial bioenergetics. They also identify a systemic bioenergetic 
component in SEPN1-RM and establish mitochondria as a novel therapeutic target. 
This role of SEPN1 contributes to explain the fatigue and core lesions in 
skeletal muscle as well as the body composition abnormalities identified as part 
of the SEPN1-RM phenotype. Finally, these results point out to an unrecognized 
interplay between mitochondrial bioenergetics and ER homeostasis in skeletal 
muscle. They could therefore pave the way to the identification of biomarkers 
and therapeutic drugs for SEPN1-RM and for other disorders in which muscle 
ER-mitochondria cross-talk are impaired.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="914~930" text="SEPN1 deficiency" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="898~910" text="Mouse models" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>