<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mitochondrial 4-HNE derived from MAO-A promotes mitoCa(2+) overload in chronic 
postischemic cardiac remodeling.

Chronic remodeling postmyocardial infarction consists in various maladaptive 
changes including interstitial fibrosis, cardiomyocyte death and mitochondrial 
dysfunction that lead to heart failure (HF). Reactive aldehydes such as 
4-hydroxynonenal (4-HNE) are critical mediators of mitochondrial dysfunction but 
the sources of mitochondrial 4-HNE in cardiac diseases together with its 
mechanisms of action remain poorly understood. Here, we evaluated whether the 
mitochondrial enzyme monoamine oxidase-A (MAO-A), which generates H2O2 as a 
by-product of catecholamine metabolism, is a source of deleterious 4-HNE in HF. 
We found that MAO-A activation increased mitochondrial ROS and promoted local 
4-HNE production inside the mitochondria through cardiolipin peroxidation in 
primary cardiomyocytes. Deleterious effects of MAO-A/4-HNE on cardiac 
dysfunction were prevented by activation of mitochondrial aldehyde dehydrogenase 
2 (ALDH2), the main enzyme for 4-HNE metabolism. Mechanistically, MAO-A-derived 
4-HNE bound to newly identified targets VDAC and MCU to promote ER-mitochondria 
contact sites and MCU higher-order complex formation. The resulting 
mitochondrial Ca2+ accumulation participated in mitochondrial respiratory 
dysfunction and loss of membrane potential, as shown with the protective effects 
of the MCU inhibitor, RU360. Most interestingly, these findings were 
recapitulated in a chronic model of ischemic remodeling where pharmacological or 
genetic inhibition of MAO-A protected the mice from 4-HNE accumulation, MCU 
oligomer formation and Ca2+ overload, thus mitigating ventricular dysfunction. 
To our knowledge, these are the first evidences linking MAO-A activation to 
mitoCa2+ mishandling through local 4-HNE production, contributing to energetic 
failure and postischemic remodeling.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1568~1583,1596~1615" text="pharmacological ... inhibition of MAO-A" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1588~1615" text="genetic inhibition of MAO-A" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="895~917" text="primary cardiomyocytes" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1630~1634" text="mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>