<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RIPK1/RIPK3/MLKL-mediated necroptosis contributes to compression-induced rat 
nucleus pulposus cells death.


The aim of this study was to systematically investigate the role of necroptosis 
in compression-induced rat nucleus pulposus (NP) cells death, as well as explore 
the underlying mechanisms involved. Rat NP cells underwent various periods of 
exposure to 1.0 MPa pressure. Cell viability and cell death were quantified by 
using cell counting kit-8 (CCK-8), and Calcein-AM/propidium iodine (PI) staining 
respectively. Necroptosis-associated target molecules receptor-interacing 
protein kinase 1 (RIPK1), phosphorylated RIPK1 (pRIPK1), receptor-interacing 
protein kinase 3 (RIPK3), phosphorylated RIPK3 (pRIPK3) and mixed lineage kinase 
domain-like (MLKL) were analyzed by Western-blot and RT-PCR. NP cells were also 
examined for morphological and ultrastructural changes, which can indicate 
necroptosis. To indirectly establish the presence of necroptosis, the RIPK1 
specific inhibitor necrostatin-1 (Nec-1), RIPK3 inhibitor GSK'872, MLKL 
inhibitor necrosulfonamide (NSA) and small interfering RNA (siRNA) were 
utilized. The results established necroptosis was taking place in NP cells. The 
level of necroptosis increased in a time-dependent manner, and this effect was 
reduced by Nec-1 in vitro. Additionally, NP cells death were significantly 
attenuated following treatment with Nec-1, GSK'872 or NSA. SiRNA-induced 
knockdown of RIPK3 or MLKL increased cell survival rate, while knockdown of 
RIPK1 resulted in a decreased cell survival rate. In summary, 
RIPK1/RIPK3/MLKL-mediated necroptosis may play an important role in NP cells 
death induced by continuous mechanical stress. Treatment strategies which aim to 
regulate necroptosis may prove beneficial, by both reducing NP cells death and 
slowing IVD degeneration.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="976~1023" text="RIPK1  specific inhibitor necrostatin-1 (Nec-1)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1025~1048" text="RIPK3 inhibitor GSK&apos;872" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1050~1088" text="MLKL  inhibitor necrosulfonamide (NSA)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1425~1458" text="SiRNA-induced  knockdown of RIPK3" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1425~1438,1440~1452,1462~1466" text="SiRNA-induced ... knockdown of ... MLKL" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1503~1522" text="knockdown of  RIPK1" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="309~321" text="Rat NP cells" experiment_type="cells" species="rat" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1195~1203" text="NP cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1307~1315" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1331~1339" text="NP cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1163~1174" text="necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1340~1350,1366~1376" text="death were ... attenuated" phenotype="cell death" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1467~1490" text="increased cell survival" phenotype="cell survival" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1537~1560" text="decreased cell survival" phenotype="cell survival" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>