<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Critical contribution of RIPK1 mediated mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative 
stress to compression-induced rat nucleus pulposus cells necroptosis and 
apoptosis.

The aim of this study was to investigate whether RIPK1 mediated mitochondrial 
dysfunction and oxidative stress contributed to compression-induced nucleus 
pulposus (NP) cells necroptosis and apoptosis, together with the interplay 
relationship between necroptosis and apoptosis in vitro. Rat NP cells underwent 
various periods of 1.0 MPa compression. To determine whether compression 
affected mitochondrial function, we evaluated the mitochondrial membrane 
potential, mitochondrial permeability transition pore (mPTP), mitochondrial 
ultrastructure and ATP content. Oxidative stress-related indicators reactive 
oxygen species, superoxide dismutase and malondialdehyde were also assessed. To 
verify the relevance between oxidative stress and necroptosis together with 
apoptosis, RIPK1 inhibitor necrostatin-1(Nec-1), mPTP inhibitor cyclosporine A 
(CsA), antioxidants and small interfering RNA technology were utilized. The 
results established that compression elicited a time-dependent mitochondrial 
dysfunction and elevated oxidative stress. Nec-1 and CsA restored mitochondrial 
function and reduced oxidative stress, which corresponded to decreased 
necroptosis and apoptosis. CsA down-regulated mitochondrial cyclophilin D 
expression, but had little effects on RIPK1 expression and pRIPK1 activation. 
Additionally, we found that Nec-1 largely blocked apoptosis; whereas, the 
apoptosis inhibitor Z-VAD-FMK increased RIPK1 expression and pRIPK1 activation, 
and coordinated regulation of necroptosis and apoptosis enabled NP cells 
survival more efficiently. In contrast to Nec-1, SiRIPK1 exacerbated 
mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress. In summary, RIPK1-mediated 
mitochondrial dysfunction and oxidative stress play a crucial role in NP cells 
necroptosis and apoptosis during compression injury. The synergistic regulation 
of necroptosis and apoptosis may exert more beneficial effects on NP cells 
survival, and ultimately delaying or even retarding intervertebral disc 
degeneration.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="952~988" text="RIPK1 inhibitor necrostatin-1(Nec-1)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1762~1769" text="SiRIPK1" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="456~468" text="Rat NP cells" experiment_type="cells" species="rat" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1703~1711" text="NP cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1318~1340" text="decreased  necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1318~1327,1345~1354" text="decreased ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1695~1702,1713~1721" text="enabled ... survival" phenotype="cell survival" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1655~1680" text="regulation of necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1655~1668,1685~1694" text="regulation of ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>