<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BDNF-mediated mitophagy alleviates high-glucose-induced brain microvascular 
endothelial cell injury.

Endothelial cell dysfunction and diabetic vascular complications are 
intrinsically linked. Although BDNF plays a protective role in cerebral 
microvascular complications caused by diabetes, the mechanisms of this activity 
are not fully clear. In this study, we investigated the role of BDNF in the 
hyperglycemic injury of BMECs and its associated intracellular signal 
transduction pathways. BMECs were treated with 33 mM glucose to imitate the 
endothelium under hyperglycemic conditions. The high-glucose treatment caused 
cell dysfunction, as evaluated by oxidative stress and cell apoptosis, which 
could be alleviated by BDNF. In addition, BDNF preserved mitochondrial function 
as assessed by mPTP opening, mitochondrial membrane potential, calcium content, 
and mitochondrial biogenesis markers. Western blot analysis of LC3-II, p62, and 
TOMM20 and the detection of mRFP-GFP-LC3 adenovirus for autophagy flux revealed 
that BDNF enhanced autophagy flux. Furthermore, BDNF activated mitophagy, which 
was confirmed by the observed colocalization of LC3-II with BNIP3 and from 
transmission electron microscopy observations. The HIF-1α/BNIP3 signaling 
pathway was associated with BDNF/TrkB-induced mitophagy. In addition, 
BDNF-induced mitophagy played a protective role against BMEC damage under 
hyperglycemia. Thus, the results of this study suggest that 
BDNF/TrkB/HIF-1α/BNIP3-mediated mitophagy protects BMECs from hyperglycemia.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="686~690" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="691~700" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1043~1066" text="enhanced autophagy flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1086~1105" text="activated mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1303~1320" text="induced mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1341~1358" text="induced mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>