<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Lactate accelerates vascular calcification through NR4A1-regulated mitochondrial 
fission and BNIP3-related mitophagy.

Arterial media calcification is related to mitochondrial dysfunction. Protective 
mitophagy delays the progression of vascular calcification. We previously 
reported that lactate accelerates osteoblastic phenotype transition of VSMC 
through BNIP3-mediated mitophagy suppression. In this study, we investigated the 
specific links between lactate, mitochondrial homeostasis, and vascular 
calcification. Ex vivo, alizarin S red and von Kossa staining in addition to 
measurement of calcium content, RUNX2, and BMP-2 protein levels revealed that 
lactate accelerated arterial media calcification. We demonstrated that lactate 
induced mitochondrial fission and apoptosis in aortas, whereas mitophagy was 
suppressed. In VSMCs, lactate increased NR4A1 expression, leading to activation 
of DNA-PKcs and p53. Lactate induced Drp1 migration to the mitochondria and 
enhanced mitochondrial fission through NR4A1. Western blot analysis of LC3-II 
and p62 and mRFP-GFP-LC3 adenovirus detection showed that NR4A1 knockdown was 
involved in enhanced autophagy flux. Furthermore, NR4A1 inhibited BNIP3-related 
mitophagy, which was confirmed by TOMM20 and BNIP3 protein levels, and LC3-II 
co-localization with TOMM20. The excessive fission and deficient mitophagy 
damaged mitochondrial structure and impaired respiratory function, determined by 
mPTP opening rate, mitochondrial membrane potential, mitochondrial morphology 
under TEM, ATP production, and OCR, which was reversed by NR4A1 silencing. 
Mechanistically, lactate enhanced fission but halted mitophagy via activation of 
the NR4A1/DNA-PKcs/p53 pathway, evoking apoptosis, finally accelerating 
osteoblastic phenotype transition of VSMC and calcium deposition. This study 
suggests that the NR4A1/DNA-PKcs/p53 pathway is involved in the mechanism by 
which lactate accelerates vascular calcification, partly through excessive 
Drp-mediated mitochondrial fission and BNIP3-related mitophagy deficiency.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1119~1134" text="NR4A1 knockdown" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1595~1610" text="NR4A1 silencing" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="793~799" text="aortas" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="839~844" text="VSMCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1805~1809" text="VSMC" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="746~753,780~789" text="induced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="809~834" text="mitophagy was  suppressed" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1152~1175" text="enhanced autophagy flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1196~1205,1221~1230" text="inhibited ... mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1659~1675" text="halted mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1727~1744" text="evoking apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>