<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Matrix metalloproteinase 9 induces keratinocyte apoptosis through FasL/Fas 
pathway in diabetic wound.

Apoptosis is a mechanism to remove unwanted cells in the tissue. In diabetic 
wound, which is characterized by delayed healing process, excessive apoptosis is 
documented and plays a crucial role. Matrix metalloproteinase 9 (MMP9), which is 
elevated in non-healed diabetic wound, is necessary for healing process but its 
abnormality resulted in a delayed healing. The classical function of MMP9 is the 
degradation of extracellular matrix (ECM). However, there is some literature 
evidence that MMP9 triggers cell apoptosis. Whether the excessive MMP9 
contributes to epidermis cell apoptosis in delayed healing diabetic wound and 
the underlying mechanisms is not clear. In this study, we aimed to explore 
whether MMP9 induced keratinocyte apoptosis and investigate the plausible 
mechanisms. Our in vitro study showed that advanced glycation end products 
(AGEs) induced keratinocyte apoptosis and enhanced MMP9 level. Besides, MMP9, 
both intra-cellular expressions and extra-cellular supplement, promoted cell 
apoptosis. Further, MMP9 resulted in an increased expression of FasL, other than 
Fas and p53. These findings identified a novel effect that MMP9 exerted in 
delayed diabetic wound healing, owing to a pro-apoptotic effect on keratinocyte, 
which was mediated by an increase of FasL expression. This study increases 
understanding of elevated MMP9 which is involved in diabetic wound repair and 
offers some insights into novel future therapies.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="905~913" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="980~992" text="keratinocyte" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1116~1120" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="972~979,993~1002" text="induced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1107~1115,1122~1131" text="promoted ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>