<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Down-regulating IL-6/GP130 targets improved the anti-tumor effects of 
5-fluorouracil in colon cancer.

Recent studies have confirmed that IL-6/GP130 targets are closely associated 
with tumor growth, metastasis and drug resistance. 5-Fluorouracil (5-FU) is the 
most common chemotherapeutic agent for colon cancer but is limited due to 
chemoresistance and high cytotoxicity. Bazedoxifene (BZA), a third-generation 
selective estrogen receptor modulator, was discovered by multiple ligand 
simultaneous docking and drug repositioning approaches to have a novel function 
as an IL-6/GP130 target inhibitor. Thus, we speculated that in colon cancer, the 
anti-tumor efficacy of 5-FU might be increased in combination with IL-6/GP130 
inhibitors. CCK8 assay and colony formation assay were used to detect the cell 
proliferation and colony formation. We measured the IC50 value of 5-FU alone and 
in combination with BZA by cell viability inhibition. Cell migration and 
invasion ability were tested by scratch migration assays and transwell invasion 
assays. Flow cytometric analysis for cell apoptosis and cell cycle. Quantitative 
real-time PCR was used to detect Bad, Bcl-2 and Ki-67 mRNA expression and 
western blotting (WB) assay analyzed protein expression of Bad/Bcl-2 signaling 
pathway. Further mechanism study, WB analysis detected the key proteins level in 
IL-6/GP130 targets and JAK/STAT3, Ras/Raf/MEK/ERK, and PI3K/AKT/mTOR signaling 
pathway. A colon cancer xenograft model was used to further confirm the efficacy 
of 5-FU and BZA in vivo. The GP130, P-STAT3, P-AKT, and P-ERK expression levels 
were detected by immunohistochemistry in the xenograft tumor. BZA markedly 
potentiates the anti-tumor function of 5-FU in vitro and in vivo. Conversely, 
5-FU activation is reduced following exogenous IL-6 treatment in cells. Further 
mechanistic studies determined that BZA treatment enhanced 5-FU anti-tumor 
activation by inhibiting the IL-6/GP130 signaling pathway and the 
phosphorylation status of the downstream effectors AKT, ERK and STAT3. In 
contrast, IL-6 can attenuate 5-FU function via activating IL-6R/GP130 signaling 
and the P-AKT, P-ERK and P-STAT3 levels. This study firstly verifies that 
targeting IL-6/GP130 signaling can increase the anti-tumor function of 5-FU; in 
addition, this strategy can sensitize cancer cell drug sensitivity, implying 
that blocking IL-6/GP130 targets can reverse chemoresistance. Therefore, 
combining 5-FU and IL-6/GP130 target inhibitors may be a promising approach for 
cancer treatment.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1732~1740" text="in vitro" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1745~1752" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1832~1837" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>