<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Age-dependent autophagy induction after injury promotes axon regeneration by 
limiting NOTCH.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is essential for maintaining cellular homeostasis 
through the degradation of organelles and proteins. It also has a prominent role 
in modulating aging. However, the role of autophagy in the neuronal response to 
axon injury and axon regeneration, particularly in the context of aging, remains 
largely unknown. Our candidate genetic screen for axon regeneration regulators 
has identified genes in the autophagy pathway. Using a reporter that monitors 
autophagosomes and autolysosomes, we were able to monitor the dynamics of 
autophagy during axon regeneration. In response to axon injury, there was a 
significant increase in the number of autophagic vesicles. Injury-triggered 
autophagy activation and axon regeneration capacity undergo an age-dependent 
decline, and autophagy-activating agents partially rescued these declines. We 
found that DLK-1 was both required and sufficient for injury-induced autophagy 
activation. Autophagic vesicles co-localized with the NOTCH4 ortholog, LIN-12 
receptor, a previously identified inhibitor of axon regeneration. Epistasis 
analyses indicate that LIN-12 might be a target of autophagy in axon 
regeneration. Together, our data suggest that DLK-mediated injury signaling can 
activate autophagy, which might limit the level of LIN-12 and NOTCH proteins to 
promote axon regeneration. Our findings reveal that autophagy activation can 
promote axon regeneration in neurons that lack maximal regrowth capacity, 
providing a promising therapeutic strategy for axon injury.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1536~1543" text="neurons" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="667~671" text="axon" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="701~705" text="axon" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1030~1051" text="autophagy  activation" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1348~1366" text="activate autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="739~784" text="increase in the number of autophagic vesicles" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>