<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PET imaging of cardiomyocyte apoptosis in a rat myocardial infarction model.

Cardiomyocyte apoptosis has been observed in several cardiovascular diseases and 
contributes to the subsequent cardiac remodeling processes and progression to 
heart failure. Consequently, apoptosis imaging is helpful for noninvasively 
detecting the disease progression and providing treatment guidance. Here, we 
tested 18F-labeled 2-(5-fluoropentyl)-2-methyl-malonic acid (18F-ML-10) and 
18F-labeled 2-(3-fluoropropyl)-2-methyl-malonic acid (18F-ML-8) for apoptosis 
imaging in rat models of myocardial infarction (MI) and compared them with 
18F-fluorodeoxyglucose (18F-FDG). MI was induced in Sprague-Dawley rats by 
permanent left coronary artery ligation. Procedural success was confirmed by 
echocardiography and positron emission tomography (PET) imaging with 18F-FDG. In 
vivo PET imaging with 18F-ML-10 and 18F-ML-8 was performed in the MI models at 
different time points after operation. Terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase 
dUTP nick-end labeling (TUNEL) assays and immunohistochemical analyses were used 
to evaluate myocardial apoptosis. In vitro cell binding assays were performed to 
validate 18F-ML-8 binding to apoptotic cardiomyocytes. PET imaging demonstrated 
high 18F-ML-10 and 18F-ML-8 uptake where 18F-FDG uptake was absent. The focal 
accumulation of the two tracers was high on days 1 and 3 but was not notable on 
days 5 and 7 after surgery. The infarct-to-lung uptake ratio was 4.29 ± 0.30 for 
18F-ML-10 and 3.51 ± 0.18 for 18F-ML-8 (n = 6, analyzed by averaging the uptake 
ratios on postoperative days 1 and 3, P < 0.05). The TUNEL results showed that 
myocardial cell apoptosis was closely related to the focal uptake of the 
apoptotic tracers in the infarct area. In addition, the apoptosis rates 
calculated from the TUNEL results were better correlated with 18F-ML-8 uptake 
than with 18F-ML-10 uptake. Ex vivo cell binding assays demonstrated that 
18F-ML-8 accumulated in apoptotic cells but not in necrotic or normal cells. PET 
imaging using 18F-ML-10 or 18F-ML-8 allows the noninvasive detection of 
myocardial apoptosis in the early phase. In addition, 18F-ML-8 may be better 
than 18F-ML-10 for apoptosis imaging. We propose that PET imaging with 18F-ML-10 
or 18F-ML-8 combined with 18F-FDG is an alternative for detecting and assessing 
MI.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="678~697" text="Sprague-Dawley rats" experiment_type="organism" species="rat" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1668~1683" text="myocardial cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1684~1693" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>