<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mille modis morimur: We die in a thousand ways.

Dying cells subjected to apoptotic programs are engulfed by neighboring cells or 
by professional phagocytes, without inflammation or immunological reactions in 
the tissue where apoptosis takes place. Apoptotic cells release 
danger-associated project signals to their neighbours, through different 
molecular patterns, stimulate antigen production and immune responses. 
Microenvironmental effects with several functional consequences indicate that 
cell death is a complex process and may take place in several ways. This idea is 
expressed by the title of the Special Issue and by the title of the guest 
editorial "Mille modis morimur" meaning that not only multicellular organisms, 
but also single cells may die in a thousand ways. This idea is demonstrated by 
the papers serving as examples for cell death. Apoptosis was induced by clary 
sage oil in Candida cells. Heavy metal (Gd) induced cell motility and apoptosis 
was found in mammalian cells. RNA oxidation enhanced the reversion frequency of 
apoptosis in yeast mutants. The frequency of apoptotic micronucleus formation 
increased in a concentration-dependent manner by methotrexate. The antioxidant 
coenzyme Q10 protected renal proximal tubule cells against nicotine-induced 
apoptosis. The synergy of 2-deoxy-D-glucose combined with berberine induced 
lysosome/autophagy. The mitochondrial apoptotic pathway could be regulated by 
glucocorticoid receptor in collaboration with Bcl-2 family proteins in 
developing T cells. Cylindrospermopsin induced biochemical changes led to 
apoptosis in plants. Mechanisms of stress seriously impacted the risk of 
apoptosis. Transcriptional control of apoptotic cell clearance was achieved by 
macrophage nuclear receptors. Finally, the clinical aspects of apoptosis-induced 
lymphopenia were reviewed in sepsis and other severe injuries. These examples 
not only support the view of many ways of cell death, but predict further 
potential ways to induce or reduce the risk of cell death.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="909~922" text="Candida cells" experiment_type="cells" species="yeast" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1072~1077" text="yeast" experiment_type="organism" species="yeast" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1241~1268" text="renal proximal tubule cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1523~1541" text="developing T cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1611~1617" text="plants" experiment_type="organism" species="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="991~1006" text="mammalian cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="865~886" text="Apoptosis was induced" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="941~948,967~976" text="induced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1022~1068" text="enhanced the reversion frequency of  apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1231~1240,1269~1276,1295~1304" text="protected ... against ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1363~1370,1381~1390" text="induced ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1590~1607" text="led to  apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>