<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Elevated IL-22 in psoriasis plays an anti-apoptotic role in keratinocytes 
through mediating Bcl-xL/Bax.

IL-22 is known to mediate inflammation in psoriasis, while IL-22 binding protein 
(IL-22BP) binds IL-22 to suppress IL-22 signaling. However, the function of 
IL-22 in regulating apoptosis in psoriasis remains poorly understood. In this 
study, we found that IL-22/IL-22R1 in lesional skin and IL-22 in serum from 
psoriatic patients were highly upregulated compared with healthy controls, while 
IL-22BP was not changed. Correlations between IL-22/IL-22R1 levels and the 
thickness of psoriatic lesions suggested that IL-22 might positively regulate 
abnormal hyperplasia in psoriasis. Apoptotic keratinocytes were increased only 
in stratum corneum, but not in spinous and basal layers of psoriasis. Moreover, 
IL-22 promoted cell viability in human epidermal keratinocytes (HEKs). The 
apoptosis induced by TNF-α and IFN-γ was inhibited in HEKs treated with IL-22, 
since that IL-22 upregulated Bcl-xL and downregulated Bax production in HEKs in 
the presence of TNF-α and IFN-γ. In addition, IL-22BP could counteract the 
anti-apoptotic effect of IL-22. Our finding demonstrates that IL-22 might play 
an anti-apoptosis role on keratinocytes to balance cell proliferation and 
apoptosis in psoriatic epidermis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="852~888" text="human epidermal keratinocytes (HEKs)" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="949~953" text="HEKs" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1047~1051" text="HEKs" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="825~848" text="promoted cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="895~912,932~945" text="apoptosis induced ... was inhibited" activity="inhibits" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="895~912" text="apoptosis induced" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>