<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[2-aryl benzimidazole conjugate induced apoptosis in human breast cancer MCF-7 
cells through caspase independent pathway.

Apoptosis is a representative form of programmed cell death, which has been 
assumed to be critical for cancer prevention. Thus, any agent that can induce 
apoptosis may be useful for cancer treatment and apoptosis induction is arguably 
the most potent defense against cancer promotion. In our previous studies, 
2-aryl benzimidazole conjugates were synthesized and evaluated for their 
antiproliferative activity and one of the new molecule (2f) was considered as a 
potential lead. This lead molecule showed significant antiproliferative activity 
against human breast cancer cell line, MCF-7. The results of the present study 
revealed that this compound arrested the cell cycle at G2/M phase. Topoisomerase 
II inhibition assay and Western blot analysis suggested that this compound 
effectively inhibits topoisomerase II activity which leads to apoptotic cell 
death. Apoptosis induction in MCF-7 cells was further confirmed by loss of 
mitochondrial membrane potential (∆Ψm), release of cytochrome c from 
mitochondria, an increase in the level of apoptosis inducing factor (AIF), 
generation of reactive oxygen species (ROS), up regulation of proapoptotic 
protein Bax and down regulation of anti apoptotic protein Bcl-2. Apoptosis assay 
using Annexin V-FITC assay also suggested that this compound induced cell death 
by apoptosis. However, compound 2f induced apoptosis could not be reversed by 
Z-VAD-FMK (a pan-caspase inhibitor) demonstrated that the 2f induced apoptosis 
was caspase independent. Further, 2f treatment did not activate caspase-7 and 
caspase-9 activity, suggesting that this compound induced apoptosis in breast 
cancer cells via a caspase independent pathway. Most importantly, this compound 
was less toxic towards non-tumorigenic breast epithelial cells, MCF-10A. 
Furthermore, docking studies also support the potentiality of this molecule to 
bind to the DNA topoisomerase II.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1020~1031" text="MCF-7 cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1760~1780" text="breast  cancer cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1872~1920" text="non-tumorigenic breast epithelial cells, MCF-10A" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="782~819" text="arrested the cell cycle at G2/M phase" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="965~995" text="leads to apoptotic cell  death" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="997~1016" text="Apoptosis induction" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1431~1449" text="induced cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1431~1438,1454~1463" text="induced ... apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1486~1503" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1591~1608" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E7" spans="1739~1756" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>