<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Apoptosis-inducing factor (Aif1) mediates anacardic acid-induced apoptosis in 
Saccharomyces cerevisiae.

Anacardic acid is a medicinal phytochemical that inhibits proliferation of 
fungal as well as several types of cancer cells. It induces apoptotic cell death 
in various cell types, but very little is known about the mechanism involved in 
the process. Here, we used budding yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae as a model to 
study the involvement of some key elements of apoptosis in the anacardic 
acid-induced cell death. Plasma membrane constriction, chromatin condensation, 
DNA degradation, and externalization of phosphatidylserine (PS) indicated that 
anacardic acid induces apoptotic cell death in S. cerevisiae. However, the 
exogenous addition of broad-spectrum caspase inhibitor Z-VAD-FMK or deletion of 
the yeast caspase Yca1 showed that the anacardic acid-induced cell death is 
caspase independent. Apoptosis-inducing factor (AIF1) deletion mutant was 
resistant to the anacardic acid-induced cell death, suggesting a key role of 
Aif1. Overexpression of Aif1 made cells highly susceptible to anacardic acid, 
further confirming that Aif1 mediates anacardic acid-induced apoptosis. 
Interestingly, instead of the increase in the intracellular reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) normally observed during apoptosis, anacardic acid caused a 
decrease in the intracellular ROS levels. Quantitative real-time PCR analysis 
showed downregulation of the BIR1 survivin mRNA expression during the anacardic 
acid-induced apoptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="804~839" text="deletion of  the yeast caspase Yca1" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="915~963" text="Apoptosis-inducing factor (AIF1) deletion mutant" description="knock out" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1053~1075" text="Overexpression of Aif1" description="increased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="707~720" text="S. cerevisiae" experiment_type="organism" species="yeast" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1081~1086" text="cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="675~703" text="induces apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="871~889" text="induced cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="969~981,1001~1019" text="resistant to ... induced cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1155~1163,1179~1196" text="mediates ... induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1516~1533" text="induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>