<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Treating metastatic prostate cancer with microRNA-145.

Prostate cancer (PCa) is an incurable disease at the metastatic stage. Although 
there are different options for treatment, the results are limited. MicroRNAs 
(miRNAs) are a group of small, noncoding, regulatory RNAs with important roles 
in regulating gene expression. miR-145 is reported to be a key tumor suppressor 
miRNA (tsmiR) that controls important oncogenes, such as MYC and RAS. In this 
study, in vitro studies were performed to show the control of MYC and RAS by 
miR-145. Flow cytometry was used to analyze cell proliferation and apoptosis. 
The efficacy of miR-145 in treating metastatic PCa was tested in nude mice using 
a model of bone metastasis promoted by intraventricular injection of PC-3MLuc-C6 
cells. Tumor growth was evaluated by an in vivo bioluminescence system. After 
the full establishment of metastases on day 21, six animals were treated with 
three intravenous doses of miR-145 (on days 21, 24 and 27), and six were 
injected with scramble miRNA as controls. Compared to the controls, tumor growth 
was significantly reduced in animals receiving miR-145, most importantly on day 
7 after the third and last dose of miRNA. After discontinuing the treatment, 
tumor growth resumed, becoming similar to the group of non-treated animals. A 
decrease in MYC and RAS expression was observed in all cell lines after 
treatment with miR-145, although statistical significance was achieved only in 
experiments with LNCaP and PC3 cell lines, with a decrease in 56% (p = 0.012) 
and 31% (p = 0.013) of RAS expression, respectively. Our results suggest that 
miR-145 is a potential molecule to be tested for treatment of metastatic, 
castration-resistant PCa.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1120~1127" text="animals" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1384~1394" text="cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1499~1523" text="LNCaP and PC3 cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="908~915" text="animals" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="678~687" text="nude mice" experiment_type="organism" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="764~782" text="PC-3MLuc-C6  cells" experiment_type="transformed cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1077~1094,1109~1116" text="tumor growth  was ... reduced" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1250~1270" text="tumor growth resumed" phenotype="tumour growth" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>