<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Clotam enhances anti-proliferative effect of vincristine in Ewing sarcoma cells.

Current therapeutic strategies used in Ewing sarcoma (ES) especially for 
relapsed patients have resulted in modest improvements in survival over the past 
20 years. Combination therapeutic approach presents as an alternative to 
overcoming drug resistance in metastatic ES. This study evaluated the effect of 
Clotam (tolfenamic acid or TA), a small molecule and inhibitor of Specificity 
protein1 (Sp1) and survivin for sensitizing ES cell lines to chemotherapeutic 
agent, vincristine (VCR). ES cells (CHLA-9 and TC-32) were treated with TA or 
VCR or TA + VCR (combination), and cell viability was assessed after 24/48/72 h. 
Effect of TA or VCR or TA + VCR treatment on cell cycle arrest and apoptosis 
were evaluated using propidium iodide, cell cycle assay and Annexin V flow 
cytometry respectively. The apoptosis markers, caspase 3/7 (activity levels) and 
cleaved-PARP (protein expression) were measured. Cardiomyocytes, H9C2 were used 
as non-malignant cells. While, all treatments caused time- and dose-dependent 
inhibition of cell viability, interestingly, combination treatment caused 
significantly higher response (~ 80% inhibition, p < 0.05). Cell viability 
inhibition was accompanied by inhibition of Sp1 and Survivin. TA + VCR treatment 
significantly (p < 0.05) increased caspase 3/7 activity which strongly 
correlated with upregulated c-PARP level and Annexin V staining. Cell cycle 
arrest was observed at G0/G1 (TA) or G2/M (VCR and TA + VCR). All treatments did 
not cause cytotoxicity in H9C2 cells. These results suggest that TA could 
enhance the anti-cancer activity of VCR in ES cells. Therefore, TA + VCR 
combination could be further tested to develop as safe/effective therapeutic 
strategy for treating ES.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="427~486" text="small molecule and inhibitor of Specificity  protein1 (Sp1)" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1598~1608" text="H9C2 cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="997~1051" text="Cardiomyocytes, H9C2 were used  as non-malignant cells" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="516~529" text="ES cell lines" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="577~604" text="ES cells (CHLA-9 and TC-32)" experiment_type="cell line" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1108~1136" text="inhibition of cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1243~1269" text="Cell viability  inhibition" phenotype="cell survival" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1478~1518" text="Cell cycle  arrest was observed at G0/G1" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1478~1512,1527~1531" text="Cell cycle  arrest was observed at ... G2/M" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" activity="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>