<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Caspase-12 is involved in stretch-induced apoptosis mediated endoplasmic 
reticulum stress.

It is well recognized that mandibular growth, which is caused by a variety of 
functional appliances, is considered to be the result of both neuromuscular and 
skeletal adaptations. Accumulating evidence has demonstrated that apoptosis 
plays an important role in the adaptation of skeletal muscle function. However, 
the underlying mechanism of apoptosis that is induced by stretch continues to be 
incompletely understood. Endoplasmic reticulum stress (ERS), a newly defined 
signaling pathway, initiates apoptosis. This study seeks to determine if 
caspase-12 is involved in stretch-induced apoptosis mediated endoplasmic 
reticulum stress in myoblast and its underlying mechanism. Apoptosis was 
assessed by Hochest staining, DAPI staining and annexin V binding and PI 
staining. ER chaperones, such as GRP78, CHOP and caspase-12, were determined by 
reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR) and Western blot. 
Furthermore, caspase-12 inhibitor was used to value the mechanism of the 
caspase-12 pathway. Apoptosis of myoblast, which is subjected to cyclic stretch, 
was observed in a time-dependent manner. We found that GRP78 mRNA and protein 
were significantly increased and CHOP and caspase-12 were activated in myoblast 
that was exposed to cyclic stretch. Caspase-12 inhibition reduced 
stretch-induced apoptosis, and caspase-12 activated caspase-3 to induce 
apoptosis. We concluded that caspase-12 played an important role in 
stretch-induced apoptosis that is associated by endoplasmic reticulum stress by 
activating caspase-3.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1376~1397" text="Caspase-12 inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1131~1139" text="myoblast" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1118~1127" text="Apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1398~1405,1415~1432" text="reduced ... induced apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1472~1489" text="induce  apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>