<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Down-regulated TMED10 in Alzheimer disease induces autophagy via ATG4B 
activation.

Several studies have shown that dysfunction of macroautophagy/autophagy is 
associated with many human diseases, including neurodegenerative disease and 
cancer. To explore the molecular mechanisms of autophagy, we performed a 
cell-based functional screening with SH-SY5Y cells stably expressing GFP-LC3, 
using an siRNA library and identified TMED10 (transmembrane p24 trafficking 
protein 10), previously known as the γ-secretase-modulating protein, as a novel 
regulator of autophagy. Further investigations revealed that depletion of TMED10 
induced the activation of autophagy. Interestingly, protein-protein interaction 
assays showed that TMED10 directly binds to ATG4B (autophagy related gene 4B 
cysteine peptidase), and the interaction is diminished under autophagy 
activation conditions such as rapamycin treatment and serum deprivation. In 
addition, inhibition of TMED10 significantly enhanced the proteolytic activity 
of ATG4B for LC3 cleavage. Importantly, the expression of TMED10 in AD 
(Alzheimer disease) patients was considerably decreased, and downregulation of 
TMED10 increased amyloid-β (Aβ) production. Treatment with Aβ increased ATG4B 
proteolytic activity as well as dissociation of TMED10 and ATG4B. Taken 
together, our results suggest that the AD-associated protein TMED10 negatively 
regulates autophagy by inhibiting ATG4B activity.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="611~630" text="depletion of TMED10" description="decreased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="950~970" text="inhibition of TMED10" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1153~1178" text="downregulation of  TMED10" description="decreased expression level" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="350~389" text="SH-SY5Y cells stably expressing GFP-LC3" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1088~1120" text="AD  (Alzheimer disease) patients" experiment_type="organism" species="human" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="632~667" text="induced the activation of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1392~1423" text="negatively  regulates autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>