<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[STYK1 promotes autophagy through enhancing the assembly of autophagy-specific 
class III phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase complex I.

Macroautophagy/autophagy plays key roles in development, oncogenesis, and 
cardiovascular and metabolic diseases. Autophagy-specific class III 
phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase complex I (PtdIns3K-C1) is essential for 
autophagosome formation. However, the regulation of this complex formation 
requires further investigation. Here, we discovered that STYK1 
(serine/threonine/tyrosine kinase 1), a member of the receptor tyrosine kinases 
(RTKs) family, is a new upstream regulator of autophagy. We discovered that 
STYK1 facilitated autophagosome formation in human cells and zebrafish, which 
was characterized by elevated LC3-II and lowered SQSTM1/p62 levels and increased 
puncta formation by several marker proteins, such as ATG14, WIPI1, and ZFYVE1. 
Moreover, we observed that STYK1 directly binds to the PtdIns3K-C1 complex as a 
homodimer. The binding with this complex was promoted by Tyr191 phosphorylation, 
by means of which the kinase activity of STYK1 was elevated. We also 
demonstrated that STYK1 elevated the serine phosphorylation of BECN1, thereby 
decreasing the interaction between BECN1 and BCL2. Furthermore, we found that 
STYK1 preferentially facilitated the assembly of the PtdIns3K-C1 complex and was 
required for PtdIns3K-C1 complex kinase activity. Taken together, our findings 
provide new insights into autophagy induction and reveal evidence of novel 
crosstalk between the components of RTK signaling and autophagy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="690~701" text="human cells" experiment_type="cells" species="human" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="706~715" text="zebrafish" experiment_type="organism" species="fish" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="601~623" text="regulator of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="651~686" text="facilitated autophagosome formation" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>