<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Suppression of autophagy during mitosis via CUL4-RING ubiquitin ligases-mediated 
WIPI2 polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is a cellular process in which cytosolic contents are 
degraded by lysosome in response to various stress conditions. Apart from its 
role in the maintenance of cellular homeostasis, autophagy also involves in 
regulation of cell cycle progression under nutrient-deprivation conditions. 
However, whether and how autophagy is regulated by the cell cycle especially 
during mitosis remains largely undefined. Here we show that WIPI2/ATG18B (WD 
repeat domain, phosphoinositide interacting 2), an autophagy-related (ATG) 
protein that plays a critical role in autophagosome biogenesis, is a direct 
substrate of CUL4-RING ubiquitin ligases (CRL4s). Upon mitosis induction, CRL4s 
are activated via neddylation, and recruit WIPI2 via DDB1 (damage specific DNA 
binding protein 1), leading to polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation of 
WIPI2 and suppression of autophagy. The WIPI2 protein level and autophagy during 
mitosis could be rescued by knockdown of CRL4s or treatment with 
MLN4924/Pevonedistat, a selective inhibitor of CRLs, via suppression of NAE1 
(NEDD8 activating enzyme E1 subunit 1). Moreover, restoration of WIPI2 rescues 
autophagy during mitosis and leads to mitotic slippage and cell senescence. Our 
study thus discovers a novel function of CRL4s in autophagy by targeting WIPI2 
for polyubiquitination and proteasomal degradation during mitosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1112~1130" text="knockdown of CRL4s" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1134~1201" text="treatment with  MLN4924/Pevonedistat, a selective inhibitor of CRLs" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1367~1371" text="cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1012~1036" text="suppression of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="decreases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1066~1075,1092~1108" text="autophagy ... could be rescued" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1299~1317" text="rescues  autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1337~1345,1372~1382" text="leads to ... senescence" phenotype="senescence" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>