<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Small molecule-driven NLRP3 inflammation inhibition via interplay between 
ubiquitination and autophagy: implications for Parkinson disease.

Aging-related, nonresolving inflammation in both the central nervous system 
(CNS) and periphery predisposes individuals to the development of 
neurodegenerative disorders (NDDs). Inflammasomes are thought to be especially 
relevant to immune homeostasis, and their dysregulation contributes to 
inflammation and NDDs. However, few agents have been clinically shown to reduce 
NDD incidence by targeting inflammasomes. Our study indicated that NLRP3 (NLR 
family, pyrin domain containing 3) inflammasome is involved in Parkinson disease 
(PD) progression in patients and various murine models. In addition, the small 
molecule kaempferol (Ka) protected mice against LPS- and SNCA-induced 
neurodegeneration by inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome activation as evidenced by 
the fact that Ka reduced cleaved CASP1 expression and disrupted 
NLRP3-PYCARD-CASP1 complex assembly with concomitant decreased IL1B secretion. 
Mechanically, Ka promoted macroautophagy/autophagy in microglia, leading to 
reduced NLRP3 protein expression, which in turn deactivated the NLRP3 
inflammasome. Intriguingly, ubiquitination was involved in Ka-induced autophagic 
NLRP3 degradation. These findings were further confirmed in vivo as knockdown of 
Atg5 expression or autophagy inhibitor treatment significantly inhibited the 
Ka-mediated NLRP3 inflammasome inhibition and neurodegeneration amelioration. 
Thus, we demonstrated that Ka promotes neuroinflammatory inhibition via the 
cooperation of ubiquitination and autophagy, suggesting that Ka is a promising 
therapeutic strategy for the treatment of NDDs.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1353~1382" text="knockdown of  Atg5 expression" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="721~734" text="murine models" experiment_type="not stated" species="mouse" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1342~1349" text="in vivo" experiment_type="organism" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1072~1080,1096~1105" text="promoted ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1635~1644" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="not stated" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>