<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Neuronal-targeted TFEB rescues dysfunction of the autophagy-lysosomal pathway 
and alleviates ischemic injury in permanent cerebral ischemia.

Mounting attention has been focused on defects in macroautophagy/autophagy and 
the autophagy-lysosomal pathway (ALP) in cerebral ischemia. TFEB (transcription 
factor EB)-mediated induction of ALP has been recently considered as the common 
mechanism in ameliorating the pathological lesion of myocardial ischemia and 
neurodegenerative diseases. Here we explored the vital role of TFEB in permanent 
middle cerebral artery occlusion (pMCAO)-mediated dysfunction of ALP and 
ischemic insult in rats. The results showed that ALP function was first enhanced 
in the early stage of the ischemic process, especially in neurons of the cortex, 
and this was accompanied by increased TFEB expression and translocation to the 
nucleus, which was mediated at least in part through activation by 
PPP3/calcineurin. At the later stages of ischemia, a gradual decrease in the 
level of nuclear TFEB was coupled with a progressive decline in lysosomal 
activity, accumulation of autophagosomes and autophagy substrates, and 
exacerbation of the ischemic injury. Notably, neuron-specific overexpression of 
TFEB significantly enhanced ALP function and rescued the ischemic damage, 
starting as early as 6 h and even lasting to 48 h after ischemia. Furthermore, 
neuron-specific knockdown of TFEB markedly reversed the activation of ALP and 
further aggravated the neurological deficits and ischemic outcome at the early 
stage of pMCAO. These results highlight neuronal-targeted TFEB as one of the key 
players in the pMCAO-mediated dysfunction of ALP and ischemic injury, and 
identify TFEB as a promising target for therapies aimed at neuroprotection in 
cerebral ischemia.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1202~1241" text="neuron-specific overexpression of  TFEB" description="conditional knock in" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1392~1425" text="neuron-specific knockdown of TFEB" description="knock down" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="638~642" text="rats" experiment_type="organism" species="rat" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>