<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BNIP3L/NIX and FUNDC1-mediated mitophagy is required for mitochondrial network 
remodeling during cardiac progenitor cell differentiation.

Cell-based therapies represent a very promising strategy to repair and 
regenerate the injured heart to prevent progression to heart failure. To date, 
these therapies have had limited success due to a lack of survival and retention 
of the infused cells. Therefore, it is important to increase our understanding 
of the biology of these cells and utilize this information to enhance their 
survival and function in the injured heart. Mitochondria are critical for 
progenitor cell function and survival. Here, we demonstrate the importance of 
mitochondrial autophagy, or mitophagy, in the differentiation process in adult 
cardiac progenitor cells (CPCs). We found that mitophagy was rapidly induced 
upon initiation of differentiation in CPCs. We also found that mitophagy was 
mediated by mitophagy receptors, rather than the PINK1-PRKN/PARKIN pathway. 
Mitophagy mediated by BNIP3L/NIX and FUNDC1 was not involved in regulating 
progenitor cell fate determination, mitochondrial biogenesis, or reprogramming. 
Instead, mitophagy facilitated the CPCs to undergo proper mitochondrial network 
reorganization during differentiation. Abrogating BNIP3L- and FUNDC1-mediated 
mitophagy during differentiation led to sustained mitochondrial fission and 
formation of donut-shaped impaired mitochondria. It also resulted in increased 
susceptibility to cell death and failure to survive the infarcted heart. 
Finally, aging is associated with accumulation of mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) 
damage in cells and we found that acquiring mtDNA mutations selectively 
disrupted the differentiation-activated mitophagy program in CPCs. These 
findings demonstrate the importance of BNIP3L- and FUNDC1-mediated mitophagy as 
a critical regulator of mitochondrial network formation during differentiation, 
as well as the consequences of accumulating mtDNA mutations. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="758~796" text="adult  cardiac progenitor cells (CPCs)" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="881~885" text="CPCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1074~1089" text="progenitor cell" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1190~1194" text="CPCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1757~1761" text="CPCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="812~825,834~841" text="mitophagy was ... induced" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1461~1500" text="increased  susceptibility to cell death" phenotype="cell death" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1505~1523" text="failure to survive" phenotype="cell survival" activity="inhibits" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1696~1709,1736~1753" text="disrupted the ... mitophagy program" phenotype="mitophagy" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>