<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Lipophagy-derived fatty acids undergo extracellular efflux via lysosomal 
exocytosis.

The autophagic degradation of lipid droplets (LDs), termed lipophagy, is a major 
mechanism that contributes to lipid turnover in numerous cell types. While 
numerous factors, including nutrient deprivation or overexpression of 
PNPLA2/ATGL (patatin-like phospholipase domain containing 2) drive lipophagy, 
the trafficking of fatty acids (FAs) produced from this pathway is largely 
unknown. Herein, we show that PNPLA2 and nutrient deprivation promoted the 
extracellular efflux of FAs. Inhibition of autophagy or lysosomal lipid 
degradation attenuated FA efflux highlighting a critical role for lipophagy in 
this process. Rather than direct transport of FAs across the lysosomal membrane, 
lipophagy-derived FA efflux requires lysosomal fusion to the plasma membrane. 
The lysosomal Ca2+ channel protein MCOLN1/TRPML1 (mucolipin 1) regulates 
lysosomal-plasma membrane fusion and its overexpression increased, while 
inhibition blocked FA efflux. In addition, inhibition of autophagy/lipophagy or 
MCOLN1, or sequestration of extracellular FAs with BSA attenuated the oxidation 
and re-esterification of lipophagy-derived FAs. Overall, these studies show that 
the well-established pathway of lysosomal fusion to the plasma membrane is the 
primary route for the disposal of FAs derived from lipophagy. Moreover, the 
efflux of FAs and their reuptake or subsequent extracellular trafficking to 
adjacent cells may play an important role in cell-to-cell lipid exchange and 
signaling.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="896~923,976~990" text="MCOLN1/TRPML1 (mucolipin 1) ... overexpression" description="increased expression level" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="896~923,1009~1019" text="MCOLN1/TRPML1 (mucolipin 1) ... inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1052~1065,1090~1096" text="inhibition of ... MCOLN1" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>