<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TLR4 (toll-like receptor 4) activation suppresses autophagy through inhibition 
of FOXO3 and impairs phagocytic capacity of microglia.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is a lysosome-dependent catabolic process for the 
turnover of proteins and organelles in eukaryotes. Autophagy plays an important 
role in immunity and inflammation, as well as metabolism and cell survival. 
Diverse immune and inflammatory signals induce autophagy in macrophages through 
pattern recognition receptors, such as toll-like receptors (TLRs). However, the 
physiological role of autophagy and its signaling mechanisms in microglia remain 
poorly understood. Microglia are phagocytic immune cells that are resident in 
the central nervous system and share many characteristics with macrophages. 
Here, we show that autophagic flux and expression of autophagy-related (Atg) 
genes in microglia are significantly suppressed upon TLR4 activation by 
lipopolysaccharide (LPS), in contrast to their stimulation by LPS in 
macrophages. Metabolomics analysis of the levels of phosphatidylinositol 
(PtdIns) and its 3-phosphorylated form, PtdIns3P, in combination with 
bioinformatics prediction, revealed an LPS-induced reduction in the synthesis of 
PtdIns and PtdIns3P in microglia but not macrophages. Interestingly, inhibition 
of PI3K, but not MTOR or MAPK1/3, restored autophagic flux with concomitant 
dephosphorylation and nuclear translocation of FOXO3. A constitutively active 
form of FOXO3 also induced autophagy, suggesting FOXO3 as a downstream target of 
the PI3K pathway for autophagy inhibition. LPS treatment impaired phagocytic 
capacity of microglia, including MAP1LC3B/LC3-associated phagocytosis (LAP) and 
amyloid β (Aβ) clearance. PI3K inhibition restored LAP and degradation capacity 
of microglia against Aβ. These findings suggest a unique mechanism for the 
regulation of microglial autophagy and point to the PI3K-FOXO3 pathway as a 
potential therapeutic target to regulate microglial function in brain disorders. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1287~1306" text="inhibition  of PI3K" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1430~1468" text="A constitutively active  form of FOXO3" description="knock in" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1722~1737" text="PI3K inhibition" description="pharmacological inhibition" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1333~1357" text="restored autophagic flux" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1474~1491" text="induced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>