<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[m(6)A mRNA methylation regulates testosterone synthesis through modulating 
autophagy in Leydig cells.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is indispensable for testosterone synthesis in Leydig 
cells (LCs), and here we report a negative association between m6A modification 
and autophagy in LCs during testosterone synthesis. A gradual decrease of 
METTL14 (methyltransferase like 14) and an increase of ALKBH5 (alkB homolog 5, 
RNA demethylase) were observed in LCs during their differentiation from stem LCs 
to adult LCs. These events led to reduced mRNA methylation levels of 
N6-methyladenosine (m6A) and enhanced autophagy in LCs. Similar regulation of 
METTL14, ALKBH5, and m6A was also observed in LCs upon treatment with human 
chorionic gonadotropin (HsCG). Mechanistically, m6A modification promoted 
translation of PPM1A (protein phosphatase 1A, magnesium dependent, alpha 
isoform), a negative AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) regulator, but 
decreased expression of CAMKK2 (calcium/calmodulin-dependent protein kinase 
kinase 2, beta), a positive AMPK regulator, by reducing its RNA stability. Thus, 
m6A modification resulted in reduced AMPK activity and subsequent autophagy 
inhibition. We further demonstrated that ALKBH5 upregulation by HsCG was 
dependent on enhanced binding of the transcriptional factor CEBPB 
(CCAAT/enhancer binding protein [C/EBP], beta) and the TFEB (transcription 
factor EB) to its gene promoter. Moreover, HsCG treatment decreased METTL14 by 
reducing its stability. Collectively, this study highlights a vital role of m6A 
RNA methylation in the modulation of testosterone synthesis in LCs, providing 
insight into novel therapeutic strategies by exploiting m6A RNA methylation as 
targets for treating azoospermatism and oligospermatism patients with reduction 
in serum testosterone.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="623~626" text="LCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="697~700" text="LCs" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="601~619" text="enhanced autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="increases" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1175~1196" text="autophagy  inhibition" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>