<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Alborixin clears amyloid-β by inducing autophagy through PTEN-mediated 
inhibition of the AKT pathway.

Imbalance in production and clearance of amyloid beta (Aβ) is the primary reason 
for its deposition in Alzheimer disease. Macroautophagy/autophagy is one of the 
important mechanisms for clearance of both intracellular and extracellular Aβ. 
Here, through screening, we identified alborixin, an ionophore, as a potent 
inducer of autophagy. We found that autophagy induced by alborixin substantially 
cleared Aβ in microglia and primary neuronal cells. Induction of autophagy was 
accompanied by up regulation of autophagy proteins BECN1/Beclin 1, ATG5, ATG7 
and increased lysosomal activities. Autophagy induced by alborixin was 
associated with inhibition of the phosphoinositide 3-kinase (PI3K)-AKT pathway. 
A knock down of PTEN and consistent, constitutive activation of AKT inhibited 
alborixin-induced autophagy and consequent clearance of Aβ. Furthermore, 
clearance of Aβ by alborixin led to significant reduction of Aβ-mediated 
cytotoxicity in primary neurons and differentiated N2a cells. Thus, our findings 
put forward alborixin as a potential anti-Alzheimer therapeutic lead.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="820~838" text="knock down of PTEN" description="knock down" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="855~885" text="constitutive activation of AKT" description="knock in" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="520~529" text="microglia" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="534~556" text="primary neuronal cells" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1061~1076" text="primary neurons" experiment_type="primary culture" species="not stated" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1081~1105" text="differentiated N2a cells" experiment_type="cells" species="not stated" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="424~444" text="inducer of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="460~477" text="autophagy induced" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="558~580" text="Induction of autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="701~718" text="Autophagy induced" phenotype="autophagy" activity="causes" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="886~895,915~924" text="inhibited ... autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" activity="inhibits" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>