<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Telomere Maintenance Mechanisms Define Clinical Outcome in High-Risk 
Neuroblastoma.

Neuroblastoma is a childhood cancer with heterogeneous clinical outcomes. To 
comprehensively assess the impact of telomere maintenance mechanism (TMM) on 
clinical outcomes in high-risk neuroblastoma, we integrated the C-circle assay 
[a marker for alternative lengthening of telomeres (ALT)], TERT mRNA expression 
by RNA-sequencing, whole-genome/exome sequencing, and clinical covariates in 134 
neuroblastoma patient samples at diagnosis. In addition, we assessed TMM in 
neuroblastoma cell lines (n = 104) and patient-derived xenografts (n = 28). ALT 
was identified in 23.4% of high-risk neuroblastoma tumors and genomic 
alterations in ATRX were detected in 60% of ALT tumors; 40% of ALT tumors lacked 
genomic alterations in known ALT-associated genes. Patients with high-risk 
neuroblastoma were classified into three subgroups (TERT-high, ALT+, and 
TERT-low/non-ALT) based on presence of C-circles and TERT mRNA expression (above 
or below median TERT expression). Event-free survival was similar among 
TERT-high, ALT+, or TERT-low/non-ALT patients. However, overall survival (OS) 
for TERT-low/non-ALT patients was significantly higher relative to TERT-high or 
ALT patients (log-rank test; P < 0.01) independent of current clinical and 
molecular prognostic markers. Consistent with the observed higher OS in patients 
with TERT-low/non-ALT tumors, continuous shortening of telomeres and decreasing 
viability occurred in low TERT-expressing, non-ALT patient-derived high-risk 
neuroblastoma cell lines. These findings demonstrate that assaying TMM with TERT 
mRNA expression and C-circles provides precise stratification of high-risk 
neuroblastoma into three subgroups with substantially different OS: a previously 
undescribed TERT-low/non-ALT cohort with superior OS (even after relapse) and 
two cohorts of patients with poor survival that have distinct molecular 
therapeutic targets.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>