<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Inhibition of IL1β by Canakinumab May Be Effective against Diverse Molecular 
Subtypes of Lung Cancer: An Exploratory Analysis of the CANTOS Trial.

In the Canakinumab Anti-inflammatory Thrombosis Outcomes Study (CANTOS), 
inhibition of the IL1β inflammatory pathway by canakinumab has been shown to 
significantly reduce lung cancer incidence and mortality. Here we performed 
molecular characterization of CANTOS patients who developed lung cancer during 
the study, including circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA) and soluble inflammatory 
biomarker analysis. Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in Cancer (COSMIC) database 
ctDNA mutations were detected in 65% (46/71) of the CANTOS patients with lung 
cancer, with 51% (36/71) having detectable ctDNA at the time point closest to 
lung cancer diagnosis and 43% (29/67) having detectable ctDNA at trial 
randomization. Mutations commonly found in lung cancer were observed with no 
evidence of enrichment in any mutation following canakinumab treatment. Median 
time to lung cancer diagnosis in patients with (n = 29) versus without (n = 38) 
detectable COSMIC ctDNA mutations at baseline was 407 days versus 837 days (P = 
0.011). For serum inflammatory biomarker analysis, circulating levels of 
C-reactive protein (CRP), IL6, IL18, IL1 receptor antagonist, TNFα, leptin, 
adiponectin, fibrinogen, and plasminogen activator inhibitor-1 were determined. 
Patients with the highest level of baseline CRP or IL6, both downstream of IL1β 
signaling, trended toward a shorter time to lung cancer diagnosis. Other 
inflammation markers outside of the IL1β pathway at baseline did not trend with 
time to lung cancer diagnosis. These results provide further evidence for the 
importance of IL1β-mediated protumor inflammation in lung cancer and suggest 
canakinumab's effect may be mediated in part by delaying disease progression of 
diverse molecular subtypes of lung cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>