<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Single-nucleus transcriptomic survey of cell diversity and functional maturation 
in postnatal mammalian hearts.

A fundamental challenge in understanding cardiac biology and disease is that the 
remarkable heterogeneity in cell type composition and functional states have not 
been well characterized at single-cell resolution in maturing and diseased 
mammalian hearts. Massively parallel single-nucleus RNA sequencing (snRNA-seq) 
has emerged as a powerful tool to address these questions by interrogating the 
transcriptome of tens of thousands of nuclei isolated from fresh or frozen 
tissues. snRNA-seq overcomes the technical challenge of isolating intact single 
cells from complex tissues, including the maturing mammalian hearts; reduces 
biased recovery of easily dissociated cell types; and minimizes aberrant gene 
expression during the whole-cell dissociation. Here we applied sNucDrop-seq, a 
droplet microfluidics-based massively parallel snRNA-seq method, to investigate 
the transcriptional landscape of postnatal maturing mouse hearts in both healthy 
and disease states. By profiling the transcriptome of nearly 20,000 nuclei, we 
identified major and rare cardiac cell types and revealed significant 
heterogeneity of cardiomyocytes, fibroblasts, and endothelial cells in postnatal 
developing hearts. When applied to a mouse model of pediatric mitochondrial 
cardiomyopathy, we uncovered profound cell type-specific modifications of the 
cardiac transcriptional landscape at single-nucleus resolution, including 
changes of subtype composition, maturation states, and functional remodeling of 
each cell type. Furthermore, we employed sNucDrop-seq to decipher the cardiac 
cell type-specific gene regulatory network (GRN) of GDF15, a heart-derived 
hormone and clinically important diagnostic biomarker of heart disease. 
Together, our results present a rich resource for studying cardiac biology and 
provide new insights into heart disease using an approach broadly applicable to 
many fields of biomedicine.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>