<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SARS-CoV-2 infection is associated with a pro-thrombotic platelet phenotype.

Novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) is associated with a hypercoagulable 
state, characterized by abnormal coagulation parameters and by increased 
incidence of cardiovascular complications. With this study, we aimed to 
investigate the activation state and the expression of transmembrane proteins in 
platelets of hospitalized COVID-19 patients. We investigated transmembrane 
proteins expression with a customized mass cytometry panel of 21 antibodies. 
Platelets of 8 hospitalized COVID-19 patients not requiring intensive care 
support and without pre-existing conditions were compared to platelets of 
healthy controls (11 donors) with and without in vitro stimulation with thrombin 
receptor-activating peptide (TRAP). Mass cytometry of non-stimulated platelets 
detected an increased surface expression of activation markers P-Selectin (0.67 
vs. 1.87 median signal intensity for controls vs. patients, p = 0.0015) and 
LAMP-3 (CD63, 0.37 vs. 0.81, p = 0.0004), the GPIIb/IIIa complex (4.58 vs. 5.03, 
p < 0.0001) and other adhesion molecules involved in platelet activation and 
platelet-leukocyte interactions. Upon TRAP stimulation, mass cytometry detected 
a higher expression of P-selectin in COVID-19 samples compared to controls 
(p < 0.0001). However, we observed a significantly reduced capacity of COVID-19 
platelets to increase the expression of activation markers LAMP-3 and P-Selectin 
upon stimulation with TRAP. We detected a hyperactivated phenotype in platelets 
during SARS-CoV-2 infection, consisting of highly expressed platelet activation 
markers, which might contribute to the hypercoagulopathy observed in COVID-19. 
In addition, several transmembrane proteins were more highly expressed compared 
to healthy controls. These findings support research projects investigating 
antithrombotic and antiplatelet treatment regimes in COVID-19 patients, and 
provide new insights on the phenotypical platelet expression during SARS-CoV-2 
infection.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>