<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Expansion of myeloid-derived suppressor cells in patients with severe 
coronavirus disease (COVID-19).

ARS-CoV-2 is associated with a 3.4% mortality rate in patients with severe 
disease. The pathogenesis of severe cases remains unknown. We performed an 
in-depth prospective analysis of immune and inflammation markers in two patients 
with severe COVID-19 disease from presentation to convalescence. Peripheral 
blood from 18 SARS-CoV-2-infected patients, 9 with severe and 9 with mild 
COVID-19 disease, was obtained at admission and analyzed for T-cell activation 
profile, myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSCs) and cytokine profiles. MDSC 
functionality was tested in vitro. In four severe and in four mild patients, a 
longitudinal analysis was performed daily from the day of admission to the early 
convalescent phase. Early after admission severe patients showed neutrophilia, 
lymphopenia, increase in effector T cells, a persisting higher expression of 
CD95 on T cells, higher serum concentration of IL-6 and TGF-β, and a cytotoxic 
profile of NK and T cells compared with mild patients, suggesting a highly 
engaged immune response. Massive expansion of MDSCs was observed, up to 90% of 
total circulating mononuclear cells in patients with severe disease, and up to 
25% in the patients with mild disease; the frequency decreasing with recovery. 
MDSCs suppressed T-cell functions, dampening excessive immune response. MDSCs 
decline at convalescent phase was associated to a reduction in TGF-β and to an 
increase of inflammatory cytokines in plasma samples. Substantial expansion of 
suppressor cells is seen in patients with severe COVID-19. Further studies are 
required to define their roles in reducing the excessive 
activation/inflammation, protection, influencing disease progression, potential 
to serve as biomarkers of disease severity, and new targets for immune and 
host-directed therapeutic approaches.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>