<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The specific PKC-α inhibitor chelerythrine blunts costunolide-induced eryptosis.

Costunolide, a natural sesquiterpene lactone, has multiple pharmacological 
activities such as neuroprotection or induction of apoptosis and eryptosis. 
However, the effects of costunolide on pro-survival factors and enzymes in human 
erythrocytes, e.g. glutathione and glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PDH) 
respectively, have not been studied yet. Our aim was to determine the mechanisms 
underlying costunolide-induced eryptosis and to reverse this process. 
Phosphatidylserine exposure was estimated from annexin-V-binding, cell volume 
from forward scatter in flow cytometry, and intracellular glutathione [GSH]i 
from high performance liquid chromatography. The oxidized status of 
intracellular glutathione and enzyme activities were measured by 
spectrophotometry. Treatment of erythrocytes with costunolide dose-dependently 
enhanced the percentage of annexin-V-binding cells, decreased the cell volume, 
depleted [GSH]i and completely inhibited G6PDH activity. The effects of 
costunolide on annexin-V-binding and cell volume were significantly reversed by 
pre-treatment of erythrocytes with the specific PKC-α inhibitor chelerythrine. 
The latter, however, had no effect on costunolide-induced GSH depletion. 
Costunolide induces eryptosis, depletes [GSH]i and inactivates G6PDH activity. 
Furthermore, our study reveals an inhibitory effect of chelerythrine on 
costunolide-induced eryptosis, indicating a relationship between costunolide and 
PKC-α. In addition, chelerythrine acts independently of the GSH depletion. 
Understanding the mechanisms of G6PDH inhibition accompanied by GSH depletion 
should be useful for development of anti-malarial therapeutic strategies or for 
synthetic lethality-based approaches to escalate oxidative stress in cancer 
cells for their sensitization to chemotherapy and radiotherapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>