<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cancer Cell-Derived Matrisome Proteins Promote Metastasis in Pancreatic Ductal 
Adenocarcinoma.

The prognosis for pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) remains poor despite 
decades of effort. The abundant extracellular matrix (ECM) in PDAC comprises a 
major fraction of the tumor mass and plays various roles in promoting resistance 
to therapies. However, nonselective depletion of ECM has led to poor patient 
outcomes. Consistent with that observation, we previously showed that individual 
matrisome proteins derived from stromal cells correlate with either long or 
short patient survival. In marked contrast, those derived from cancer cells 
correlate strongly with poor survival. Here, we studied three cancer 
cell-derived matrisome proteins that are significantly overrepresented during 
PDAC progression, AGRN (agrin), SERPINB5 (serine protease inhibitor B5), and 
CSTB (cystatin B). Using both overexpression and knockdown experiments, we 
demonstrate that all three are promoters of PDAC metastasis. Furthermore, these 
proteins operate at different metastatic steps. AGRN promoted 
epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition in primary tumors, whereas SERPINB5 and 
CSTB enhanced late steps in the metastatic cascade by elevating invadopodia 
formation and in vivo extravasation. All three genes were associated with a poor 
prognosis in human patients and high levels of SERPINB5, secreted by cancer 
cells and deposited in the ECM, correlated with poor patient prognosis. This 
study provides strong evidence that cancer cell-derived matrisome proteins can 
be causal in promoting tumorigenesis and metastasis and lead to poor patient 
survival. Therefore, compared with the bulk matrix, mostly made by stromal 
cells, precise interventions targeting cancer cell-derived matrisome proteins, 
such as AGRN, SERPINB5, and CSTB, may represent preferred potential therapeutic 
targets. SIGNIFICANCE: This study provides insights into the biological roles of 
cancer cell-derived matrisome proteins in PDAC and supports the notion that 
these proteins are protumorigenic and better therapeutic targets.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1000~1004" text="PDAC" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1140~1154" text="primary tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1269~1276" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1005~1015" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1100~1136" text="epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1192~1228" text="late steps in the metastatic cascade" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="987~996" text="promoters" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1090~1098" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1183~1191" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>