<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Risk SNP-Mediated Enhancer-Promoter Interaction Drives Colorectal Cancer through 
Both FADS2 and AP002754.2.

Although genome-wide association studies (GWAS) have identified more than 100 
colorectal cancer risk loci, most of the biological mechanisms associated with 
these loci remain unclear. Here we first performed a comprehensive expression 
quantitative trait loci analysis in colorectal cancer tissues adjusted for 
multiple confounders to test the determinants of germline variants in 
established GWAS susceptibility loci on mRNA and long noncoding RNA (lncRNA) 
expression. Combining integrative functional genomic/epigenomic analyses and a 
large-scale population study consisting of 6,024 cases and 10,022 controls, we 
then prioritized rs174575 with a C>G change as a potential causal candidate for 
colorectal cancer at 11q12.2, as its G allele was associated with an increased 
risk of colorectal cancer (OR = 1.26; 95% confidence interval = 1.17-1.36; P = 
2.57 × 10-9). rs174575 acted as an allele-specific enhancer to distally 
facilitate expression of both FADS2 and lncRNA AP002754.2 via long-range 
enhancer-promoter interaction loops, which were mediated by E2F1. AP002754.2 
further activated a transcriptional activator that upregulated FADS2 expression. 
FADS2, in turn, was overexpressed in colorectal cancer tumor tissues and 
functioned as a potential oncogene that facilitated colorectal cancer cell 
proliferation and xenograft growth in vitro and in vivo by increasing the 
metabolism of PGE2, an oncogenic molecule involved in colorectal cancer 
tumorigenesis. Our findings represent a novel mechanism by which a noncoding 
variant can facilitate long-range genome interactions to modulate the expression 
of multiple genes including not only mRNA, but also lncRNA, which provides new 
insights into the understanding of colorectal cancer etiology. SIGNIFICANCE: 
This study provides an oncogenic regulatory circuit among several oncogenes 
including E2F1, FADS2, and AP002754.2 underlying the association of rs174575 
with colorectal cancer risk, which is driven by long-range enhancer-promoter 
interaction loops.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1407~1429" text="colorectal cancer cell" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1449~1458" text="xenograft" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1466~1474" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1479~1486" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1431~1444" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1395~1406" text="facilitated" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>