<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[CircFOXK2 Promotes Growth and Metastasis of Pancreatic Ductal Adenocarcinoma by 
Complexing with RNA-Binding Proteins and Sponging MiR-942.

The detailed biological functions of circular RNA (circRNA) are largely 
unexplored. Using circRNA sequencing, we identified 169 differentially expressed 
circRNA in pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) cells compared with nontumor 
human pancreatic ductal epithelial cells. Among them, circFOXK2 was validated 
with significant upregulation in PDAC cells and 63% of primary tumors (53 of 
84). circFOXK2 promoted cell growth, migration, and invasion and was involved in 
cell-cycle progression and apoptosis. circFOXK2 contained multiple miRNA binding 
sites, functioning as a sponge for miR-942, which in turn promoted expression of 
ANK1, GDNF, and PAX6. A novel and highly specific circRNA-pulldown followed by 
mass spectrometry analysis identified 94 circFOXK2-interacting proteins, which 
were involved in cell adhesion, mRNA splicing, and structural molecule activity. 
Of these, circFOKX2 interactions with YBX1 and hnRNPK enhanced expression of 
oncogenes NUF2 and PDXK. Knockdown of circFOXK2 reduced binding of YBX1 and 
hnRNPK to NUF2 and PDXK, in turn decreasing their expression. Collectively, our 
findings demonstrate that circFOXK2 in complex with YBX1 and hnRNPK promotes 
expression of oncogenic proteins that contribute to PDAC progression. 
SIGNIFICANCE: This study reveals a prominent role for the circRNA circFOXK2 in 
PDAC progression, suggesting that circFOXK2 might be a novel diagnostic marker 
for PDAC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1125~1147" text="Knockdown of circFOXK2" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="558~569" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="571~580" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="586~594" text="invasion" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="643~652" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="549~557" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="603~614" text="involved in" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>