<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Circadian Rhythm Is Disrupted by ZNF704 in Breast Carcinogenesis.

Copy number gain in chromosome 8q21 is frequently detected in breast cancer, yet 
the oncogenic potential underlying this amplicon in breast carcinogenesis 
remains to be delineated. We report here that ZNF704, a gene mapped to 8q21, is 
recurrently amplified in various malignancies including breast cancer. ZNF704 
acted as a transcriptional repressor and interacted with the transcriptional 
corepressor SIN3A complex. Genome-wide interrogation of transcriptional targets 
revealed that the ZNF704/SIN3A complex represses a panel of genes including PER2 
that are critically involved in the function of the circadian clock. 
Overexpression of ZNF704 prolonged the period and dampened the amplitude of the 
circadian clock. ZNF704 promoted the proliferation and invasion of breast cancer 
cells in vitro and accelerated the growth and metastasis of breast cancer in 
vivo. Consistently, the level of ZNF704 expression inversely correlated with 
that of PER2 in breast carcinomas, and high level of ZNF704 correlated with 
advanced histologic grades, lymph node positivity, and poor prognosis of 
patients with breast cancer, especially those with HER2+ and basal-like 
subtypes. These results indicate that ZNF704 is an important regulator of the 
circadian clock and a potential driver for breast carcinogenesis. SIGNIFICANCE: 
This study indicates that ZNF704 could be a potential oncogenic factor, 
disrupting circadian rhythm of breast cancer cells and contributing to breast 
carcinogenesis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="695~719" text="Overexpression of ZNF704" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="843~863" text="breast cancer  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="864~872" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="918~931" text="breast cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="932~940" text="in  vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="813~826" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="831~839" text="invasion" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="904~914" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="800~808" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="877~888" text="accelerated" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>