<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Ferroptosis Inducers Are a Novel Therapeutic Approach for Advanced Prostate 
Cancer.

Ferroptosis is a type of programmed cell death induced by the accumulation of 
lipid peroxidation and lipid reactive oxygen species in cells. It has been 
recently demonstrated that cancer cells are vulnerable to ferroptosis inducers 
(FIN). However, the therapeutic potential of FINs in prostate cancer in 
preclinical settings has not been explored. In this study, we demonstrate that 
mediators of ferroptosis, solute carrier family 7 member 11, SLC3A2, and 
glutathione peroxidase, are expressed in treatment-resistant prostate cancer. We 
further demonstrate that treatment-resistant prostate cancer cells are sensitive 
to two FINs, erastin and RSL3. Treatment with erastin and RSL3 led to a 
significant decrease in prostate cancer cell growth and migration in vitro and 
significantly delayed the tumor growth of treatment-resistant prostate cancer in 
vivo, with no measurable side effects. Combination of erastin or RSL3 with 
standard-of-care second-generation antiandrogens for advanced prostate cancer 
halted prostate cancer cell growth and migration in vitro and tumor growth in 
vivo. These results demonstrate the potential of erastin or RSL3 independently 
and in combination with standard-of-care second-generation antiandrogens as 
novel therapeutic strategies for advanced prostate cancer. SIGNIFICANCE: These 
findings reveal that induction of ferroptosis is a new therapeutic strategy for 
advanced prostate cancer as a monotherapy and in combination with 
second-generation antiandrogens.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="809~824" text="prostate cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="851~859" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="907~942" text="treatment-resistant prostate cancer" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="943~951" text="in  vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1109~1124" text="prostate cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1151~1159" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1177~1185" text="in  vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="825~836" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="841~850" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="891~903" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1125~1136" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1141~1150" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1164~1176" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="797~805" text="decrease" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="879~886" text="delayed" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1102~1108" text="halted" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>