<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[HACE1 Prevents Lung Carcinogenesis via Inhibition of RAC-Family GTPases.

HACE1 is an E3 ubiquitin ligase with important roles in tumor biology and tissue 
homeostasis. Loss or mutation of HACE1 has been associated with the occurrence 
of a variety of neoplasms, but the underlying mechanisms have not been defined 
yet. Here, we report that HACE1 is frequently mutated in human lung cancer. In 
mice, loss of Hace1 led to enhanced progression of KRasG12D -driven lung tumors. 
Additional ablation of the oncogenic GTPase Rac1 partially reduced progression 
of Hace1-/- lung tumors. RAC2, a novel ubiquitylation target of HACE1, could 
compensate for the absence of its homolog RAC1 in Hace1-deficient, but not in 
HACE1-sufficient tumors. Accordingly, ablation of both Rac1 and Rac2 fully 
averted the increased progression of KRasG12D -driven lung tumors in Hace1-/- 
mice. In patients with lung cancer, increased expression of HACE1 correlated 
with reduced levels of RAC1 and RAC2 and prolonged survival, whereas elevated 
expression of RAC1 and RAC2 was associated with poor prognosis. This work 
defines HACE1 as a crucial regulator of the oncogenic activity of RAC-family 
GTPases in lung cancer development. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="402~415" text="loss of Hace1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="447~463" text="KRasG12D -driven" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="489~526" text="ablation of the oncogenic GTPase Rac1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="561~569" text="Hace1-/-" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="686~701" text="Hace1-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="753~783" text="ablation of both Rac1 and Rac2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="828~844" text="KRasG12D -driven" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="860~868" text="Hace1-/-" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="396~400" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="464~475" text="lung tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="570~581" text="lung tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="732~738" text="tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="845~856" text="lung tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="870~874" text="mice" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>