<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cellular Senescence Promotes Skin Carcinogenesis through p38MAPK and p44/42MAPK 
Signaling.

Cellular senescence entails an irreversible growth arrest that evolved in part 
to prevent cancer. Paradoxically, senescent cells secrete proinflammatory and 
growth-stimulatory molecules, termed the senescence-associated secretory 
phenotype (SASP), which is correlated with cancer cell proliferation in culture 
and xenograft models. However, at what tumor stage and how senescence and the 
SASP act on endogenous tumor growth in vivo is unknown. To understand the role 
of senescence in cancer etiology, we subjected p16-3MR transgenic mice, which 
permit the identification and selective elimination of senescent cells in vivo, 
to the well-established two-step protocol of squamous cell skin carcinoma, in 
which tumorigenesis is initiated by a carcinogen 7,12-dimethylbenz[α]anthracene, 
and then promoted by 12-O-tetradecanoyl-phorbol-13-acetate (TPA). We show that 
TPA promotes skin carcinogenesis by inducing senescence and a SASP. Systemic 
induction of senescence in nontumor-bearing p16-3MR mice using a chemotherapy 
followed by the two-step carcinogenesis protocol potentiated the conversion of 
benign papillomas to carcinomas by elevating p38MAPK and MAPK/ERK signaling. 
Ablation of senescent cells reduced p38MAPK and MAPK/ERK signaling, thereby 
preventing the progression of benign papillomas to carcinomas. Thus, we show for 
the first time that senescent cells are tumor promoters, not tumor initiators, 
and that they stimulate skin carcinogenesis by elevating p38MAPK and MAPK/ERK 
signaling. These findings pave the way for developing novel therapeutics against 
senescence-fueled cancers.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="613~636" text="p16-3MR transgenic mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="980~984" text="skin" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1072~1101" text="nontumor-bearing p16-3MR mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1294~1309" text="senescent cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1204~1221" text="benign papillomas" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1389~1406" text="benign papillomas" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="811~824" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="985~999" text="carcinogenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1012~1022" text="senescence" phenotype="senescence" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1058~1068" text="senescence" phenotype="senescence" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="828~837" text="initiated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="896~904" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="971~979" text="promotes" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1003~1011" text="inducing" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1045~1054" text="induction" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>