<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[
ATM Loss Confers Greater Sensitivity to ATR Inhibition Than PARP Inhibition in 
Prostate Cancer.

Alterations in DNA damage response (DDR) genes are common in advanced prostate 
tumors and are associated with unique genomic and clinical features. ATM is a 
DDR kinase that has a central role in coordinating DNA repair and cell-cycle 
response following DNA damage, and ATM alterations are present in approximately 
5% of advanced prostate tumors. Recently, inhibitors of PARP have demonstrated 
activity in advanced prostate tumors harboring DDR gene alterations, 
particularly in tumors with BRCA1/2 alterations. However, the role of 
alterations in DDR genes beyond BRCA1/2 in mediating PARP inhibitor sensitivity 
is poorly understood. To define the role of ATM loss in prostate tumor DDR 
function and sensitivity to DDR-directed agents, we created a series of 
ATM-deficient preclinical prostate cancer models and tested the impact of ATM 
loss on DNA repair function and therapeutic sensitivities. ATM loss altered DDR 
signaling, but did not directly impact homologous recombination function. 
Furthermore, ATM loss did not significantly impact sensitivity to PARP 
inhibition but robustly sensitized to inhibitors of the related DDR kinase ATR. 
These results have important implications for planned and ongoing prostate 
cancer clinical trials and suggest that patients with tumor ATM alterations may 
be more likely to benefit from ATR inhibitor than PARP inhibitor therapy. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="868~881" text="ATM-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1006~1014" text="ATM loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1116~1124" text="ATM loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="882~916" text="preclinical prostate cancer models" context="neoplasm" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>