<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Regorafenib induces lethal autophagy arrest by stabilizing PSAT1 in 
glioblastoma.

GBM (glioblastoma multiforme) is the most common and aggressive brain tumor with 
no curative options available. Therefore, it is imperative to develop novel 
potent therapeutic drugs for GBM treatment. Here, we show that regorafenib, an 
oral multi-kinase inhibitor, exhibits superior therapeutic efficacy over 
temozolomide, the first-line chemotherapeutic agent for GBM treatment both in 
vitro and in vivo. Mechanistically, regorafenib directly stabilizes PSAT1 
(phosphoserine aminotransferase 1), a critical enzyme for serine synthesis, to 
trigger PRKAA-dependent autophagy initiation and inhibit RAB11A-mediated 
autophagosome-lysosome fusion, resulting in lethal autophagy arrest in GBM 
cells. Maintenance of PSAT1 at a high level is essential for regorafenib-induced 
GBM suppression. Together, our data provide novel mechanistic insights of 
regorafenib-induced autophagy arrest and suggest a new paradigm for effective 
treatment of GBM.Abbreviations: 3-MA: 3-methyladenine; ACACA: acetyl coenzyme A 
carboxylase alpha; ACTB/β-actin: actin, beta; AMPK: adenosine 
monophosphate-activated protein kinase; ATG5: autophagy related 5; CTSD: 
cathepsin D; DN-: dominant-negative; GBM: glioblastoma multiforme; LAMP1: 
lysosomal-associated membrane protein 1; MAP1LC3B/LC3B: microtubule associated 
protein 1 light chain 3 beta; PIK3C3/VPS34: phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase 
catalytic subunit type 3; PRKAA/AMPKα: protein kinase AMP-activated catalytic 
subunit alpha; PSAT1: phosphoserine aminotransferase 1; SQSTM1/p62: sequestosome 
1; TKIs: tyrosine kinase inhibitors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="776~786" text="GBM  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="655~664" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="756~765" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="631~638" text="trigger" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="766~772" text="arrest" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>