<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Identification of a Small-Molecule Inhibitor That Disrupts the SIX1/EYA2 
Complex, EMT, and Metastasis.

Metastasis is the major cause of mortality for patients with cancer, and 
dysregulation of developmental signaling pathways can significantly contribute 
to the metastatic process. The Sine oculis homeobox homolog 1 (SIX1)/eyes absent 
(EYA) transcriptional complex plays a critical role in the development of 
multiple organs and is typically downregulated after development is complete. In 
breast cancer, aberrant expression of SIX1 has been demonstrated to stimulate 
metastasis through activation of TGFβ signaling and subsequent induction of 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT). In addition, SIX1 can induce metastasis 
via non-cell autonomous means, including activation of GLI-signaling in 
neighboring tumor cells and activation of VEGFC-induced lymphangiogenesis. Thus, 
targeting SIX1 would be expected to inhibit metastasis while conferring limited 
side effects. However, transcription factors are notoriously difficult to 
target, and thus novel approaches to inhibit their action must be taken. Here we 
identified a novel small molecule compound, NCGC00378430 (abbreviated as 8430), 
that reduces the SIX1/EYA2 interaction. 8430 partially reversed transcriptional 
and metabolic profiles mediated by SIX1 overexpression and reversed SIX1-induced 
TGFβ signaling and EMT. 8430 was well tolerated when delivered to mice and 
significantly suppressed breast cancer-associated metastasis in vivo without 
significantly altering primary tumor growth. Thus, we have demonstrated for the 
first time that pharmacologic inhibition of the SIX1/EYA2 complex and associated 
phenotypes is sufficient to suppress breast cancer metastasis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1326~1345" text="SIX1 overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1439~1443" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1510~1517" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1474~1487" text="breast cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1392~1395" text="EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1499~1509" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1558~1570" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1350~1358" text="reversed" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1463~1473" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1518~1549" text="without  significantly altering" effect="no effect" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>