<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Futibatinib Is a Novel Irreversible FGFR 1-4 Inhibitor That Shows Selective 
Antitumor Activity against FGFR-Deregulated Tumors.

FGFR signaling is deregulated in many human cancers, and FGFR is considered a 
valid target in FGFR-deregulated tumors. Here, we examine the preclinical 
profile of futibatinib (TAS-120; 
1-[(3S)-[4-amino-3-[(3,5-dimethoxyphenyl)ethynyl]-1H-pyrazolo[3, 4-d] 
pyrimidin-1-yl]-1-pyrrolidinyl]-2-propen-1-one), a structurally novel, 
irreversible FGFR1-4 inhibitor. Among a panel of 296 human kinases, futibatinib 
selectively inhibited FGFR1-4 with IC50 values of 1.4 to 3.7 nmol/L. Futibatinib 
covalently bound the FGFR kinase domain, inhibiting FGFR phosphorylation and, in 
turn, downstream signaling in FGFR-deregulated tumor cell lines. Futibatinib 
exhibited potent, selective growth inhibition of several tumor cell lines 
(gastric, lung, multiple myeloma, bladder, endometrial, and breast) harboring 
various FGFR genomic aberrations. Oral administration of futibatinib led to 
significant dose-dependent tumor reduction in various FGFR-driven human tumor 
xenograft models, and tumor reduction was associated with sustained FGFR 
inhibition, which was proportional to the administered dose. The frequency of 
appearance of drug-resistant clones was lower with futibatinib than a reversible 
ATP-competitive FGFR inhibitor, and futibatinib inhibited several drug-resistant 
FGFR2 mutants, including the FGFR2 V565I/L gatekeeper mutants, with greater 
potency than any reversible FGFR inhibitors tested (IC50, 1.3-50.6 nmol/L). 
These results indicate that futibatinib is a novel orally available, potent, 
selective, and irreversible inhibitor of FGFR1-4 with a broad spectrum of 
antitumor activity in cell lines and xenograft models. These findings provide a 
strong rationale for testing futibatinib in patients with tumors oncogenically 
driven by FGFR genomic aberrations, with phase I to III trials ongoing. 
SIGNIFICANCE: Preclinical characterization of futibatinib, an irreversible 
FGFR1-4 inhibitor, demonstrates selective and potent antitumor activity against 
FGFR-deregulated cancer cell lines and xenograft models, supporting clinical 
evaluation in patients with FGFR-driven tumors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="753~769" text="tumor cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="841~926" text="tumor cell lines  (gastric, lung, multiple myeloma, bladder, endometrial, and breast)" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1069~1110" text="FGFR-driven human tumor  xenograft models" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1740~1750" text="cell lines" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1755~1771" text="xenograft models" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1042~1057" text="tumor reduction" phenotype="tumour regression" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1007~1013" text="led to" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>