<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Senescent Stromal Cells Promote Cancer Resistance through SIRT1 Loss-Potentiated 
Overproduction of Small Extracellular Vesicles.

Cellular senescence is a potent tumor-suppressive program that prevents 
neoplastic events. Paradoxically, senescent cells develop an inflammatory 
secretome, termed the senescence-associated secretory phenotype, which is 
implicated in age-related pathologies including cancer. Here, we report that 
senescent cells actively synthesize and release small extracellular vesicles 
(sEV) with a distinctive size distribution. Mechanistically, SIRT1 loss 
supported accelerated sEV production despite enhanced proteome-wide 
ubiquitination, a process correlated with ATP6V1A downregulation and defective 
lysosomal acidification. Once released, senescent stromal sEVs significantly 
altered the expression profile of recipient cancer cells and enhanced their 
aggressiveness, specifically drug resistance mediated by expression of 
ATP-binding cassette subfamily B member 4 (ABCB4). Targeting SIRT1 with agonist 
SRT2104 prevented development of cancer resistance by restraining sEV production 
by senescent stromal cells. In clinical oncology, sEVs in peripheral blood of 
posttreatment cancer patients were readily detectable by routine biotechniques, 
presenting an exploitable biomarker to monitor therapeutic efficacy and predict 
long-term outcome. Together, this study identifies a distinct mechanism 
supporting pathologic activities of senescent cells and provides a potent avenue 
to circumvent advanced human malignancies by cotargeting cancer cells and their 
surrounding microenvironment, which contributes to drug resistance via secretion 
of sEVs from senescent stromal cells. SIGNIFICANCE: Senescent stromal cells 
produce a large number of sEVs to promote cancer resistance in therapeutic 
settings, a process driven by SIRT1 decline in stromal cells and ABCB4 
augmentation in cancer cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="571~581" text="SIRT1 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1010~1047" text="Targeting SIRT1 with agonist  SRT2104" perturbingaction="pharmacological augmentation" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="854~866" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1125~1148" text="senescent stromal cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>