<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Altered mitochondria functionality defines a metastatic cell state in lung 
cancer and creates an exploitable vulnerability.

Lung cancer is a prevalent and lethal cancer type that leads to more deaths than 
the next four major cancer types combined. Metastatic cancer spread is 
responsible for most cancer deaths but the cellular changes that enable cancer 
cells to leave the primary tumor and establish inoperable and lethal metastases 
remain poorly understood. To uncover genes that are specifically required to 
sustain metastasis survival or growth, we performed a genome-scale pooled 
lentiviral-shRNA library screen in cells that represent non-metastatic and 
metastatic states of lung adenocarcinoma. Mitochondrial ribosome and 
mitochondria-associated genes were identified as top gene sets associated with 
metastasis-specific lethality. Metastasis-derived cell lines in vitro and 
metastases analyzed ex vivo from an autochthonous lung cancer mouse model had 
lower mitochondrial membrane potential and reduced mitochondrial functionality 
than non-metastatic primary tumors. Electron microscopy of metastases uncovered 
irregular mitochondria with bridging and loss of normal membrane structure. 
Consistent with these findings, compounds that inhibit mitochondrial translation 
or replication had a greater effect on the growth of metastasis-derived cells. 
Finally, mice with established tumors developed fewer metastases upon treatment 
with phenformin in vivo. These results suggest that the metastatic cell state in 
lung adenocarcinoma is associated with a specifically altered mitochondrial 
functionality that can be therapeutically exploited.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1383~1387" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1405~1411" text="tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1471~1478" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="629~634" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1428~1438" text="metastases" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1412~1427" text="developed fewer" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>