<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Dysregulated Glutamate Transporter SLC1A1 Propels Cystine Uptake via Xc(-) for 
Glutathione Synthesis in Lung Cancer.

Cancer cells need to generate large amounts of glutathione (GSH) to buffer 
oxidative stress during tumor development. A rate-limiting step for GSH 
biosynthesis is cystine uptake via a cystine/glutamate antiporter Xc-. Xc- is a 
sodium-independent antiporter passively driven by concentration gradients from 
extracellular cystine and intracellular glutamate across the cell membrane. 
Increased uptake of cystine via Xc- in cancer cells increases the level of 
extracellular glutamate, which would subsequently restrain cystine uptake via 
Xc-. Cancer cells must therefore evolve a mechanism to overcome this negative 
feedback regulation. In this study, we report that glutamate transporters, in 
particular SLC1A1, are tightly intertwined with cystine uptake and GSH 
biosynthesis in lung cancer cells. Dysregulated SLC1A1, a sodium-dependent 
glutamate carrier, actively recycled extracellular glutamate into cells, which 
enhanced the efficiency of cystine uptake via Xc- and GSH biosynthesis as 
measured by stable isotope-assisted metabolomics. Conversely, depletion of 
glutamate transporter SLC1A1 increased extracellular glutamate, which inhibited 
cystine uptake, blocked GSH synthesis, and induced oxidative stress-mediated 
cell death or growth inhibition. Moreover, glutamate transporters were 
frequently upregulated in tissue samples of patients with non-small cell lung 
cancer. Taken together, active uptake of glutamate via SLC1A1 propels cystine 
uptake via Xc- for GSH biosynthesis in lung tumorigenesis. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1184~1226" text="depletion of  glutamate transporter SLC1A1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1357~1367" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1322~1329" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>