<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Ablation of the Brca1-Palb2 Interaction Phenocopies Fanconi Anemia in Mice.

Heterozygous mutations in the BRCA1 gene predispose women to breast and ovarian 
cancer, while biallelic BRCA1 mutations are a cause of Fanconi anemia (FA), a 
rare genetic disorder characterized by developmental abnormalities, early-onset 
bone marrow failure, increased risk of cancers, and hypersensitivity to 
DNA-crosslinking agents. BRCA1 is critical for homologous recombination of DNA 
double-strand breaks (DSB). Through its coiled-coil domain, BRCA1 interacts with 
an essential partner, PALB2, recruiting BRCA2 and RAD51 to sites of DNA damage. 
Missense mutations within the coiled-coil domain of BRCA1 (e.g., L1407P) that 
affect the interaction with PALB2 have been reported in familial breast cancer. 
We hypothesized that if PALB2 regulates or mediates BRCA1 tumor suppressor 
function, ablation of the BRCA1-PALB2 interaction may also elicit genomic 
instability and tumor susceptibility. We generated mice defective for the 
Brca1-Palb2 interaction (Brca1 L1363P in mice) and established MEF cells from 
these mice. Brca1 L1363P/L1363P MEF exhibited hypersensitivity to DNA-damaging 
agents and failed to recruit Rad51 to DSB. Brca1 L1363P/L1363P mice were viable 
but exhibited various FA symptoms including growth retardation, 
hyperpigmentation, skeletal abnormalities, and male/female infertility. 
Furthermore, all Brca1 L1363P/L1363P mice exhibited macrocytosis and died due to 
bone marrow failure or lymphoblastic lymphoma/leukemia with activating Notch1 
mutations. These phenotypes closely recapitulate clinical features observed in 
patients with FA. Collectively, this model effectively demonstrates the 
significance of the BRCA1-PALB2 interaction in genome integrity and provides an 
FA model to investigate hematopoietic stem cells for mechanisms underlying 
progressive failure of hematopoiesis and associated development of 
leukemia/lymphoma, and other FA phenotypes.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="996~1000" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1083~1092" text="MEF cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1105~1109" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1435~1439" text="mice" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>