<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Extracellular Vesicle-Derived miR-124 Resolves Radiation-Induced Brain Injury.

Radiation-induced cognitive dysfunction (RICD) is a progressive and debilitating 
health issue facing patients following cranial radiotherapy to control central 
nervous system cancers. There has been some success treating RICD in rodents 
using human neural stem cell (hNSC) transplantation, but the procedure is 
invasive, requires immunosuppression, and could cause other complications such 
as teratoma formation. Extracellular vesicles (EV) are nanoscale membrane-bound 
structures that contain biological contents including mRNA, miRNA, proteins, and 
lipids that can be readily isolated from conditioned culture media. It has been 
previously shown that hNSC-derived EV resolves RICD following cranial 
irradiation using an immunocompromised rodent model. Here, we use 
immunocompetent wild-type mice to show that hNSC-derived EV treatment 
administered either intravenously via retro-orbital vein injection or via 
intracranial transplantation can ameliorate cognitive deficits following 9 Gy 
head-only irradiation. Cognitive function assessed on the novel place 
recognition, novel object recognition, and temporal order tasks was not only 
improved at early (5 weeks) but also at delayed (6 months) postirradiation times 
with just a single EV treatment. Improved behavioral outcomes were also 
associated with reduced neuroinflammation as measured by a reduction in 
activated microglia. To identify the mechanism of action, analysis of EV cargo 
implicated miRNA (miR-124) as a potential candidate in the mitigation of RICD. 
Furthermore, viral vector-mediated overexpression of miR-124 in the irradiated 
brain ameliorated RICD and reduced microglial activation. Our findings 
demonstrate for the first time that systemic administration of hNSC-derived EV 
abrogates RICD and neuroinflammation in cranially irradiated wild-type rodents 
through a mechanism involving miR-124.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1632~1679" text="viral vector-mediated overexpression of miR-124" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="857~887" text="immunocompetent wild-type mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1469~1478" text="microglia" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1699~1704" text="brain" context="tissue/organ" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>