<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Allosteric SHP2 Inhibitor, IACS-13909, Overcomes EGFR-Dependent and 
EGFR-Independent Resistance Mechanisms toward Osimertinib.

Src homology 2 domain-containing phosphatase (SHP2) is a phosphatase that 
mediates signaling downstream of multiple receptor tyrosine kinases (RTK) and is 
required for full activation of the MAPK pathway. SHP2 inhibition has 
demonstrated tumor growth inhibition in RTK-activated cancers in preclinical 
studies. The long-term effectiveness of tyrosine kinase inhibitors such as the 
EGFR inhibitor (EGFRi), osimertinib, in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) is 
limited by acquired resistance. Multiple clinically identified mechanisms 
underlie resistance to osimertinib, including mutations in EGFR that preclude 
drug binding as well as EGFR-independent activation of the MAPK pathway through 
alternate RTK (RTK-bypass). It has also been noted that frequently a tumor from 
a single patient harbors more than one resistance mechanism, and the plasticity 
between multiple resistance mechanisms could restrict the effectiveness of 
therapies targeting a single node of the oncogenic signaling network. Here, we 
report the discovery of IACS-13909, a specific and potent allosteric inhibitor 
of SHP2, that suppresses signaling through the MAPK pathway. IACS-13909 potently 
impeded proliferation of tumors harboring a broad spectrum of activated RTKs as 
the oncogenic driver. In EGFR-mutant osimertinib-resistant NSCLC models with 
EGFR-dependent and EGFR-independent resistance mechanisms, IACS-13909, 
administered as a single agent or in combination with osimertinib, potently 
suppressed tumor cell proliferation in vitro and caused tumor regression in 
vivo. Together, our findings provide preclinical evidence for using a SHP2 
inhibitor as a therapeutic strategy in acquired EGFRi-resistant NSCLC. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1171~1234" text="IACS-13909, a specific and potent allosteric inhibitor  of SHP2" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1334~1340" text="tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1628~1638" text="tumor cell" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1653~1661" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1690~1698" text="in  vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1317~1330" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1639~1652" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1673~1689" text="tumor regression" phenotype="tumour regression" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1309~1316" text="impeded" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1617~1627" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1666~1672" text="caused" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>