<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Fibroblasts from Distinct Pancreatic Pathologies Exhibit Disease-Specific 
Properties.

Although fibrotic stroma forms an integral component of pancreatic diseases, 
whether fibroblasts programmed by different types of pancreatic diseases are 
phenotypically distinct remains unknown. Here, we show that fibroblasts isolated 
from patients with pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC), chronic pancreatitis 
(CP), periampullary tumors, and adjacent normal (NA) tissue (N = 34) have 
distinct mRNA and miRNA profiles. Compared with NA fibroblasts, PDAC-associated 
fibroblasts were generally less sensitive to an antifibrotic stimulus (NPPB) and 
more responsive to positive regulators of activation such as TGFβ1 and WNT. Of 
the disease-associated fibroblasts examined, PDAC- and CP-derived fibroblasts 
shared greatest similarity, yet PDAC-associated fibroblasts expressed higher 
levels of tenascin C (TNC), a finding attributable to miR-137, a novel regulator 
of TNC. TNC protein and transcript levels were higher in PDAC tissue versus CP 
tissue and were associated with greater levels of stromal activation, and 
conditioned media from TNC-depleted PDAC-associated fibroblasts modestly 
increased both PDAC cell proliferation and PDAC cell migration, indicating that 
stromal TNC may have inhibitory effects on PDAC cells. Finally, circulating TNC 
levels were higher in patients with PDAC compared with CP. Our characterization 
of pancreatic fibroblast programming as disease-specific has consequences for 
therapeutic targeting and for the manner in which fibroblasts are used in 
research.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="547~575" text="PDAC-associated  fibroblasts" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1209~1218" text="PDAC cell" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1237~1246" text="PDAC cell" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1219~1232" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1247~1256" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1194~1203" text="increased" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>