<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[FGF Trapping Inhibits Multiple Myeloma Growth through c-Myc Degradation-Induced 
Mitochondrial Oxidative Stress.

Multiple myeloma, the second most common hematologic malignancy, frequently 
relapses because of chemotherapeutic resistance. Fibroblast growth factors (FGF) 
act as proangiogenic and mitogenic cytokines in multiple myeloma. Here, we 
demonstrate that the autocrine FGF/FGFR axis is essential for multiple myeloma 
cell survival and progression by protecting multiple myeloma cells from 
oxidative stress-induced apoptosis. In keeping with the hypothesis that the 
intracellular redox status can be a target for cancer therapy, FGF/FGFR blockade 
by FGF trapping or tyrosine kinase inhibitor impaired the growth and 
dissemination of multiple myeloma cells by inducing mitochondrial oxidative 
stress, DNA damage, and apoptotic cell death that were prevented by the 
antioxidant vitamin E or mitochondrial catalase overexpression. In addition, 
mitochondrial oxidative stress occurred as a consequence of proteasomal 
degradation of the c-Myc oncoprotein that led to glutathione depletion. 
Accordingly, expression of a proteasome-nondegradable c-Myc protein mutant was 
sufficient to avoid glutathione depletion and rescue the proapoptotic effects 
due to FGF blockade. These findings were confirmed on bortezomib-resistant 
multiple myeloma cells as well as on bone marrow-derived primary multiple 
myeloma cells from newly diagnosed and relapsed/refractory patients, including 
plasma cells bearing the t(4;14) translocation obtained from patients with 
high-risk multiple myeloma. Altogether, these findings dissect the mechanism by 
which the FGF/FGFR system plays a nonredundant role in multiple myeloma cell 
survival and disease progression, and indicate that FGF targeting may represent 
a therapeutic approach for patients with multiple myeloma with poor prognosis 
and advanced disease stage.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1118~1179" text="expression of a proteasome-nondegradable c-Myc protein mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="748~770" text="multiple myeloma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1318~1362" text="bortezomib-resistant  multiple myeloma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1377~1428" text="bone marrow-derived primary multiple  myeloma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1495~1507" text="plasma cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="832~852" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="774~782" text="inducing" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>