<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[NRAS Status Determines Sensitivity to SHP2 Inhibitor Combination Therapies 
Targeting the RAS-MAPK Pathway in Neuroblastoma.

Survival for high-risk neuroblastoma remains poor and treatment for relapsed 
disease rarely leads to long-term cures. Large sequencing studies of 
neuroblastoma tumors from diagnosis have not identified common targetable driver 
mutations other than the 10% of tumors that harbor mutations in the anaplastic 
lymphoma kinase (ALK) gene. However, at neuroblastoma recurrence, more frequent 
mutations in genes in the RAS-MAPK pathway have been detected. The 
PTPN11-encoded tyrosine phosphatase SHP2 is an activator of the RAS pathway, and 
we and others have shown that pharmacologic inhibition of SHP2 suppresses the 
growth of various tumor types harboring KRAS mutations such as pancreatic and 
lung cancers. Here we report inhibition of growth and downstream RAS-MAPK 
signaling in neuroblastoma cells in response to treatment with the SHP2 
inhibitors SHP099, II-B08, and RMC-4550. However, neuroblastoma cell lines 
harboring endogenous NRAS Q61K mutation (which is commonly detected at relapse) 
or isogenic neuroblastoma cells engineered to overexpress NRASQ61K were 
distinctly resistant to SHP2 inhibitors. Combinations of SHP2 inhibitors with 
other RAS pathway inhibitors such as trametinib, vemurafenib, and ulixertinib 
were synergistic and reversed resistance to SHP2 inhibition in neuroblastoma in 
vitro and in vivo. These results suggest for the first time that combination 
therapies targeting SHP2 and other components of the RAS-MAPK pathway may be 
effective against conventional therapy-resistant relapsed neuroblastoma, 
including those that have acquired NRAS mutations.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="967~1012" text="SHP2  inhibitors SHP099, II-B08, and RMC-4550" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1176~1196" text="overexpress NRASQ61K" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1227~1242" text="SHP2 inhibitors" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1260~1275" text="SHP2 inhibitors" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1405~1420" text="SHP2 inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="913~932" text="neuroblastoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1023~1047" text="neuroblastoma cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1142~1161" text="neuroblastoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1424~1437" text="neuroblastoma" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1438~1447" text="in  vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1452~1459" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>