<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MDM2 and MDMX promote ferroptosis by PPARα-mediated lipid remodeling.

MDM2 and MDMX, negative regulators of the tumor suppressor p53, can work 
separately and as a heteromeric complex to restrain p53's functions. MDM2 also 
has pro-oncogenic roles in cells, tissues, and animals that are independent of 
p53. There is less information available about p53-independent roles of MDMX or 
the MDM2-MDMX complex. We found that MDM2 and MDMX facilitate ferroptosis in 
cells with or without p53. Using small molecules, RNA interference reagents, and 
mutant forms of MDMX, we found that MDM2 and MDMX, likely working in part as a 
complex, normally facilitate ferroptotic death. We observed that MDM2 and MDMX 
alter the lipid profile of cells to favor ferroptosis. Inhibition of MDM2 or 
MDMX leads to increased levels of FSP1 protein and a consequent increase in the 
levels of coenzyme Q10, an endogenous lipophilic antioxidant. This suggests that 
MDM2 and MDMX normally prevent cells from mounting an adequate defense against 
lipid peroxidation and thereby promote ferroptosis. Moreover, we found that 
PPARα activity is essential for MDM2 and MDMX to promote ferroptosis, suggesting 
that the MDM2-MDMX complex regulates lipids through altering PPARα activity. 
These findings reveal the complexity of cellular responses to MDM2 and MDMX and 
suggest that MDM2-MDMX inhibition might be useful for preventing degenerative 
diseases involving ferroptosis. Furthermore, they suggest that MDM2/MDMX 
amplification may predict sensitivity of some cancers to ferroptosis inducers.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="546~566" text="mutant forms of MDMX" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="761~788" text="Inhibition of MDM2 or  MDMX" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="733~738" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="655~672" text="ferroptotic death" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="748~759" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="644~654" text="facilitate" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="742~747" text="favor" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>