<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mitochondria-to-nucleus retrograde signaling drives formation of cytoplasmic 
chromatin and inflammation in senescence.

Cellular senescence is a potent tumor suppressor mechanism but also contributes 
to aging and aging-related diseases. Senescence is characterized by a stable 
cell cycle arrest and a complex proinflammatory secretome, termed the 
senescence-associated secretory phenotype (SASP). We recently discovered that 
cytoplasmic chromatin fragments (CCFs), extruded from the nucleus of senescent 
cells, trigger the SASP through activation of the innate immunity cytosolic DNA 
sensing cGAS-STING pathway. However, the upstream signaling events that 
instigate CCF formation remain unknown. Here, we show that dysfunctional 
mitochondria, linked to down-regulation of nuclear-encoded mitochondrial 
oxidative phosphorylation genes, trigger a ROS-JNK retrograde signaling pathway 
that drives CCF formation and hence the SASP. JNK links to 53BP1, a nuclear 
protein that negatively regulates DNA double-strand break (DSB) end resection 
and CCF formation. Importantly, we show that low-dose HDAC inhibitors restore 
expression of most nuclear-encoded mitochondrial oxidative phosphorylation 
genes, improve mitochondrial function, and suppress CCFs and the SASP in 
senescent cells. In mouse models, HDAC inhibitors also suppress oxidative 
stress, CCF, inflammation, and tissue damage caused by senescence-inducing 
irradiation and/or acetaminophen-induced mitochondria dysfunction. Overall, our 
findings outline an extended mitochondria-to-nucleus retrograde signaling 
pathway that initiates formation of CCF during senescence and is a potential 
target for drug-based interventions to inhibit the proaging SASP.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1278~1293" text="senescent cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1298~1310" text="mouse models" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>