<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Induction of AP-1 by YAP/TAZ contributes to cell proliferation and organ growth.

Yes-associated protein (YAP) and its homolog transcriptional coactivator with 
PDZ-binding motif (TAZ) are key effectors of the Hippo pathway to control cell 
growth and organ size, of which dysregulation yields to tumorigenesis or 
hypertrophy. Upon activation, YAP/TAZ translocate into the nucleus and bind to 
TEAD transcription factors to promote transcriptional programs for proliferation 
or cell specification. Immediate early genes, represented by AP-1 complex, are 
rapidly induced and control later-phase transcriptional program to play key 
roles in tumorigenesis and organ maintenance. Here, we report that YAP/TAZ 
directly promote FOS transcription that in turn contributes to the biological 
function of YAP/TAZ. YAP/TAZ bind to the promoter region of FOS to stimulate its 
transcription. Deletion of YAP/TAZ blocks the induction of immediate early genes 
in response to mitogenic stimuli. FOS induction contributes to expression of 
YAP/TAZ downstream target genes. Genetic deletion or chemical inhibition of AP-1 
suppresses growth of YAP-driven cancer cells, such as Lats1/2-deficient cancer 
cells as well as Gαq/11 mutated uveal melanoma. Furthermore, AP-1 inhibition 
almost completely abrogates the hepatomegaly induced by YAP overexpression. Our 
findings reveal a feed-forward interplay between immediate early transcription 
of AP-1 and Hippo pathway function.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="886~905" text="Deletion of YAP/TAZ" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1084~1111" text="chemical inhibition of AP-1" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1167~1184" text="Lats1/2-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1254~1269" text="AP-1 inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1134~1157" text="YAP-driven cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1185~1198" text="cancer  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1225~1239" text="uveal melanoma" context="neoplasm" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>