<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Estrogen-related receptors are targetable ROS sensors.

Excessive reactive oxygen species (ROS) can cause oxidative stress and 
consequently cell injury contributing to a wide range of diseases. Addressing 
the critical gaps in our understanding of the adaptive molecular events 
downstream ROS provocation holds promise for the identification of druggable 
metabolic vulnerabilities. Here, we unveil a direct molecular link between the 
activity of two estrogen-related receptor (ERR) isoforms and the control of 
glutamine utilization and glutathione antioxidant production. ERRα 
down-regulation restricts glutamine entry into the TCA cycle, while ERRγ 
up-regulation promotes glutamine-driven glutathione production. Notably, we 
identify increased ERRγ expression/activation as a hallmark of oxidative stress 
triggered by mitochondrial disruption or chemotherapy. Enhanced tumor 
antioxidant capacity is an underlying feature of human breast cancer (BCa) 
patients that respond poorly to treatment. We demonstrate that pharmacological 
inhibition of ERRγ with the selective inverse agonist GSK5182 increases 
antitumor efficacy of the chemotherapeutic paclitaxel on poor outcome BCa tumor 
organoids. Our findings thus underscore the ERRs as novel redox sensors and 
effectors of a ROS defense program and highlight the potential therapeutic 
advantage of exploiting ERRγ inhibitors for the treatment of BCa and other 
diseases where oxidative stress plays a central role.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="577~598" text="ERRα  down-regulation" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="651~670" text="ERRγ  up-regulation" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1025~1103" text="pharmacological  inhibition of ERRγ with the selective inverse agonist GSK5182" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1185~1205" text="BCa tumor  organoids" context="organoid" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>