<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Stem cell niche-specific Ebf3 maintains the bone marrow cavity.

Bone marrow is the tissue filling the space between bone surfaces. Hematopoietic 
stem cells (HSCs) are maintained by special microenvironments known as niches 
within bone marrow cavities. Mesenchymal cells, termed CXC chemokine ligand 12 
(CXCL12)-abundant reticular (CAR) cells or leptin receptor-positive (LepR+) 
cells, are a major cellular component of HSC niches that gives rise to 
osteoblasts in bone marrow. However, it remains unclear how osteogenesis is 
prevented in most CAR/LepR+ cells to maintain HSC niches and marrow cavities. 
Here, using lineage tracing, we found that the transcription factor early B-cell 
factor 3 (Ebf3) is preferentially expressed in CAR/LepR+ cells and that 
Ebf3-expressing cells are self-renewing mesenchymal stem cells in adult marrow. 
When Ebf3 is deleted in CAR/LepR+ cells, HSC niche function is severely 
impaired, and bone marrow is osteosclerotic with increased bone in aged mice. In 
mice lacking Ebf1 and Ebf3, CAR/LepR+ cells exhibiting a normal morphology are 
abundantly present, but their niche function is markedly impaired with depleted 
HSCs in infant marrow. Subsequently, the mutants become progressively more 
osteosclerotic, leading to the complete occlusion of marrow cavities in early 
adulthood. CAR/LepR+ cells differentiate into bone-producing cells with reduced 
HSC niche factor expression in the absence of Ebf1/Ebf3 Thus, HSC cellular 
niches express Ebf3 that is required to create HSC niches, to inhibit their 
osteoblast differentiation, and to maintain spaces for HSCs.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="852~867" text="Ebf3 is deleted" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1007~1028" text="lacking Ebf1 and Ebf3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1434~1454" text="absence of Ebf1/Ebf3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="871~886" text="CAR/LepR+ cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="987~996" text="aged mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1002~1006" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1030~1045" text="CAR/LepR+ cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1163~1167" text="HSCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1329~1344" text="CAR/LepR+ cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1345~1358" text="differentiate" phenotype="differentiation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>