<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The KDM5A/RBP2 histone demethylase represses NOTCH signaling to sustain 
neuroendocrine differentiation and promote small cell lung cancer tumorigenesis.

More than 90% of small cell lung cancers (SCLCs) harbor loss-of-function 
mutations in the tumor suppressor gene RB1 The canonical function of the RB1 
gene product, pRB, is to repress the E2F transcription factor family, but pRB 
also functions to regulate cellular differentiation in part through its binding 
to the histone demethylase KDM5A (also known as RBP2 or JARID1A). We show that 
KDM5A promotes SCLC proliferation and SCLC's neuroendocrine differentiation 
phenotype in part by sustaining expression of the neuroendocrine transcription 
factor ASCL1. Mechanistically, we found that KDM5A sustains ASCL1 levels and 
neuroendocrine differentiation by repressing NOTCH2 and NOTCH target genes. To 
test the role of KDM5A in SCLC tumorigenesis in vivo, we developed a 
CRISPR/Cas9-based mouse model of SCLC by delivering an adenovirus (or an 
adeno-associated virus [AAV]) that expresses Cre recombinase and sgRNAs 
targeting Rb1, Tp53, and Rbl2 into the lungs of Lox-Stop-Lox Cas9 mice. 
Coinclusion of a KDM5A sgRNA decreased SCLC tumorigenesis and metastasis, and 
the SCLCs that formed despite the absence of KDM5A had higher NOTCH activity 
compared to KDM5A +/+ SCLCs. This work establishes a role for KDM5A in SCLC 
tumorigenesis and suggests that KDM5 inhibitors should be explored as treatments 
for SCLC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="987~1108" text="adenovirus (or an  adeno-associated virus [AAV]) that expresses Cre recombinase and sgRNAs  targeting Rb1, Tp53, and Rbl2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1191~1195" text="SCLC" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1118~1123" text="lungs" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1145~1149" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="950~969" text="mouse model of SCLC" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1196~1209" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1214~1224" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1181~1190" text="decreased" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>