<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Inactivation of MTOR promotes autophagy-mediated epithelial injury in 
particulate matter-induced airway inflammation.

Particulate matter (PM) is able to induce airway epithelial injury, while the 
detailed mechanisms remain unclear. Here we demonstrated that PM exposure 
inactivated MTOR (mechanistic target of rapamycin kinase), enhanced 
macroautophagy/autophagy, and impaired lysosomal activity in HBE (human 
bronchial epithelial) cells and in mouse airway epithelium. Genetic or 
pharmaceutical inhibition of MTOR significantly enhanced, while inhibition of 
autophagy attenuated, PM-induced IL6 expression in HBE cells. Consistently, 
club-cell-specific deletion of Mtor aggravated, whereas loss of Atg5 in 
bronchial epithelium reduced, PM-induced airway inflammation. Interestingly, the 
augmented inflammatory responses caused by MTOR deficiency were markedly 
attenuated by blockage of downstream autophagy both in vitro and in vivo. 
Mechanistically, the dysregulation of MTOR-autophagy signaling was partially 
dependent on activation of upstream TSC2, and interacted with the TLR4-MYD88 to 
orchestrate the downstream NFKB activity and to regulate the production of 
inflammatory cytokines in airway epithelium. Moreover, inhibition of autophagy 
reduced the expression of EPS15 and the subsequent endocytosis of PM. Taken 
together, the present study provides a mechanistic explanation for how airway 
epithelium localized MTOR-autophagy axis regulates PM-induced airway injury, 
suggesting that activation of MTOR and/or suppression of autophagy in local 
airway might be effective therapeutic strategies for PM-related airway 
disorders.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="488~521" text="pharmaceutical inhibition of MTOR" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="644~679" text="club-cell-specific deletion of Mtor" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="700~737" text="loss of Atg5 in  bronchial epithelium" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="842~857" text="MTOR deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="404~443" text="HBE (human  bronchial epithelial) cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="451~474" text="mouse airway epithelium" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="618~627" text="HBE cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="925~933" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="938~945" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="358~367" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="333~341" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>