<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[GABARAPs and LC3s have opposite roles in regulating ULK1 for autophagy 
induction.

ULK1 (unc-51 like autophagy activating kinase 1) is the key mediator of MTORC1 
signaling to macroautophagy/autophagy. ULK1 functions as a protein complex by 
interacting with ATG13, RB1CC1/FIP200, and ATG101. How the ULK1 complex is 
regulated to trigger autophagy induction remains unclear. In this study, we have 
determined roles of Atg8-family proteins (ATG8s) in regulating ULK1 activity and 
autophagy. Using human cells depleted of each subfamily of ATG8, we found that 
the GABARAP subfamily positively regulates ULK1 activity and phagophore and 
autophagosome formation in response to starvation. In contrast, the LC3 
subfamily negatively regulates ULK1 activity and phagophore formation. By 
reconstituting ATG8-depleted cells with individual ATG8 members, we identified 
GABARAP and GABARAPL1 as positive and LC3B and LC3C as negative regulators of 
ULK1 activity. To address the role of ATG8 binding to ULK1, we mutated the LIR 
of endogenous ULK1 to disrupt the ATG8-ULK1 interaction by genome editing. The 
mutation drastically reduced the activity of ULK1, autophagic degradation of 
SQSTM1, and phagophore formation in response to starvation. The mutation also 
suppressed the formation and turnover of autophagosomes in response to 
starvation. Similar to the mutation of the ULK1 LIR, disruption of the 
ATG13-ATG8 interaction suppressed ULK1 activity and autophagosome formation. In 
contrast, RB1CC1 did not show any specific binding to ATG8s, and mutation of its 
LIR did not affect ULK1 activity. Together, this study demonstrates differential 
binding and opposite regulation of the ULK1 complex by GABARAPs and LC3s, and an 
important role of the ULK1- and ATG13-ATG8 interactions in autophagy 
induction.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1010~1045" text="mutated the LIR  of endogenous ULK1" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="500~511" text="human cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="817~822" text="cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>