<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[REDD1 loss reprograms lipid metabolism to drive progression of RAS mutant 
tumors.

Human cancers with activating RAS mutations are typically highly aggressive and 
treatment-refractory, yet RAS mutation itself is insufficient for tumorigenesis, 
due in part to profound metabolic stress induced by RAS activation. Here we show 
that loss of REDD1, a stress-induced metabolic regulator, is sufficient to 
reprogram lipid metabolism and drive progression of RAS mutant cancers. Redd1 
deletion in genetically engineered mouse models (GEMMs) of KRAS-dependent 
pancreatic and lung adenocarcinomas converts preneoplastic lesions into invasive 
and metastatic carcinomas. Metabolic profiling reveals that REDD1-deficient/RAS 
mutant cells exhibit enhanced uptake of lysophospholipids and lipid storage, 
coupled to augmented fatty acid oxidation that sustains both ATP levels and 
ROS-detoxifying NADPH. Mechanistically, REDD1 loss triggers HIF-dependent 
activation of a lipid storage pathway involving PPARγ and the prometastatic 
factor CD36. Correspondingly, decreased REDD1 expression and a signature of 
REDD1 loss predict poor outcomes selectively in RAS mutant but not RAS wild-type 
human lung and pancreas carcinomas. Collectively, our findings reveal the 
REDD1-mediated stress response as a novel tumor suppressor whose loss defines a 
RAS mutant tumor subset characterized by reprogramming of lipid metabolism, 
invasive and metastatic progression, and poor prognosis. This work thus provides 
new mechanistic and clinically relevant insights into the phenotypic 
heterogeneity and metabolic rewiring that underlies these common cancers.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="477~492" text="Redd1  deletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="701~728" text="REDD1-deficient/RAS  mutant" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="917~927" text="REDD1 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="519~531" text="mouse models" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="559~594" text="pancreatic and lung adenocarcinomas" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="729~734" text="cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>