<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[(+)-Clausenamide protects against drug-induced liver injury by inhibiting 
hepatocyte ferroptosis.

Drug-induced liver injury is the major cause of acute liver failure. However, 
the underlying mechanisms seem to be multifaceted and remain poorly understood, 
resulting in few effective therapies. Here, we report a novel mechanism that 
contributes to acetaminophen-induced hepatotoxicity through the induction of 
ferroptosis, a distinctive form of programmed cell death. We subsequently 
identified therapies protective against acetaminophen-induced liver damage and 
found that (+)-clausenamide ((+)-CLA), an active alkaloid isolated from the 
leaves of Clausena lansium (Lour.) Skeels, inhibited acetaminophen-induced 
hepatocyte ferroptosis both in vivo and in vitro. Consistently, (+)-CLA 
significantly alleviated acetaminophen-induced or erastin-induced hepatic 
pathological damages, hepatic dysfunctions and excessive production of lipid 
peroxidation both in cultured hepatic cell lines and mouse liver. Furthermore, 
treatment with (+)-CLA reduced the mRNA level of prostaglandin endoperoxide 
synthase 2 while it increased the protein level of glutathione peroxidase 4 in 
hepatocytes and mouse liver, confirming that the inhibition of ferroptosis 
contributes to the protective effect of (+)-CLA on drug-induced liver damage. We 
further revealed that (+)-CLA specifically reacted with the Cys-151 residue of 
Keap1, which blocked Nrf2 ubiquitylation and resulted in an increased Nrf2 
stability, thereby leading to the activation of the Keap1-Nrf2 pathway to 
prevent drug-induced hepatocyte ferroptosis. Our studies illustrate the 
innovative mechanisms of acetaminophen-induced liver damage and present a novel 
intervention strategy to treat drug overdose by using (+)-CLA.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="724~734" text="hepatocyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="752~759" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="764~772" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="980~998" text="hepatic cell lines" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1003~1014" text="mouse liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1187~1198" text="hepatocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1203~1214" text="mouse liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1597~1607" text="hepatocyte" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="735~746" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1608~1619" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="691~700" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1576~1583" text="prevent" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>