<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Scutellarin ameliorates pulmonary fibrosis through inhibiting 
NF-κB/NLRP3-mediated epithelial-mesenchymal transition and inflammation.

Idiopathic pulmonary fibrosis (IPF) is featured with inflammation and extensive 
lung remodeling caused by overloaded deposition of extracellular matrix. 
Scutellarin is the major effective ingredient of breviscapine and its 
anti-inflammation efficacy has been reported before. Nevertheless, the impact of 
scutellarin on IPF and the downstream molecular mechanism remain unclear. In 
this study, scutellarin suppressed BLM-induced inflammation via NF-κB/NLRP3 
pathway both in vivo and in vitro. BLM significantly elevated p-p65/p65 ratio, 
IκBα degradation, and levels of NLRP3, caspase-1, caspase-11, ASC, GSDMDNterm, 
IL-1β, and IL-18, while scutellarin reversed the above alterations except for 
that of caspase-11. Scutellarin inhibited BLM-induced epithelial-mesenchymal 
transition (EMT) process in vivo and in vitro. The expression levels of 
EMT-related markers, including fibronectin, vimentin, N-cadherin, matrix 
metalloproteinase 2 (MMP-2) and MMP-9, were increased in BLM group, and 
suppressed by scutellarin. The expression level of E-cadherin showed the 
opposite changes. However, overexpression of NLRP3 eliminated the 
anti-inflammation and anti-EMT functions of scutellarin in vitro. In conclusion, 
scutellarin suppressed inflammation and EMT in BLM-induced pulmonary fibrosis 
through NF-κB/NLRP3 signaling.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1238~1261" text="overexpression of NLRP3" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="613~620" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="625~633" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="942~949" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="954~962" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1334~1342" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="893~941" text="epithelial-mesenchymal  transition (EMT) process" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1400~1403" text="EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="871~880" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="885~892" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1372~1382" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>