<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Blockade of EIF5A hypusination limits colorectal cancer growth by inhibiting MYC 
elongation.

Eukaryotic Translation Initiation Factor 5A (EIF5A) is a translation factor 
regulated by hypusination, a unique posttranslational modification catalyzed by 
deoxyhypusine synthetase (DHPS) and deoxyhypusine hydroxylase (DOHH) starting 
from the polyamine spermidine. Emerging data are showing that hypusinated EIF5A 
regulates key cellular processes such as autophagy, senescence, polyamine 
homeostasis, energy metabolism, and plays a role in cancer. However, the effects 
of EIF5A inhibition in preclinical cancer models, the mechanism of action, and 
specific translational targets are still poorly understood. We show here that 
hypusinated EIF5A promotes growth of colorectal cancer (CRC) cells by directly 
regulating MYC biosynthesis at specific pausing motifs. Inhibition of EIF5A 
hypusination with the DHPS inhibitor GC7 or through lentiviral-mediated 
knockdown of DHPS or EIF5A reduces the growth of various CRC cells. Multiplex 
gene expression analysis reveals that inhibition of hypusination impairs the 
expression of transcripts regulated by MYC, suggesting the involvement of this 
oncogene in the observed effect. Indeed, we demonstrate that EIF5A regulates MYC 
elongation without affecting its mRNA content or protein stability, by 
alleviating ribosome stalling at five distinct pausing motifs in MYC CDS. Of 
note, we show that blockade of the hypusination axis elicits a remarkable growth 
inhibitory effect in preclinical models of CRC and significantly reduces the 
size of polyps in APCMin/+ mice, a model of human familial adenomatous polyposis 
(FAP). Together, these data illustrate an unprecedented mechanism, whereby the 
tumor-promoting properties of hypusinated EIF5A are linked to its ability to 
regulate MYC elongation and provide a rationale for the use of DHPS/EIF5A 
inhibitors in CRC therapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="938~985" text="lentiviral-mediated  knockdown of DHPS or EIF5A" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1606~1614" text="APCMin/+" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="766~795" text="colorectal cancer (CRC) cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1016~1025" text="CRC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1531~1556" text="preclinical models of CRC" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1615~1619" text="mice" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>