<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[PDK4 promotes vascular calcification by interfering with autophagic activity and 
metabolic reprogramming.

Pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 4 (PDK4) is an important mitochondrial matrix 
enzyme in cellular energy regulation. Previous studies suggested that PDK4 is 
increased in the calcified vessels of patients with atherosclerosis and is 
closely associated with mitochondrial function, but the precise regulatory 
mechanisms remain largely unknown. This study aims to investigate the role of 
PDK4 in vascular calcification and the molecular mechanisms involved. Using a 
variety of complementary techniques, we found impaired autophagic activity in 
the process of vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) calcification, whereas 
knocking down PDK4 had the opposite effect. PDK4 drives the metabolic 
reprogramming of VSMCs towards a Warburg effect, and the inhibition of PDK4 
abrogates VSMCs calcification. Mechanistically, PDK4 disturbs the integrity of 
the mitochondria-associated endoplasmic reticulum membrane, concomitantly 
impairing mitochondrial respiratory capacity, which contributes to a decrease in 
lysosomal degradation by inhibiting the V-ATPase and lactate dehydrogenase B 
interaction. PDK4 also inhibits the nuclear translocation of the transcription 
factor EB, thus inhibiting lysosomal function. These changes result in the 
interruption of autophagic flux, which accelerates calcium deposition in VSMCs. 
In addition, glycolysis serves as a metabolic adaptation to improve VSMCs 
oxidative stress resistance, whereas inhibition of glycolysis by 
2-deoxy-D-glucose induces the apoptosis of VSMCs and increases the calcium 
deposition in VSMCs. Our results suggest that PDK4 plays a key role in vascular 
calcification through autophagy inhibition and metabolic reprogramming.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="729~747" text="knocking down PDK4" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1421~1426" text="VSMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1613~1618" text="VSMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1660~1665" text="VSMCs" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1364~1379" text="autophagic flux" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1600~1609" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1588~1595" text="induces" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>