<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Discovery of a novel ferroptosis inducer-talaroconvolutin A-killing colorectal 
cancer cells in vitro and in vivo.

Ferropotsis is among the most important mechanisms of cancer suppression, which 
could be harnessed for cancer therapy. However, no natural small-molecule 
compounds with cancer inhibitory activity have been identified to date. In the 
present study, we reported the discovery of a novel ferroptosis inducer, 
talaroconvolutin A (TalaA), and the underlying molecular mechanism. We 
discovered that TalaA killed colorectal cancer cells in dose-dependent and 
time-dependent manners. Interestingly, TalaA did not induce apoptosis, but 
strongly triggered ferroptosis. Notably, TalaA was significantly more effective 
than erastin (a well-known ferroptosis inducer) in suppressing colorectal cancer 
cells via ferroptosis. We revealed a dual mechanism of TalaA' action against 
cancer. On the one hand, TalaA considerably increased reactive oxygen species 
levels to a certain threshold, the exceeding of which induced ferroptosis. On 
the other hand, this compound downregulated the expression of the channel 
protein solute carrier family 7 member 11 (SLC7A11) but upregulated arachidonate 
lipoxygenase 3 (ALOXE3), promoting ferroptosis. Furthermore, in vivo experiments 
in mice evidenced that TalaA effectively suppressed the growth of xenografted 
colorectal cancer cells without obvious liver and kidney toxicities. The 
findings of this study indicated that TalaA could be a new potential powerful 
drug candidate for colorectal cancer therapy due to its outstanding ability to 
kill colorectal cancer cells via ferroptosis induction.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="527~550" text="colorectal cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="794~818" text="colorectal cancer  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1267~1274" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1291~1295" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1354~1390" text="xenografted  colorectal cancer cells" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="634~643" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="669~680" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="823~834" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1032~1043" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1241~1252" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="619~633" text="did not induce" effect="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="659~668" text="triggered" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1024~1031" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1231~1240" text="promoting" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>