<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[LncRNA MM2P-induced, exosome-mediated transfer of Sox9 from monocyte-derived 
cells modulates primary chondrocytes.

Monocyte-derived cells were shown to promote cartilage repair in osteoarthritis. 
The role of the long non-coding RNA (lncRNA) MM2P in this function of 
monocyte-derived cells remained unexplored. Treatment of RAW264.7 murine 
macrophages and mouse bone marrow-derived macrophages with IL-4 or IL-13 
upregulated MM2P expression, upstream of STAT3 and STAT6 phosphorylation. 
Specifically, MM2P blocked SHP2-mediated dephosphorylation of STAT3 at Try705 
and interacted with the RNA-binding protein FUS. In turn, p-STAT3 increased the 
Sox9 gene expression. These cells released Sox9 mRNA and protein-containing 
exosomes, as demonstrated by a transmission electron microscope, nanoparticle 
tracking analysis, and detection of typical surface markers. Their culture 
supernatant promoted the differentiation of mouse primary chondrocytes, i.e., 
upregulated the expression of Col1a2 and Acan genes and promoted the secretion 
of extracellular matrix components proteoglycan and type II collagen. These 
effects were mediated by Sox9 mRNA and protein delivered to chondrocytes by 
exosomes. Together, ex vivo treatment of monocyte-derived cells with IL-4 or 
IL-13 promoted chondrocyte differentiation and functions through 
exosome-mediated delivery of Sox9 mRNA and protein.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="327~355" text="RAW264.7 murine  macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="360~397" text="mouse bone marrow-derived macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="681~686" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="929~955" text="mouse primary chondrocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1239~1261" text="monocyte-derived cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1291~1302" text="chondrocyte" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="910~925" text="differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1303~1318" text="differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="897~905" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1282~1290" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>