<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Endothelin 1-induced retinal ganglion cell death is largely mediated by JUN 
activation.

Glaucoma is a neurodegenerative disease characterized by loss of retinal 
ganglion cells (RGCs), the output neurons of the retina. Multiple lines of 
evidence show the endothelin (EDN, also known as ET) system is important in 
glaucomatous neurodegeneration. To date, the molecular mechanisms within RGCs 
driving EDN-induced RGC death have not been clarified. The pro-apoptotic 
transcription factor JUN (the canonical target of JNK signaling) and the 
endoplasmic reticulum stress effector and transcription factor DNA damage 
inducible transcript 3 (DDIT3, also known as CHOP) have been shown to act 
downstream of EDN receptors. Previous studies demonstrated that JUN and DDIT3 
were important regulators of RGC death after glaucoma-relevant injures. Here, we 
characterized EDN insult in vivo and investigated the role of JUN and DDIT3 in 
EDN-induced RGC death. To accomplish this, EDN1 ligand was intravitreally 
injected into the eyes of wildtype, Six3-cre+Junfl/fl (Jun-/-), Ddit3 null 
(Ddit3-/-), and Ddit3-/-Jun-/- mice. Intravitreal EDN1 was sufficient to drive 
RGC death in vivo. EDN1 insult caused JUN activation in RGCs, and deletion of 
Jun from the neural retina attenuated RGC death after EDN insult. However, 
deletion of Ddit3 did not confer significant protection to RGCs after EDN1 
insult. These results indicate that EDN caused RGC death via a JUN-dependent 
mechanism. In addition, EDN signaling is known to elicit potent 
vasoconstriction. JUN signaling was shown to drive neuronal death after ischemic 
insult. Therefore, the effects of intravitreal EDN1 on retinal vessel diameter 
and hypoxia were explored. Intravitreal EDN1 caused transient retinal 
vasoconstriction and regions of RGC and Müller glia hypoxia. Thus, it remains a 
possibility that EDN elicits a hypoxic insult to RGCs, causing apoptosis via 
JNK-JUN signaling. The importance of EDN-induced vasoconstriction and hypoxia in 
causing RGC death after EDN insult and in models of glaucoma requires further 
investigation.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1046~1072" text="Six3-cre+Junfl/fl (Jun-/-)" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1074~1096" text="Ddit3 null  (Ddit3-/-)" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1102~1116" text="Ddit3-/-Jun-/-" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1232~1248" text="deletion of  Jun" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1321~1338" text="deletion of Ddit3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1117~1121" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1028~1032" text="eyes" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1176~1183" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1258~1271" text="neural retina" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1166~1169" text="RGC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1283~1286" text="RGC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1380~1384" text="RGCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1444~1447" text="RGC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1805~1808" text="RGC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C9" spans="1813~1824" text="Müller glia" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>