<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Dual inhibition of HDAC and tyrosine kinase signaling pathways with CUDC-907 
attenuates TGFβ1 induced lung and tumor fibrosis.

TGFβ1 signaling is a critical driver of collagen accumulation in pulmonary 
fibrotic diseases and a well-characterized regulator of cancer associated 
fibroblasts (CAF) activation in lung cancer. Myofibroblasts induced by TGFβ1 and 
other factors are key players in the pathogenesis of lung fibrosis and tumor. 
Tremendous attention has been gained to targeting myofibroblasts in order to 
inhibit the progression of fibrosis and myofibroblast-induced tumor progression 
and metastasis. Here we determined the therapeutic efficacy of simultaneously 
targeting PI3K and HDAC pathways in lung myofibroblasts and CAF with a single 
agent and to evaluate biomarkers of treatment response. CUDC-907 is a 
first-in-class compound, functioning as a dual inhibitor of HDACs and PI3K/AKT 
pathway. We investigated its effects in counteracting the activity of 
TGFβ1-induced myofibroblasts/CAF in regard to cell proliferation, migration, 
invasion, apoptosis in vitro antifibrosis efficiency in vivo. We found that 
CUDC-907 inhibited myofibroblasts/CAF cell proliferation, migration and 
apoptosis in a dose-dependent manner and caused cell cycle arrest at G1-S phase. 
CUDC-907 not only inhibited myofibroblasts markers expression, but also 
significantly inhibited the phosphorylation level of AKT, mTOR, Smad2/3, and 
promoted acetylation of histones. Furthermore, the observed inhibitory effect 
was also confirmed in bleomycin-induced mice lung fibrosis and nude mouse 
transplanted tumor model. Overall, these data suggest that dual inhibition of 
HDAC and the tyrosine kinase signaling pathways with CUDC-907 is a promising 
treatment strategy for TGFβ1-induced lung and tumor fibrosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1153~1177" text=" myofibroblasts/CAF cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1318~1332" text="myofibroblasts" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1178~1191" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1193~1202" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1208~1217" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1256~1273" text="cell cycle arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1144~1153" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1249~1255" text="caused" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>