<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Immunomodulatory activity of IR700-labelled affibody targeting HER2.

There is an urgent need to develop therapeutic approaches that can increase the 
response rate to immuno-oncology agents. Photoimmunotherapy has recently been 
shown to generate anti-tumour immunological responses by releasing 
tumour-associated antigens from ablated tumour cell residues, thereby enhancing 
antigenicity and adjuvanticity. Here, we investigate the feasibility of a novel 
HER2-targeted affibody-based conjugate (ZHER2:2395-IR700) selectively to induce 
cancer cell death in vitro and in vivo. The studies in vitro confirmed the 
specificity of ZHER2:2395-IR700 binding to HER2-positive cells and its ability 
to produce reactive oxygen species upon light irradiation. A conjugate 
concentration- and light irradiation-dependent decrease in cell viability was 
also demonstrated. Furthermore, light-activated ZHER2:2395-IR700 triggered all 
hallmarks of immunogenic cell death, as defined by the translocation of 
calreticulin to the cell surface, and the secretion of ATP, HSP70/90 and HMGB1 
from dying cancer cells into the medium. Irradiating a co-culture of immature 
dendritic cells (DCs) and cancer cells exposed to light-activated 
ZHER2:2395-IR700 enhanced DC maturation, as indicated by augmented expression of 
CD86 and HLA-DR. In SKOV-3 xenografts, the ZHER2:2395-IR700-based phototherapy 
delayed tumour growth and increased median overall survival. Collectively, our 
results strongly suggest that ZHER2:2395-IR700 is a promising new therapeutic 
conjugate that has great potential to be applicable for photoimmunotherapy-based 
regimens.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="660~679" text="HER2-positive cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="593~601" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1092~1104" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1150~1181" text="immature  dendritic cells (DCs)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1186~1198" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1253~1255" text="DC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1329~1346" text="SKOV-3 xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="828~842" text="cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="953~963" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1397~1410" text="tumour growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="816~824" text="decrease" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="913~922" text="triggered" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1389~1396" text="delayed" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>