<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ Mesenchymal stem cells alleviate LPS-induced acute lung injury by inhibiting the 
proinflammatory function of Ly6C(+) CD8(+) T cells.

Systemic inflammatory processes, including alveolar injury, cytokine induction, 
and neutrophil accumulation, play key roles in the pathophysiology of acute lung 
injury (ALI). The immunomodulatory effects of mesenchymal stem cells (MSCs) can 
contribute to the treatment of inflammatory disorders. In previous studies, the 
focus was on innate immune cells and the effects of MSCs on ALI through CD8+ T 
cells remain unclear. In the present study, lipopolysaccharide (LPS) was used to 
induce ALI in mice. ALI mice were treated with MSCs via intratracheal 
instillation. Survival rate, histopathological changes, protein levels, total 
cell count, cytokine levels, and chemokine levels in alveolar lavage fluid were 
used to determine the efficacy of MSCs. Mass cytometry and single-cell RNA 
sequencing (scRNA-seq) were used to characterize the CD8+ T cells in the lungs. 
Ly6C- CD8+ T cells are prevalent in normal mice, whereas a specialized effector 
phenotype expressing a high level of Ly6C is predominant in advanced disease. 
MSCs significantly mitigated ALI and improved survival. MSCs decreased the 
infiltration of CD8+ T cells, especially Ly6C+ CD8+ T cells into the lungs. Mass 
cytometry revealed that CD8+ T cells expressing high Ly6C and CXCR3 levels 
caused tissue damage in the lungs of ALI mice, which was alleviated by MSCs. The 
scRNA-seq showed that Ly6C+ CD8+ T cells exhibited a more activated phenotype 
and decreased expression of proinflammatory factors that were enriched the most 
in immune chemotaxis after treatment with MSCs. We showed that CD8+ T cells play 
an important role in MSC-mediated ALI remission, and both infiltration quantity 
and proinflammatory function were inhibited by MSCs, indicating a potential 
mechanism for therapeutic intervention.

]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="637~641" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="647~651" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1263~1275" text="CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1288~1306" text="Ly6C+ CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1446~1450" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1353~1365" text="CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1433~1438" text="lungs" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1509~1527" text="Ly6C+ CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>