<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Inhibiting the NLRP3 inflammasome with MCC950 ameliorates retinal 
neovascularization and leakage by reversing the IL-1β/IL-18 activation pattern 
in an oxygen-induced ischemic retinopathy mouse model.

Activation of the nucleotide-binding domain leucine-rich repeat and pyrin domain 
containing receptor 3 (NLRP3) inflammasome plays an important role in ocular 
neovascularization. In our study, we found that the expression and activation 
levels of NLRP3 inflammasome components, including NLRP3, an 
apoptosis-associated speck-like protein (ASC) containing caspase activation and 
recruitment domain (CARD) and caspase-1 (CAS1), were significantly upregulated. 
In addition, we found interleukin (IL)-1β activity increased while IL-18 
activity decreased in the retinas of oxygen-induced ischemic retinopathy (OIR) 
mice. MCC950, an inhibitor of NLRP3, reversed the IL-1β/IL-18 activation 
pattern, inhibited the formation of retinal neovascularization (RNV), decreased 
the number of acellular capillaries and reduced leakage of retinal vessels. 
Moreover, MCC950 could regulate the expression of endothelial cell- and pericyte 
function-associated molecules, such as vascular endothelial growth factor 
(VEGF), VEGF receptor (VEGFR)1, VEGFR2, matrix metalloproteinase (MMP)2, MMP9, 
tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinases (TIMP)1, TIMP2, platelet-derived growth 
factor receptor-β (PDGFR-β), platelet-derived growth factor-B (PDGF-B), and 
angiopoietin2 (Ang2). In vitro, recombinant human (r)IL-18 and rIL-1β regulated 
the expression of endothelial cell- and pericyte function-associated molecules 
and the proliferation and migration of endothelial cells and pericytes. We 
therefore determined that inhibiting the NLRP3 inflammasome with MCC950 can 
regulate the function of endothelial cells and pericytes by reversing the 
IL-1β/IL-18 activation pattern to ameliorate RNV and leakage; thereby opening 
new avenues to treat RNV-associated ocular diseases.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="826~855" text="MCC950, an inhibitor of NLRP3" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="820~824" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1468~1476" text="In vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1646~1663" text="endothelial cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1668~1677" text="pericytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1785~1802" text="endothelial cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1807~1816" text="pericytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1615~1628" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1633~1642" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1516~1525" text="regulated" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>