<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[M2 macrophage-induced lncRNA PCAT6 facilitates tumorigenesis and angiogenesis of 
triple-negative breast cancer through modulation of VEGFR2.

As a common female malignancy, triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) is the most 
malignant subtype of breast cancers (BC). This study further studied the role of 
long noncoding RNA (lncRNA) prostate cancer-associated transcript 6 (PCAT6) in 
TNBC. Functional assays, including EdU, wound healing, transwell, and 
immunofluorescence staining, revealed the effect of PCAT6 on cell proliferation, 
migration, and EMT process. The tube-formation assay disclosed the function of 
PCAT6 on angiogenesis. In vivo assays were also established to explore the 
impact of PCAT6 on tumor growth and microangiogenesis. The results revealed that 
PCAT6 boosted TNBC cell proliferation, migration, and angiogenesis both in vitro 
and in vivo. Then, this study unveiled that M2 macrophage secreted VEGF to 
stimulate the upregulation of PCAT6, thus promoting angiogenesis in TNBC. Next, 
through bioinformatics analysis and mechanism assays, we identified that PCAT6 
positively regulated VEGFR2 expression via ceRNA pattern and then participated 
in VEGFR/AKT/mTOR signaling pathway to accelerate angiogenesis. Moreover, PCAT6 
bound USP14, a deubiquitinase, to induce the deubiquitination of VEGFR2. On the 
whole, M2 macrophage-induced upregulation of PCAT6 facilitates TNBC 
tumorigenesis through modulation of VEGFR2 expression via ceRNA and 
deubiquitination patterns.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="791~800" text="TNBC cell" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="849~857" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="863~870" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1003~1007" text="TNBC" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1401~1405" text="TNBC" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="816~825" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1407~1420" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="801~814" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="783~790" text="boosted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1389~1400" text="facilitates" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>