<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Therapeutic effect of a histone demethylase inhibitor in Parkinson's disease.

Iron accumulation in the substantia nigra is recognized as a hallmark of 
Parkinson's disease (PD). Therefore, reducing accumulated iron and associated 
oxidative stress is considered a promising therapeutic strategy for PD. However, 
current iron chelators have poor membrane permeability and lack cell-type 
specificity. Here we identified GSK-J4, a histone demethylase inhibitor with the 
ability to cross blood brain barrier, as a potent iron suppressor. Only a trace 
amount of GSK-J4 significantly and selectively reduced intracellular labile iron 
in dopaminergic neurons, and suppressed H2O2 and 6-OHDA-induced cell death in 
vitro. The iron-suppressive effect was mainly mediated by inducing an increase 
in the expression of the iron exporter ferroportin-1. In parallel, GSK-J4 
rescued dopaminergic neuron loss and motor defects in 6-OHDA-induced PD rats, 
which was accompanied by reduction of oxidative stress. Importantly, GSK-J4 
rescued the abnormal changes of histone methylation, H3K4me3 and H3K27me3 during 
6-OHDA treatment although the iron-suppressive and neuroprotective effects were 
sensitive to H3K4me3 inhibition only. Also, upregulating H3K4me3 increased 
ferroportin-1 expression and neuroprotection. Taken together, we demonstrate a 
previously unappreciated action of GSK-J4 on cell-specific iron suppression and 
neuroprotection via epigenetic mechanism. Compared with conventional iron 
chelators, this compound has a stronger therapeutic potential for PD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1231~1251" text="upregulating H3K4me3" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1200~1218" text="H3K4me3 inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="637~657" text="dopaminergic neurons" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="709~718" text="in  vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="876~895" text="dopaminergic neuron" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="937~944" text="PD rats" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="698~708" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="663~673" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>