<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[BET degrader inhibits tumor progression and stem-like cell growth via 
Wnt/β-catenin signaling repression in glioma cells.

Based on their histological appearance, gliomas are a very common primary tumor 
type of the brain and are classified into grades, Grade I to Grade IV, of the 
World Health Organization. Treatment failure is due to the cancer stem cells 
(CSC) phenotype maintenance and self-renewal. BET degraders such as ZBC260 
represents a novel class of BET inhibitors that act by inducing BET proteins 
degradation. This study explores the mode of action and effects of ZBC260 in 
vivo and in vitro against glioma. By inhibiting cell proliferation and inducting 
cell cycle arrest, the fact that glioma cell lines show sensitivity to ZBC260. 
Notably, ZBC260 targeted glioma without side effects in vivo. In addition, the 
stem cell-like properties of glioma cells were inhibited upon ZBC260 treatment. 
When the mechanism was examined, our findings indicated that Wnt/β-catenin 
pathway repression is required for ZBC260-induced stem cell-like properties and 
tumor growth suppression. In conclusion, the growth of tumors and stem cell-like 
properties were inhibited by ZBC260 via Wnt/β-catenin repression, which suggests 
ZBC260 as a potential therapeutic agent for glioma.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="642~646" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="709~726" text="glioma cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="781~787" text="glioma" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="809~816" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="865~877" text="glioma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="647~660" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="676~693" text="cell cycle arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1074~1086" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1119~1135" text="growth of tumors" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="631~641" text="inhibiting" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="665~674" text="inducting" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1087~1098" text="suppression" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1172~1181" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>