<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Rosuvastatin protects against coronary microembolization-induced cardiac injury 
via inhibiting NLRP3 inflammasome activation.

Coronary microembolization (CME), a common reason for periprocedural myocardial 
infarction (PMI), bears very important prognostic implications. However, the 
molecular mechanisms related to CME remain largely elusive. Statins have been 
shown to prevent PMI, but the underlying mechanism has not been identified. 
Here, we examine whether the NLRP3 inflammasome contributes to CME-induced 
cardiac injury and investigate the effects of statin therapy on CME. In vivo 
study, mice with CME were treated with 40 mg/kg/d rosuvastatin (RVS) orally or a 
selective NLRP3 inflammasome inhibitor MCC950 intraperitoneally (20 mg/kg/d). 
Mice treated with MCC950 and RVS showed improved cardiac contractile function 
and morphological changes, diminished fibrosis and microinfarct size, and 
reduced serum lactate dehydrogenase (LDH) level. Mechanistically, RVS decreased 
the expression of NLRP3, caspase-1, interleukin-1β, and Gasdermin D N-terminal 
domains. Proteomics analysis revealed that RVS restored the energy metabolism 
and oxidative phosphorylation in CME. Furthermore, reduced reactive oxygen 
species (ROS) level and alleviated mitochondrial damage were observed in 
RVS-treated mice. In vitro study, RVS inhibited the activation of NLRP3 
inflammasome induced by tumor necrosis factor α plus hypoxia in H9c2 cells. 
Meanwhile, the pyroptosis was also suppressed by RVS, indicated by the increased 
cell viability, decreased LDH and propidium iodide uptake in H9c2 cells. RVS 
also reduced the level of mitochondrial ROS generation in vitro. Our results 
indicate the NLRP3 inflammasome-dependent cardiac pyroptosis plays an important 
role in CME-induced cardiac injury and its inhibitor exerts cardioprotective 
effect following CME. We also uncover the anti-pyroptosis role of RVS in CME, 
which is associated with regulating mitochondrial ROS.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="588~595" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="604~617" text="mice with CME" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="758~762" text="Mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1314~1318" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1320~1328" text="In vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1439~1449" text="H9c2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1595~1605" text="H9c2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1667~1675" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1467~1477" text="pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1534~1548" text="cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1487~1497" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1523~1532" text="increased" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>