<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Exosomal arrow (Arr)/lipoprotein receptor protein 6 (LRP6) in Drosophila 
melanogaster increases the extracellular level of Sol narae (Sona) in a 
Wnt-independent manner.

Wg/Wnt as a signaling protein binds to Frizzled (Fz) and Arrow (Arr), two Wg 
co-receptors essential for Wg signaling for cell proliferation, differentiation, 
and cell survival. Arr has a long extracellular region, a single transmembrane 
domain and an intracellular region. Here, we report that a new arrm7 mutant is 
identified in a genetic screen as a suppressor of lethality induced by 
overexpression of Sol narae (Sona), a secreted metalloprotease in ADAMTS family 
involved in Wg signaling. arrm7 allele has a premature stop codon, which encodes 
Arrm7 protein missing the intracellular region. arrm7 clones show cell death 
phenotype and overexpression of Arrm7 protein also induces cell death. Levels of 
extracellular Sona were decreased in both arrm7 and arr2 null clones, 
demonstrating that Arr increases the level of extracellular Sona. Indeed, Arr 
but not Arrm7, increased levels of Sona in cytoplasm and exosome fraction by 
inhibiting the lysosomal degradation pathway. Interestingly, Arr itself was 
identified in the exosome fraction, demonstrating that Arr is secreted to 
extracellular space. When Sona-expressing S2 cells were treated with exosomal 
Arr, the extracellular level of active Sona was increased. These results show 
that exosomal Arr dictates Sona-expressing cells to increase the level of 
extracellular Sona. This new function of Arr occurred in the absence of Wg 
because S2 cells do not express Wg. We propose that Arr plays two distinct 
roles, one as an exosomal protein to increase the level of extracellular Sona in 
a Wnt-independent manner and the other as a Wg co-receptor in a Wnt-dependent 
manner.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="564~598" text="overexpression of Sol narae (Sona)" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="819~850" text="overexpression of Arrm7 protein" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="929~948" text="arrm7 and arr2 null" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1293~1317" text="Sona-expressing S2 cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="864~874" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="856~863" text="induces" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>