<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Quantifying the efficacy of checkpoint inhibitors on CD8(+) cytotoxic T cells 
for immunotherapeutic applications via single-cell interaction.

The inhibition of the PD1/PDL1 pathway has led to remarkable clinical success 
for cancer treatment in some patients. Many, however, exhibit little to no 
response to this treatment. To increase the efficacy of PD1 inhibition, 
additional checkpoint inhibitors are being explored as combination therapy 
options. TSR-042 and TSR-033 are novel antibodies for the inhibition of the PD1 
and LAG3 pathways, respectively, and are intended for combination therapy. Here, 
we explore the effect on cellular interactions of TSR-042 and TSR-033 alone and 
in combination at the single-cell level. Utilizing our droplet microfluidic 
platform, we use time-lapse microscopy to observe the effects of these 
antibodies on calcium flux in CD8+ T cells upon antigen presentation, as well as 
their effect on the cytotoxic potential of CD8+ T cells on human breast cancer 
cells. This platform allowed us to investigate the interactions between these 
treatments and their impacts on T-cell activity in greater detail than 
previously applied in vitro tests. The novel parameters we were able to observe 
included effects on the exact time to target cell killing, contact times, and 
potential for serial-killing by CD8+ T cells. We found that inhibition of LAG3 
with TSR-033 resulted in a significant increase in calcium fluctuations of CD8+ 
T cells in contact with dendritic cells. We also found that the combination of 
TSR-042 and TSR-033 appears to synergistically increase tumor cell killing and 
the single-cell level. This study provides a novel single-cell-based assessment 
of the impact these checkpoint inhibitors have on cellular interactions with 
CD8+ T cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1374~1406" text="inhibition of LAG3  with TSR-033" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="871~883" text="CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="982~1008" text="human breast cancer  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="966~978" text="CD8+ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1469~1482" text="CD8+  T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1611~1621" text="tumor cell" context="transformed cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>