<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Enolase 1 regulates stem cell-like properties in gastric cancer cells by 
stimulating glycolysis.

Recent studies have demonstrated that gastric cancer stem cells (CSCs) are a 
rare sub-group of gastric cancer (GC) cells and have an important role in 
promoting the tumor growth and progression of GC. In the present study, we 
demonstrated that the glycolytic enzyme Enolase 1 (ENO1) was involved in the 
regulation of the stem cell-like characteristics of GC cells, as compared to the 
parental cell lines PAMC-82 and SNU16, the expression of ENO1 in spheroids 
markedly increased. We then observed that ENO1 could enhance stem cell-like 
characteristics, including self-renewal capacity, cell invasion and migration, 
chemoresistance, and even the tumorigenicity of GC cells. ENO1 is known as an 
enzyme that is involved in glycolysis, but our results showed that ENO1 could 
markedly promote the glycolytic activity of cells. Furthermore, inhibiting 
glycolysis activity using 2-deoxy-D-glucose treatment significantly reduced the 
stemness of GC cells. Therefore, ENO1 could improve the stemness of CSCs by 
enhancing the cells' glycolysis. Subsequently, to further confirm our results, 
we found that the inhibition of ENO1 using AP-III-a4 (ENOblock) could reduce the 
stemness of GC cells to a similar extent as the knockdown of ENO1 by shRNA. 
Finally, increased expression of ENO1 was related to poor prognosis in GC 
patients. Taken together, our results demonstrated that ENO1 is a significant 
biomarker associated with the stemness of GC cells.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1211~1256" text="inhibition of ENO1 using AP-III-a4 (ENOblock)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1323~1349" text="knockdown of ENO1 by shRNA" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="691~695" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="769~777" text="GC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="923~928" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1048~1056" text="GC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1104~1108" text="CSCs" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1127~1132" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1287~1295" text="GC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="668~689" text="self-renewal capacity" phenotype="self-renewal" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="696~704" text="invasion" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="709~718" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="751~765" text="tumorigenicity" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="617~624" text="enhance" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>