<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ClC-3/SGK1 regulatory axis enhances the olaparib-induced antitumor effect in 
human stomach adenocarcinoma.

Currently, only a few available targeted drugs are considered to be effective in 
stomach adenocarcinoma (STAD) treatment. The PARP inhibitor olaparib is a 
molecularly targeted drug that continues to be investigated in BRCA-mutated 
tumors. However, in tumors without BRCA gene mutations, particularly in STAD, 
the effect and molecular mechanism of olaparib are unclear, which largely 
restricts the use of olaparib in STAD treatment. In this study, the in vitro 
results showed that olaparib specifically inhibited cell growth and migration, 
exerting antitumor effect in STAD cell lines. In addition, a ClC-3/SGK1 
regulatory axis was identified and validated in STAD cells. We then found that 
the down-regulation of ClC-3/SGK1 axis attenuated olaparib-induced cell growth 
and migration inhibition. On the contrary, the up-regulation of ClC-3/SGK1 axis 
enhanced olaparib-induced cell growth and migration inhibition, and the 
enhancement effect could be attenuated by SGK1 knockdown. Consistently, the 
whole-cell recorded chloride current activated by olaparib presented the same 
variation trend. Next, the clinical data showed that ClC-3 and SGK1 were highly 
expressed in human STAD tissues and positively correlated (r = 0.276, 
P = 0.009). Furthermore, high protein expression of both ClC-3 (P = 0.030) and 
SGK1 (P = 0.006) was associated with poor survival rate in STAD patients, and 
positive correlations between ClC-3/SGK1 and their downstream molecules in STAD 
tissues were demonstrated via the GEPIA datasets. Finally, our results suggested 
that olaparib inhibited the PI3K/AKT pathway in STAD cells, and up-regulation of 
ClC-3/SGK1 axis enhanced olaparib-induced PI3K/AKT pathway inhibition. The 
animal experiments indicated that olaparib also exerted antitumor effect in 
vivo. Altogether, our findings illustrate that olaparib exerts antitumor effect 
in human STAD, and ClC-3/SGK1 regulatory axis enhances the olaparib-induced 
antitumor effect. Up-regulation of the ClC-3/SGK1 axis may provide promising 
therapeutic potential for the clinical application of olaparib in STAD 
treatment.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1084~1098" text="SGK1 knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="565~573" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="684~699" text="STAD cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1720~1730" text="STAD cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1903~1911" text="in  vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1830~1836" text="animal" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="627~638" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="643~652" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="875~886" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="892~901" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="995~1006" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1011~1020" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="617~626" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="847~857" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="867~874" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="902~912" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="969~977" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="987~994" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1021~1031" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>