<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Isobacachalcone induces autophagy and improves the outcome of immunogenic 
chemotherapy.

A number of natural plant products have a long-standing history in both 
traditional and modern medical applications. Some secondary metabolites induce 
autophagy and mediate autophagy-dependent healthspan- and lifespan-extending 
effects in suitable mouse models. Here, we identified isobacachalcone (ISO) as a 
non-toxic inducer of autophagic flux that acts on human and mouse cells in 
vitro, as well as mouse organs in vivo. Mechanistically, ISO inhibits AKT as 
well as, downstream of AKT, the mechanistic target of rapamycin complex 1 
(mTORC1), coupled to the activation of the pro-autophagic transcription factors 
EB (TFEB) and E3 (TFE3). Cells equipped with a constitutively active AKT mutant 
failed to activate autophagy. ISO also stimulated the AKT-repressible activation 
of all three arms of the unfolded stress response (UPR), including the 
PERK-dependent phosphorylation of eukaryotic initiation factor 2α (eIF2α). 
Knockout of TFEB and/or TFE3 blunted the UPR, while knockout of PERK or 
replacement of eIF2α by a non-phosphorylable mutant reduced TFEB/TFE3 activation 
and autophagy induced by ISO. This points to crosstalk between the UPR and 
autophagy. Of note, the administration of ISO to mice improved the efficacy of 
immunogenic anticancer chemotherapy. This effect relied on an improved T 
lymphocyte-dependent anticancer immune response and was lost upon constitutive 
AKT activation in, or deletion of the essential autophagy gene Atg5 from, the 
malignant cells. In conclusion, ISO is a bioavailable autophagy inducer that 
warrants further preclinical characterization.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1024~1052" text="Knockout of TFEB and/or TFE3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1076~1092" text="knockout of PERK" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1475~1503" text="constitutive  AKT activation" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1511~1556" text="deletion of the essential autophagy gene Atg5" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1097~1148" text="replacement of eIF2α by a non-phosphorylable mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="453~474" text="human and mouse cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="475~484" text="in  vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="497~509" text="mouse organs" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="510~517" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="738~743" text="Cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1568~1583" text="malignant cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="813~822" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1183~1192" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="794~812" text="failed to activate" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1149~1156" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1193~1200" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>