<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DEPDC1B is a tumor promotor in development of bladder cancer through targeting 
SHC1.

Bladder cancer is one of the most commonly diagnosed malignant tumors in the 
urinary system and causes a massive cancer-related death. DEPDC1B is a DEP 
domain-containing protein that has been found to be associated with a variety of 
human cancers. This study aimed to explore the role and mechanism of DEPDC1B in 
the development of bladder cancer. The analysis of clinical specimens revealed 
the upregulated expression of DEPDC1B in bladder cancer, which was positively 
related to tumor grade. In vitro and in vivo studies showed that DEPDC1B 
knockdown could inhibit the growth of bladder cancer cells or xenografts in 
mice. The suppression of bladder cancer by DEPDC1B was executed through 
inhibiting cell proliferation, cell migration, and promoting cell apoptosis. 
Moreover, a mechanistic study found that SHC1 may be an important route through 
which DEPDC1B regulates the development of bladder cancer. Knockdown of SHC1 in 
DEPDC1B-overexpressed cancer cells could abolish the promotion effects induced 
by DEPDC1B. In conclusion, DEPDC1B was identified as a key regulator in the 
development of bladder cancer, which may be used as a potential therapeutic 
target in the treatment of bladder cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="628~646" text="DEPDC1B  knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1005~1022" text="Knockdown of SHC1" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1027~1048" text="DEPDC1B-overexpressed" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="587~595" text="In vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="600~607" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="675~695" text="bladder cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="699~709" text="xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="714~718" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="798~802" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="818~822" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="848~852" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1049~1061" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="803~816" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="823~832" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="853~862" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="787~797" text="inhibiting" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="838~847" text="promoting" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>