<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Macrophages target Salmonella by Lc3-associated phagocytosis in a systemic 
infection model.

Innate immune defense against intracellular pathogens, like Salmonella, relies 
heavily on the autophagy machinery of the host. This response is studied 
intensively in epithelial cells, the target of Salmonella during 
gastrointestinal infections. However, little is known of the role that autophagy 
plays in macrophages, the predominant carriers of this pathogen during systemic 
disease. Here we utilize a zebrafish embryo model to study the interaction of S. 
enterica serovar Typhimurium with the macroautophagy/autophagy machinery of 
macrophages in vivo. We show that phagocytosis of live but not heat-killed 
Salmonella triggers recruitment of the autophagy marker GFP-Lc3 in a variety of 
patterns labeling tight or spacious bacteria-containing compartments, also 
revealed by electron microscopy. Neutrophils display similar GFP-Lc3 
associations, but genetic modulation of the neutrophil/macrophage balance and 
ablation experiments show that macrophages are critical for the defense 
response. Deficiency of atg5 reduces GFP-Lc3 recruitment and impairs host 
resistance, in contrast to atg13 deficiency, indicating that Lc3-Salmonella 
association at this stage is independent of the autophagy preinitiation complex 
and that macrophages target Salmonella by Lc3-associated phagocytosis (LAP). In 
agreement, GFP-Lc3 recruitment and host resistance are impaired by deficiency of 
Rubcn/Rubicon, known as a negative regulator of canonical autophagy and an 
inducer of LAP. We also found strict dependency on NADPH oxidase, another 
essential factor for LAP. Both Rubcn and NADPH oxidase are required to activate 
a Salmonella biosensor for reactive oxygen species inside infected macrophages. 
These results identify LAP as the major host protective autophagy-related 
pathway responsible for macrophage defense against Salmonella during systemic 
infection.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1101~1119" text="Deficiency of atg5" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1193~1209" text="atg13 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1472~1500" text="deficiency of  Rubcn/Rubicon" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="504~526" text="zebrafish embryo model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="636~647" text="macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="648~655" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>