<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[
Long noncoding RNA LINC00336 inhibits ferroptosis in lung cancer by functioning 
as a competing endogenous RNA.

The regulatory loop between long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) and microRNAs has a 
dynamic role in transcriptional and translational regulation, and is involved in 
cancer. However, the regulatory circuitry between lncRNAs and microRNAs in 
tumorigenesis remains elusive. Here we demonstrate that a nuclear lncRNA 
LINC00336 is upregulated in lung cancer and functions as an oncogene by acting 
as a competing endogenous RNA (ceRNAs). LINC00336 bound RNA-binding protein 
ELAVL1 (ELAV-like RNA-binding protein 1) using nucleotides 1901-2107 of 
LINC00336 and the RRM interaction domain and key amino acids (aa) of ELAVL1 (aa 
101-213), inhibiting ferroptosis. Moreover, ELAVL1 increased LINC00336 
expression by stabilizing its posttranscriptional level, whereas LSH 
(lymphoid-specific helicase) increased ELAVL1 expression through the p53 
signaling pathway, further supporting the hypothesis that LSH promotes LINC00336 
expression. Interestingly, LINC00336 served as an endogenous sponge of microRNA 
6852 (MIR6852) to regulate the expression of cystathionine-β-synthase (CBS), a 
surrogate marker of ferroptosis. Finally, we found that MIR6852 inhibited cell 
growth by promoting ferroptosis. These data show that the network of lncRNA and 
ceRNA has an important role in tumorigenesis and ferroptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="757~768" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1269~1281" text="cell  growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1295~1306" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="746~756" text="inhibiting" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1259~1268" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1285~1294" text="promoting" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>