<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Inhibition of EZH2 induces NK cell-mediated differentiation and death 
in muscle-invasive bladder cancer.

Lysine-specific demethylase 6A (KDM6A) and members of the Switch/Sucrose 
Non-Fermentable (SWI/SNF) family are known to counteract the activity of 
Enhancer of Zeste Homolog 2 (EZH2), which is often overexpressed and is 
associated with poor prognosis in muscle-invasive bladder cancer. Here we 
provide evidence that alterations in chromatin modifying enzymes, including 
KDM6A and members of the SWI/SNF complex, are frequent in muscle-invasive 
bladder cancer. We exploit the loss of function mutations in KDM6A and SWI/SNF 
complex to make bladder cancer cells susceptible to EZH2-based epigenetic 
therapy that activates an immune response to drive tumor cell differentiation 
and death. We reveal a novel mechanism of action of EZH2 inhibition, alone and 
in combination with cisplatin, which induces immune signaling with the largest 
changes observed in interferon gamma (IFN-γ). This upregulation is a result of 
activated natural killer (NK) signaling as demonstrated by the increase in NK 
cell-associated genes MIP-1α, ICAM1, ICAM2, and CD86 in xenografts treated with 
EZH2 inhibitors. Conversely, EZH2 inhibition results in decreased expression of 
pluripotency markers, ALDH2 and CK5, and increased cell death. Our results 
reveal a novel sensitivity of muscle-invasive bladder cancer cells with KMD6A 
and SWI/SNF mutations to EZH2 inhibition alone and in combination with 
cisplatin. This sensitivity is mediated through increased NK cell-related 
signaling resulting in tumor cell differentiation and cell death.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="841~856" text="EZH2 inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1189~1204" text="EZH2 inhibitors" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1218~1233" text="EZH2 inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="586~621" text="loss of function mutations in KDM6A" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="651~671" text="bladder cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="761~771" text="tumor cell" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1164~1174" text="xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="772~787" text="differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1321~1331" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="755~760" text="drive" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1311~1320" text="increased" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>