<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Dynamic PGAM5 multimers dephosphorylate BCL-xL or FUNDC1 to regulate 
mitochondrial and cellular fate.

Mitochondria are highly dynamic organelles and respond to stress by changing 
their fission-fusion cycle, undergoing mitophagy, or releasing apoptotic 
proteins to initiate cell death. The molecular mechanisms that sense different 
stresses and coordinate distinct effectors still await full characterization. 
Here, we show that PGAM5, which exists in an equilibrium between dimeric and 
multimeric states, dephosphorylates BCL-xL to inhibit apoptosis or FUNDC1 to 
activate mitofission and mitophagy in response to distinct stresses. In 
vinblastine-treated cells, PGAM5 dephosphorylates BCL-xL at Ser62 to restore 
BCL-xL sequestration of BAX and BAK and thereby resistance to apoptosis. 
Selenite-induced oxidative stress increases the multimerization of PGAM5, 
resulting in its dissociation from BCL-xL, which causes increased BCL-xL 
phosphorylation and apoptosis. Once freed, the more multimeric and active PGAM5 
dephosphorylates FUNDC1 to initiate mitofission and mitophagy. The reciprocal 
interaction of PGAM5 with FUNDC1 and BCL-xL, controlled by PGAM5 
multimerization, serves as a molecular switch between mitofission/mitophagy and 
apoptosis.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="664~669" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="547~556" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="596~605" text="mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="784~793" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="965~974" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1078~1087" text="mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="539~546" text="inhibit" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="571~579" text="activate" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="770~780" text="resistance" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="920~926" text="causes" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1053~1061" text="initiate" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>