<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Exosomal miRNA-19b-3p of tubular epithelial cells promotes M1 macrophage 
activation in kidney injury.

Tubulointerstitial inflammation is a common characteristic of acute and chronic 
kidney injury. However, the mechanism by which the initial injury of tubular 
epithelial cells (TECs) drives interstitial inflammation remains unclear. This 
paper aims to explore the role of exosomal miRNAs derived from TECs in the 
development of tubulointerstitial inflammation. Global microRNA(miRNA) 
expression profiling of renal exosomes was examined in a LPS induced acute 
kidney injury (AKI) mouse model and miR-19b-3p was identified as the miRNA that 
was most notably increased in TEC-derived exosomes compared to controls. Similar 
results were also found in an adriamycin (ADR) induced chronic proteinuric 
kidney disease model in which exosomal miR-19b-3p was markedly released. 
Interestingly, once released, TEC-derived exosomal miR-19b-3p was internalized 
by macrophages, leading to M1 phenotype polarization through targeting 
NF-κB/SOCS-1. A dual-luciferase reporter assay confirmed that SOCS-1 was the 
direct target of miR-19b-3p. Importantly, the pathogenic role of exosomal 
miR-19b-3p in initiating renal inflammation was revealed by the ability of 
adoptively transferred of purified TEC-derived exosomes to cause 
tubulointerstitial inflammation in mice, which was reversed by inhibition of 
miR-19b-3p. Clinically, high levels of miR-19b-3p were found in urinary exosomes 
and were correlated with the severity of tubulointerstitial inflammation in 
patients with diabetic nephropathy. Thus, our studies demonstrated that exosomal 
miR-19b-3p mediated the communication between injured TECs and macrophages, 
leading to M1 macrophage activation. The exosome/miR-19b-3p/SOCS1 axis played a 
critical pathologic role in tubulointerstitial inflammation, representing a new 
therapeutic target for kidney disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1390~1415" text="inhibition of  miR-19b-3p" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="587~598" text="mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="567~573" text="kidney" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="806~812" text="kidney" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1362~1366" text="mice" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>