<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SIGMAR1/Sigma-1 receptor ablation impairs autophagosome clearance.

Autophagosome-lysosome fusion is a common critical step in various forms of 
macroautophagy/autophagy including mitophagy, the selective degradation of 
mitochondria. Regulations of this fusion process remain poorly defined. Here we 
have determined the role of SIGMAR1, a unique endoplasmic reticulum membrane 
protein. Knockout of Sigmar1 impaired mitochondrial clearance without altering 
the PINK1-PRKN/Parkin signaling, in mouse retinal explants and cultured cells 
treated with carbonyl cyanide m-chlorophenyl hydrazone (CCCP) for induction of 
mitophagy. SIGMAR1 depletion also caused accumulation of autophagosome markers 
LC3-II and SQSTM1, but did not change the levels of BECN1 and ATG7, proteins 
associated with autophagosome biogenesis. Lysosomal pH and protease activities 
were not negatively affected. However, sigmar1 knockout partially compromised 
autophagosome-lysosome fusion in CCCP-treated NSC34 cells, as revealed by 
reduced GFP fluorescence quenching of GFP-RFP-LC3-II puncta and co-localization 
of lysosomes with mitochondria. Furthermore, SIGMAR1 co-immunoprecipitated with 
ATG14, STX17, and VAMP8 (but not SNAP29), proteins key to autophagosome-lysosome 
membrane fusion. Re-expressing SIGMAR1 in the null background rescued clearance 
of mitochondria and autophagosomes. In summary, we started out finding that 
sigmar1 knockout impaired the clearance of mitochondria and autophagosomes, and 
then narrowed down the SIGMAR1 modulation to the autophagosome-lysosome fusion 
step. This study may shed new light on understanding autophagy-associated 
cyto-protection and disease mechanisms.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="389~408" text="Knockout of Sigmar1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="630~647" text="SIGMAR1 depletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="896~912" text="sigmar1 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1272~1293" text="Re-expressing SIGMAR1" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1413~1429" text="sigmar1 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="496~518" text="mouse retinal explants" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="523~537" text="cultured cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="982~993" text="NSC34 cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="619~628" text="mitophagy" phenotype="mitophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="605~614" text="induction" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>