<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The deubiquitinase USP10 regulates KLF4 stability and suppresses lung 
tumorigenesis.

Krüppel-like factor 4 (KLF4), a key transcription factor, acts as a 
multifunctional player involved in the progression of numerous aggressive 
cancers. The proteasome-dependent pathway is one of the main modalities in 
controlling KLF4 abundance at a posttranslational level. Although some of the 
ubiquitin ligases have been identified, the deubiquitinases of KLF4 and the 
regulatory function remain unexplored. Here, by screening ubiquitin-specific 
proteases that may interact with KLF4, we found ubiquitin-specific peptidase 10 
(USP10) as a deubiquitinating enzyme for KLF4. Forced expression of USP10 
remarkably increases KLF4 protein level by blocking the latter degradation, 
whereas the depletion of USP10 promotes KLF4 degradation and thus enhances 
tumorigenesis. Loss of USP10 in mice downregulates KLF4 expression and 
accelerates KrasG12D-driven lung adenocarcinoma initiation and progression. In 
addition, our data revealed that KLF4 can facilitate the transcription of tumor 
suppressor TIMP3 by directly binding to the TIMP3 promoter. Clinically, 
reduction of USP10 expression, concomitant with decreased KLF4 and TIMP3 
abundance in carcinoma tissue, predicts poor prognosis of lung cancer patient. 
Taken together, our results demonstrate that USP10 is a critical regulator of 
KLF4, pinpointing USP10-KLF4-TIMP3 axis as a promising therapeutic target in 
lung cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="669~695" text="Forced expression of USP10" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="786~804" text="depletion of USP10" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="865~878" text="Loss of USP10" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="934~949" text="KrasG12D-driven" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="882~886" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="950~969" text="lung adenocarcinoma" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="850~863" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="840~848" text="enhances" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>