<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Prohibitin levels regulate OMA1 activity and turnover in neurons.

The GTPase OPA1 and the AAA-protease OMA1 serve well-established roles in 
mitochondrial stress responses and mitochondria-initiated cell death. In 
addition to its role in mitochondrial membrane fusion, cristae structure, and 
bioenergetic function, OPA1 controls apoptosis by sequestering cytochrome c (cyt 
c) in mitochondrial cristae. Cleavage of functional long OPA1 (L-OPA1) isoforms 
by OMA1 inactivates mitochondrial fusion and primes apoptosis. OPA1 cleavage is 
regulated by the prohibitin (PHB) complex, a heteromeric, ring-shaped 
mitochondrial inner membrane scaffolding complex composed of PHB1 and PHB2. In 
neurons, PHB plays a protective role against various stresses, and PHB deletion 
destabilizes OPA1 causing neurodegeneration. While deletion of OMA1 prevents 
OPA1 destabilization and attenuates neurodegeneration in PHB2 KO mice, how PHB 
levels regulate OMA1 is still unknown. Here, we investigate the effects of 
modulating neuronal PHB levels on OMA1 stability and OPA1 cleavage. We 
demonstrate that PHB promotes OMA1 turnover, effectively decreasing the pool of 
OMA1. Further, we show that OMA1 binds to cardiolipin (CL), a major 
mitochondrial phospholipid. CL binding promotes OMA1 turnover, as we show that 
deleting the CL-binding domain of OMA1 decreases its turnover rate. Since PHB is 
known to stabilize CL, these data suggest that PHB modulates OMA1 through CL. 
Furthermore, we show that PHB decreases cyt c release induced by tBID and 
attenuates caspase 9 activation in response to hypoxic stress in neurons. Taken 
together, our results suggest that PHB-mediated CL stabilization regulates 
stress responses and cell death through OMA1 turnover and cyt c release.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1307~1345" text="deleting the CL-binding domain of OMA1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1608~1615" text="neurons" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>