<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MPTP-driven NLRP3 inflammasome activation in microglia plays a central role in 
dopaminergic neurodegeneration.

Parkinson's disease (PD) is a progressive neurodegenerative disease 
characterized by the loss of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra (SN) 
and the reduction of dopamine levels in the striatum. Although details of the 
molecular mechanisms underlying dopaminergic neuronal death in PD remain 
unclear, neuroinflammation is also considered a potent mediator in the 
pathogenesis and progression of PD. In the present study, we present evidences 
that microglial NLRP3 inflammasome activation is critical for dopaminergic 
neuronal loss and the subsequent motor deficits in the 
1-methyl-4-phenyl-1,2,3,6-tetrahydropyridine (MPTP) mouse model of PD. 
Specifically, NLRP3 deficiency significantly reduces motor dysfunctions and 
dopaminergic neurodegeneration of MPTP-treated mice. Furthermore, NLRP3 
deficiency abolishes MPTP-induced microglial recruitment, interleukin-1β 
production and caspase-1 activation in the SN of mouse brain. In primary 
microglia and mixed glial cell cultures, MPTP/ATP treatment promotes the robust 
assembly and activation of the NLRP3 inflammasome via producing mitochondrial 
reactive oxygen species. Consistently, 1-methyl-4-phenyl-pyridinium (MPP+) 
induces NLRP3 inflammasome activation in the presence of ATP or nigericin 
treatment in mouse bone-marrow-derived macrophages. These findings reveal a 
novel priming role of neurotoxin MPTP or MPP+ for NLRP3 activation. 
Subsequently, NLRP3 inflammasome-active microglia induces profound neuronal 
death in a microglia-neuron co-culture model. Furthermore, Cx3Cr1CreER-based 
microglia-specific expression of an active NLRP3 mutant greatly exacerbates 
motor deficits and dopaminergic neuronal loss of MPTP-treated mice. Taken 
together, our results indicate that microglial NLRP3 inflammasome activation 
plays a pivotal role in the MPTP-induced neurodegeneration in PD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="785~801" text="NLRP3 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="914~931" text="NLRP3  deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1662~1736" text="Cx3Cr1CreER-based  microglia-specific expression of an active NLRP3 mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="895~899" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1038~1055" text="SN of mouse brain" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1060~1078" text="primary  microglia" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1083~1108" text="mixed glial cell cultures" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1393~1430" text="mouse bone-marrow-derived macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1614~1647" text="microglia-neuron co-culture model" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1820~1824" text="mice" context="organism" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>