<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The circular RNA ACR attenuates myocardial ischemia/reperfusion injury by 
suppressing autophagy via modulation of the Pink1/ FAM65B pathway.

Dysregulated autophagy is associated with many pathological disorders such as 
cardiovascular diseases. Emerging evidence has suggested that circular RNAs 
(circRNAs) have important roles in some biological processes. However, it 
remains unclear whether circRNAs participate in the regulation of autophagy. 
Here we report that a circRNA, termed autophagy-related circular RNA (ACR), 
represses autophagy and myocardial infarction by targeting Pink1-mediated 
phosphorylation of FAM65B. ACR attenuates autophagy and cell death in 
cardiomyocytes. Moreover, ACR protects the heart from ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) 
injury and reduces myocardial infarct sizes. We identify Pink1 as an ACR target 
to mediate the function of ACR in cardiomyocyte autophagy. ACR activates Pink1 
expression through directly binding to Dnmt3B and blocking Dnmt3B-mediated DNA 
methylation of Pink1 promoter. Pink1 suppresses autophagy and Pink1 transgenic 
mice show reduced myocardial infarction sizes. Further, we find that FAM65B is a 
downstream target of Pink1 and Pink1 phosphorylates FAM65B at serine 46. 
Phosphorylated FAM65B inhibits autophagy and cell death in the heart. Our 
findings reveal a novel role for the circRNA in regulating autophagy and 
ACR-Pink1-FAM65B axis as a regulator of autophagy in the heart will be potential 
therapeutic targets in treatment of cardiovascular diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1060~1076" text="Pink1 transgenic" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1078~1082" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1297~1302" text="heart" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="675~689" text="cardiomyocytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="539~548" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="646~655" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="660~670" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1265~1274" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1279~1289" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="529~538" text="represses" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="635~645" text="attenuates" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1256~1264" text="inhibits" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>