<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The necroptosis machinery mediates axonal degeneration in a model of Parkinson 
disease.

Parkinson's disease (PD) is the second most common neurodegenerative condition, 
characterized by motor impairment due to the progressive degeneration of 
dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra and depletion of dopamine release 
in the striatum. Accumulating evidence suggest that degeneration of axons is an 
early event in the disease, involving destruction programs that are independent 
of the survival of the cell soma. Necroptosis, a programmed cell death process, 
is emerging as a mediator of neuronal loss in models of neurodegenerative 
diseases. Here, we demonstrate activation of necroptosis in postmortem brain 
tissue from PD patients and in a toxin-based mouse model of the disease. 
Inhibition of key components of the necroptotic pathway resulted in a 
significant delay of 6-hydroxydopamine-dependent axonal degeneration of 
dopaminergic and cortical neurons in vitro. Genetic ablation of necroptosis 
mediators MLKL and RIPK3, as well as pharmacological inhibition of RIPK1 in 
preclinical models of PD, decreased dopaminergic neuron degeneration, improving 
motor performance. Together, these findings suggest that axonal degeneration in 
PD is mediated by the necroptosis machinery, a process here referred to as 
necroaxoptosis, a druggable pathway to target dopaminergic neuronal loss.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="983~1040" text="Genetic ablation of necroptosis  mediators MLKL and RIPK3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1053~1088" text="pharmacological inhibition of RIPK1" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="766~777" text="mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="939~972" text="dopaminergic and cortical neurons" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="973~981" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1129~1148" text="dopaminergic neuron" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="688~699" text="necroptosis" phenotype="necroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="674~684" text="activation" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>