<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[The role of the LncRNA-FA2H-2-MLKL pathway in atherosclerosis by regulation of 
autophagy flux and inflammation through mTOR-dependent signaling.

Atherosclerosis is a progressive, chronic inflammation in arterial walls. Long 
noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) participate in inflammation, but the exact mechanism in 
atherosclerosis is unclear. Our microarray analyses revealed that the levels of 
lncRNA-FA2H-2 were significantly decreased by oxidized low-density lipoprotein 
(OX-LDL). Bioinformatics analyses indicated that mixed lineage kinase 
domain-like protein (MLKL) might be regulated by lncRNA-FA2H-2. In vitro 
experiments showed that lncRNA-FA2H-2 interacted with the promoter of the MLKL 
gene, downregulated MLKL expression, and the binding sites between -750 and 471 
were necessary for lncRNA-FA2H-2 responsiveness to MLKL. Silencing lncRNA-FA2H-2 
and overexpression of MLKL could activate inflammation and inhibited autophagy 
flux. Both lncRNA-FA2H-2 knockdown and overexpression of MLKL could 
significantly aggravate inflammatory responses induced by OX-LDL. We found that 
the 3-methyladenine (3-MA) and Atg7-shRNA enhanced inflammatory responses 
induced by knockdown of lncRNA-FA2H-2 and overexpression of MLKL. We 
demonstrated that the effects of MLKL on autophagy might be associated with a 
mechanistic target of rapamycin (mTOR)-dependent signaling pathways. In vivo 
experiments with apoE knockout mice fed a western diet demonstrated that 
LncRNA-FA2H-2 knockdown decreased microtubule-associated expression of 
microtubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3 II and lysosome-associated 
membrane protein 1, but increased expression of sequestosome 1 (p62), MLKL, 
vascular cell adhesion molecule-1, monocyte chemoattractant protein-1, and 
interleukin-6 in atherosclerotic lesions. Our findings indicated that the 
lncRNA-FA2H-2-MLKL pathway is essential for regulation of autophagy and 
inflammation, and suggested that lncRNA-FA2H-2 and MLKL could act as potential 
therapeutic targets to ameliorate atherosclerosis-related diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="833~856" text="Silencing lncRNA-FA2H-2" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="862~884" text="overexpression of MLKL" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="949~972" text="lncRNA-FA2H-2 knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="977~999" text="overexpression of MLKL" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1119~1129" text="Atg7-shRNA" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1174~1200" text="knockdown of lncRNA-FA2H-2" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1205~1227" text="overexpression of MLKL" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P8" spans="1407~1420" text="apoE knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P9" spans="1464~1487" text="LncRNA-FA2H-2 knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="605~613" text="In vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1381~1388" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1421~1425" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="927~942" text="autophagy  flux" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="917~926" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>