<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Deep profiling of apoptotic pathways with mass cytometry identifies a 
synergistic drug combination for killing myeloma cells.

Multiple myeloma is an incurable and fatal cancer of immunoglobulin-secreting 
plasma cells. Most conventional therapies aim to induce apoptosis in myeloma 
cells but resistance to these drugs often arises and drives relapse. In this 
study, we sought to identify the best adjunct targets to kill myeloma cells 
resistant to conventional therapies using deep profiling by mass cytometry 
(CyTOF). We validated probes to simultaneously detect 26 regulators of cell 
death, mitosis, cell signaling, and cancer-related pathways at the single-cell 
level following treatment of myeloma cells with dexamethasone or bortezomib. 
Time-resolved visualization algorithms and machine learning random forest models 
(RFMs) delineated putative cell death trajectories and a hierarchy of parameters 
that specified myeloma cell survival versus apoptosis following treatment. Among 
these parameters, increased amounts of phosphorylated cAMP response 
element-binding protein (CREB) and the pro-survival protein, MCL-1, were 
defining features of cells surviving drug treatment. Importantly, the RFM 
prediction that the combination of an MCL-1 inhibitor with dexamethasone would 
elicit potent, synergistic killing of myeloma cells was validated in other cell 
lines, in vivo preclinical models and primary myeloma samples from patients. 
Furthermore, CyTOF analysis of patient bone marrow cells clearly identified 
myeloma cells and their key cell survival features. This study demonstrates the 
utility of CyTOF profiling at the single-cell level to identify clinically 
relevant drug combinations and tracking of patient responses for future clinical 
trials.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1253~1268" text="MCL-1 inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="702~715" text="myeloma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1161~1166" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1370~1381" text="cell  lines" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1383~1409" text="in vivo preclinical models" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1414~1451" text="primary myeloma samples from patients" context="transformed cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>