<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RIPK3 collaborates with GSDMD to drive tissue injury in lethal polymicrobial 
sepsis.

Sepsis is a systemic inflammatory disease causing life-threatening multi-organ 
dysfunction. Accumulating evidences suggest that two forms of programmed 
necrosis, necroptosis and pyroptosis triggered by the pathogen component 
lipopolysaccharide (LPS) and inflammatory cytokines, play important roles in the 
development of bacterial sepsis-induced shock and tissue injury. Sepsis-induced 
shock and tissue injury required receptor-interacting protein kinase-3 (RIPK3) 
and mixed lineage kinase domain-like protein (MLKL) phosphorylation, caspase11 
activation and gasdermin D (GSDMD) cleavage. However, the synergistic effect of 
necroptosis and pyroptosis in the pathological progress of sepsis remains 
elusive. In this study, we found that blockage of both necroptosis and 
pyroptosis (double deletion of Ripk3/Gsdmd or Mlkl/Gsdmd) resulted in 
accumulative protection against septic shock, systemic blood clotting and 
multi-organ injury in mice. Bone marrow transplantation confirmed that 
necroptosis and pyroptosis in both myeloid and nonmyeloid cells are 
indispensable in the progression of sepsis-induced multi-organ injury. Both 
RIPK3 and GSDMD signaling collaborated to amplify necroinflammation and tissue 
factor release in macrophages and endothelial cells, which led to tissue injury. 
Furthermore, cell death induced by inflammatory cytokines and high-mobility 
group box 1 could be prevented by double ablation of Ripk3/Gsdmd or Mlkl/Gsdmd, 
suggesting that a positive feedback loop interconnecting RIPK3/MLKL and GSDMD 
machinery and inflammation facilitated sepsis progression. Collectively, our 
findings demonstrated that RIPK3-mediated necroptosis and GSDMD-mediated 
pyroptosis collaborated to amply inflammatory signaling and enhance tissue 
injury in the process of sepsis, which may shed new light on two potential 
targets of combined therapeutic interventions for this highly lethal disorder.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="878~922" text="double deletion of Ripk3/Gsdmd or Mlkl/Gsdmd" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1503~1547" text="double ablation of Ripk3/Gsdmd or Mlkl/Gsdmd" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1034~1038" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1119~1147" text="myeloid and nonmyeloid cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1328~1339" text="macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1344~1361" text="endothelial cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1405~1415" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1490~1499" text="prevented" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>