<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Dysregulation of autophagy and stress granule-related proteins in stress-driven 
Tau pathology.

Imbalance of neuronal proteostasis associated with misfolding and aggregation of 
Tau protein is a common neurodegenerative feature in Alzheimer's disease (AD) 
and other Tauopathies. Consistent with suggestions that lifetime stress may be 
an important AD precipitating factor, we previously reported that environmental 
stress and high glucocorticoid (GC) levels induce accumulation of aggregated 
Tau; however, the molecular mechanisms for such process remain unclear. Herein, 
we monitor a novel interplay between RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) and autophagic 
machinery in the underlying mechanisms through which chronic stress and high GC 
levels impact on Tau proteostasis precipitating Tau aggregation. Using 
molecular, pharmacological and behavioral analysis, we demonstrate that chronic 
stress and high GC trigger mTOR-dependent inhibition of autophagy, leading to 
accumulation of Tau aggregates and cell death in P301L-Tau expressing mice and 
cells. In parallel, we found that environmental stress and GC disturb cellular 
homeostasis and trigger the insoluble accumulation of different RBPs, such as 
PABP, G3BP1, TIA-1, and FUS, shown to form stress granules (SGs) and Tau 
aggregation. Interestingly, an mTOR-driven pharmacological stimulation of 
autophagy attenuates the GC-driven accumulation of Tau and SG-related proteins 
as well as the related cell death, suggesting a critical interface between 
autophagy and the response of the SG-related protein in the neurodegenerative 
potential of chronic stress and GC. These studies provide novel insights into 
the RNA-protein intracellular signaling regulating the precipitating role of 
environmental stress and GC on Tau-driven brain pathology.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1042~1046" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1052~1057" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="949~958" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1007~1017" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1360~1369" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1463~1473" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="912~919" text="trigger" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="935~945" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="960~970" text="leading to" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1344~1355" text="stimulation" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1370~1380" text="attenuates" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>