<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Impact of elevated anti-apoptotic MCL-1 and BCL-2 on the development and 
treatment of MLL-AF9 AML in mice.

Many acute myeloid leukaemias (AMLs) express high levels of BCL-2 and MCL-1, 
especially after therapy. To test the impact of these anti-apoptotic proteins on 
AML development and treatment, we used haemopoietic reconstitution to generate 
MLL-AF9 AMLs expressing BCL-2 or Mcl-1 transgenes. AMLs with elevated BCL-2 or 
MCL-1 had a higher proportion of mature myeloid cells but, like conventional 
MLL-AF9 AMLs, were readily transplantable. Short-term cell lines established 
from multiple primary AMLs of each genotype were tested in vitro for 
susceptibility to chemotherapeutics currently used for treating AML 
(daunorubicin, etoposide, cytarabine); the proteasome inhibitor bortezomib; 
CDK7/9 inhibitors; and BH3 mimetics, which bind and inhibit pro-survival 
proteins. The BH3 mimetics tested, alone and in combination with the other 
drugs, were: ABT-737 which, like its clinical counterpart navitoclax, targets 
BCL-2, BCL-XL and BCL-W; BCL-2-specific ABT-199 (venetoclax); BCL-XL-specific 
A-1331852; and S63845, a new MCL-1-specific BH3 mimetic. As single agents, 
daunorubicin and bortezomib had the greatest efficacy. Elevated MCL-1 or BCL-2 
reduced sensitivity to daunorubicin but, surprisingly, not to bortezomib. MCL-1 
markedly enhanced resistance to ABT-737 and ABT-199 but not S63845, and BCL-2 
increased resistance to S63845 but not to ABT-737 or ABT-199. Notable synergies 
were achieved by combining BH3 mimetics with daunorubicin: S63845 increased the 
sensitivity of both MCL-1 and BCL-2 overexpressing MLL-AF9 AMLs, and ABT-737 
aided in killing those overexpressing BCL-2. Synergy between daunorubicin and 
ABT-199 was also apparent in vivo, although not curative. Impressive synergistic 
responses were achieved for human MLL-fusion AML cell lines treated with 
daunorubicin plus either ABT-737, ABT-199 or S63845, and with ABT-199 plus 
S63845, with or without daunorubicin. Our data suggest that AML patients may 
benefit from combining conventional cytotoxic drugs with BH3 mimetics targeting 
BCL-2 or MCL-1 or, if tolerated, both these agents.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="550~628" text="Short-term cell lines established  from multiple primary AMLs of each genotype" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="641~649" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1770~1777" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1854~1885" text="human MLL-fusion AML cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>