<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Splicing factor derived circular RNA circUHRF1 accelerates oral squamous cell 
carcinoma tumorigenesis via feedback loop.

Emerging evidences have suggested the vital roles of circular RNA (circRNA) in 
the human cancers. However, the underlying biological functions and biogenesis 
of circRNA in the oral squamous cell carcinoma (OSCC) is still ambiguous. Here, 
we investigate the oncogenic roles and biogenesis of the novel identified 
circRNA, circUHRF1 (hsa_circ_0002185), in the OSCC tumorigenesis. Results showed 
that circUHRF1 was markedly upregulated in the OSCC cells and tissue, besides, 
the overexpression was closely correlated with the poor prognosis of OSCC 
patients. Functionally, circUHRF1 promoted the proliferation, migration, 
invasion, and epithelial mesenchymal transformation (EMT) in vitro and the tumor 
growth in vivo. Mechanically, circUHRF1 acted as the sponge of miR-526b-5p, 
thereby positively regulating c-Myc. Transcription factor c-Myc could accelerate 
the transcription of TGF-β1 and ESRP1. Moreover, splicing factor ESRP1 promoted 
the circularization and biogenesis of circUHRF1 by targeting the flanking 
introns, forming the circUHRF1/miR-526b-5p/c-Myc/TGF-β1/ESRP1 feedback loop. In 
conclusion, our research identified the oncogenic roles of circUHRF1 in the OSCC 
tumorigenesis and EMT via circUHRF1/miR-526b-5p/c-Myc/TGF-β1/ESRP1 feedback 
loop, shedding light on the pathogenic mechanism of circUHRF1 for OSCC and 
providing the potential therapeutic target.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="808~816" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="839~846" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="723~736" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="738~747" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="750~758" text="invasion" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="764~807" text="epithelial mesenchymal transformation (EMT)" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="825~838" text="tumor  growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="710~718" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>