<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TP53 gain-of-function mutation promotes inflammation in glioblastoma.

Glioblastoma (GBM), the most severe and common brain tumor in adults, is 
characterized by multiple somatic mutations and aberrant activation of 
inflammatory responses. Immune cell infiltration and subsequent inflammation 
cause tumor growth and resistance to therapy. Somatic loss-of-function mutations 
in the gene encoding tumor suppressor protein p53 (TP53) are frequently observed 
in various cancers. However, numerous studies suggest that TP53 regulates 
malignant phenotypes by gain-of-function (GOF) mutations. Here we demonstrate 
that a TP53 GOF mutation promotes inflammation in GBM. Ectopic expression of a 
TP53 GOF mutant induced transcriptomic changes, which resulted in enrichment of 
gene signatures related to inflammation and chemotaxis. Bioinformatics analyses 
revealed that a gene signature, upregulated by the TP53 GOF mutation, is 
associated with progression and shorter overall survival in GBM. We also 
observed significant correlations between the TP53 GOF mutation signature and 
inflammation in the clinical database of GBM and other cancers. The TP53 GOF 
mutant showed upregulated C-C motif chemokine ligand 2 (CCL2) and tumor necrosis 
factor alpha (TNFA) expression via nuclear factor kappa B (NFκB) signaling, 
consequently increasing microglia and monocyte-derived immune cell infiltration. 
Additionally, TP53 GOF mutation and CCL2 and TNFA expression correlated 
positively with tumor-associated immunity in patients with GBM. Taken together, 
our findings suggest that the TP53 GOF mutation plays a crucial role in 
inflammatory responses, thereby deteriorating prognostic outcomes in patients 
with GBM.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="668~708" text="Ectopic expression of a  TP53 GOF mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="818~828" text="chemotaxis" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="747~758" text="resulted in" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>