<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Oocyte competence is maintained by m(6)A methyltransferase KIAA1429-mediated RNA 
metabolism during mouse follicular development.

KIAA1429 (also known as vir-like m6A methyltransferase-associated protein 
(VIRMA)), a newly identified component of the RNA m6A methyltransferase complex, 
plays critical roles in guiding region-selective m6A deposition. However, in 
mammals, whether KIAA1429 mediates RNA m6A regulatory pathway functions in vivo 
remains unknown. Here, we show that the Kiaa1429-specific deficiency in oocytes 
resulted in female infertility with defective follicular development and fully 
grown germinal vesicle (GV) oocytes failing to undergo germinal vesicle 
breakdown (GVBD) and consequently losing the ability to resume meiosis. The 
oocyte growth is accompanied by the accumulation of abundant RNAs and 
posttranscriptional regulation. We found that the loss of Kiaa1429 could also 
lead to abnormal RNA metabolism in GV oocytes. RNA-seq profiling revealed that 
Kiaa1429 deletion altered the expression pattern of the oocyte-derived factors 
essential for follicular development. In addition, our data show that the 
conditional depletion of Kiaa1429 decreased the m6A levels in oocytes and mainly 
affected the alternative splicing of genes associated with oogenesis. In 
summary, the m6A methyltransferase KIAA1429-mediated RNA metabolism plays 
critical roles in folliculogenesis and the maintenance of oocyte competence.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="487~515" text="Kiaa1429-specific deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="879~895" text="loss of Kiaa1429" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="988~1005" text="Kiaa1429 deletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="519~526" text="oocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="614~643" text="germinal vesicle (GV) oocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="758~764" text="oocyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="946~953" text="oocytes" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>