<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SPHK1 deficiency protects mice from acetaminophen-induced ER stress and 
mitochondrial permeability transition.

Acetaminophen (APAP) is the leading cause of drug-induced acute liver failure. 
Sphingosine-1-phosphate (S1P), whose formation is catalyzed by sphingosine 
kinase (SPHK)-1 or -2, is a bioactive lipid implicated in human health and 
disease. Here, we show that APAP-treated sphK1-deficient (sphK1-/-) mice 
exhibited markedly less liver damage and reduced inflammation compared with the 
wild-type mice. SPHK1 deficiency alleviated APAP-induced endoplasmic reticulum 
(ER) stress by affecting the phosphorylation of inositol-requiring enzyme 1α 
(IRE1α) and protein kinase R (PKR)-like endoplasmic reticulum kinase 
(PERK)-eukaryotic translation initiation factor 2α (eIF2α), levels of activating 
transcription factor 4 (ATF4), and activation of activating transcription factor 
6 (ATF6). SPHK1 deficiency also inhibited mitochondrial permeability transition 
(MPT), as evidenced by the impaired phosphorylation of JNK, apoptosis 
signal-regulated kinase 1 (ASK1), and glycogen synthase kinase 3β (GSK3β). In 
addition, SPHK1 deficiency reduced the levels of histone deacetylase and 
promoted the acetylation of p65 and STAT1, thereby impairing the transcription 
of inflammatory genes. Supplementation with exogenous S1P significantly reversed 
the activation of the PERK-eIF2α-ATF4 pathway and ATF6 during ER stress as well 
as the activation of GSK3β, ASK1, and JNK during MPT. Both FTY720, a functional 
S1P receptor antagonist, and PF543, an SPHK1 inhibitor, significantly 
ameliorated APAP-induced liver injury and improved animal survival. Our study 
reveals a critical role for SPHK1 in mediating APAP-induced hepatotoxicity by 
promoting ER stress and MPT.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="386~412" text="sphK1-deficient (sphK1-/-)" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="516~532" text="SPHK1 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="902~918" text="SPHK1 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1133~1149" text="SPHK1 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1550~1575" text="PF543, an SPHK1 inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="413~417" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="443~448" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="510~514" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1617~1622" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>