<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SLC27A5 deficiency activates NRF2/TXNRD1 pathway by increased lipid peroxidation 
in HCC.

Solute carrier family 27 member 5 (SLC27A5/FATP5) is involved in fatty acid 
transport and bile acid metabolism; however, little is known about its role in 
human diseases. Here, we first show that SLC27A5 expression is downregulated in 
hepatocellular carcinoma (HCC) by DNA hypermethylation, and reduced SCL27A5 
expression contributes to tumor progression and poor prognosis. Both gain- and 
loss-of-function studies demonstrated that SLC27A5 has an antiproliferative 
effect on HCC cells in vitro and in vivo. Knockout of SLC27A5 increases 
polyunsaturated lipids, leading to increased NADP+/NADPH ratio, ROS production 
as well as lipid peroxidation and the subsequent accumulation of 
4-hydroxy-2-nonenal (4-HNE) in hepatoma cells. Mass spectrometry analysis found 
that 4-HNE directly modifies cysteine residues (Cys513, 518) on KEAP1, thus 
leading KEAP1/NRF2 pathway activation and increases the expression levels of 
NRF2 target genes, such as TXNRD1. Further, SLC27A5 expression negatively 
correlates with TXNRD1 expression in hepatoma cells and clinical HCC samples, 
and blockade of NRF2/TXNRD1 using genetic approaches or inhibitors sensitizes 
SLC27A5-deficient hepatoma cells to sorafenib treatment. Collectively, we 
demonstrated that SLC27A5 acts as a novel tumor suppressor by suppressing TXNRD1 
expression via the KEAP1/NRF2 pathway in HCC. Combination therapy of sorafenib 
and NRF2/TXNRD1 inhibitors may be a promising strategy in personalized HCC 
treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="605~624" text="Knockout of SLC27A5" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1176~1224" text="blockade of NRF2/TXNRD1 using genetic approaches" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="573~582" text="HCC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="583~591" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="596~603" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="813~827" text="hepatoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1269~1283" text="hepatoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>