<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Chchd2 regulates mitochondrial morphology by modulating the levels of Opa1.

The mitochondrion is a highly dynamic organelle that is critical for energy 
production and numerous metabolic processes. Drosophila Chchd2, a homolog of the 
human disease-related genes CHCHD2 and CHCHD10, encodes a mitochondrial protein. 
In this study, we found that loss of Chchd2 in flies resulted in progressive 
degeneration of photoreceptor cells and reduced muscle integrity. In the flight 
muscles of adult Chchd2 mutants, some mitochondria exhibited curling cristae and 
a reduced number of cristae compared to those of controls. Overexpression of 
Chchd2 carrying human disease-related point mutations failed to fully rescue the 
mitochondrial defects in Chchd2 mutants. In fat body cells, loss of Chchd2 
resulted in fragmented mitochondria that could be partially rescued by Marf 
overexpression and enhanced by Opa1 RNAi. The expression level of Opa1 was 
reduced in Chchd2 mutants and increased when Chchd2 was overexpressed. The 
chaperone-like protein P32 co-immunoprecipitated with Chchd2 and YME1L, a 
protease known to processes human OPA1. Moreover, the interaction between P32 
and YME1L enhanced YME1L activity and promoted Opa1 degradation. Finally, Chchd2 
stabilized Opa1 by competing with P32 for YME1L binding. We propose a model 
whereby Chchd2 regulates mitochondrial morphology and tissue homeostasis by 
fine-tuning the levels of OPA1.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="347~361" text="loss of Chchd2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="618~690" text="Overexpression of  Chchd2 carrying human disease-related point mutations" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="744~758" text="Chchd2 mutants" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="779~793" text="loss of Chchd2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="866~886" text="Marf  overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="903~912" text="Opa1 RNAi" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="959~973" text="Chchd2 mutants" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P7" spans="993~1017" text="Chchd2 was overexpressed" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P8" spans="494~508" text="Chchd2 mutants" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="365~370" text="flies" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="412~431" text="photoreceptor cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="444~450" text="muscle" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="469~484" text="flight  muscles" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="763~777" text="fat body cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>