<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Activating transcription factor-4 promotes neuronal death induced by Parkinson's 
disease neurotoxins and α-synuclein aggregates.

Parkinson's disease (PD) is a neurodegenerative disease characterized by the 
loss of dopaminergic neurons in the substantia nigra resulting in severe and 
progressive motor impairments. However, the mechanisms underlying this neuronal 
loss remain largely unknown. Oxidative stress and ER stress have been implicated 
in PD and these factors are known to activate the integrated stress response 
(ISR). Activating transcription factor 4 (ATF4), a key mediator of the ISR, and 
has been reported to induce the expression of genes involved in cellular 
homeostasis. However, during prolonged activation ATF4 can also induce the 
expression of pro-death target genes. Therefore, in the present study, we 
investigated the role of ATF4 in neuronal cell death in models of PD. We 
demonstrate that PD neurotoxins (MPP+ and 6-OHDA) and α-synuclein aggregation 
induced by pre-formed human alpha-synuclein fibrils (PFFs) cause sustained 
upregulation of ATF4 expression in mouse cortical and mesencephalic dopaminergic 
neurons. Furthermore, we demonstrate that PD neurotoxins induce the expression 
of the pro-apoptotic factors Chop, Trb3, and Puma in dopaminergic neurons in an 
ATF4-dependent manner. Importantly, we have determined that PD neurotoxin and 
α-synuclein PFF induced neuronal death is attenuated in ATF4-deficient 
dopaminergic neurons. Furthermore, ectopic expression of ATF4 but not 
transcriptionally defective ATF4ΔRK restores sensitivity of ATF4-deficient 
neurons to PD neurotoxins. Finally, we demonstrate that the eIF2α kinase 
inhibitor C16 suppresses MPP+ and 6-OHDA induced ATF4 activation and protects 
against PD neurotoxin induced dopaminergic neuronal death. Taken together these 
results indicate that ATF4 promotes dopaminergic cell death induced by PD 
neurotoxins and pathogenic α-synuclein aggregates and highlight the ISR factor 
ATF4 as a potential therapeutic target in PD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1441~1455" text="ATF4-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1492~1518" text="ectopic expression of ATF4" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1588~1602" text="ATF4-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1098~1152" text="mouse cortical and mesencephalic dopaminergic  neurons" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1278~1298" text="dopaminergic neurons" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1457~1477" text="dopaminergic neurons" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1604~1611" text="neurons" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>