<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Tumor suppressor ZHX2 inhibits NAFLD-HCC progression via blocking LPL-mediated 
lipid uptake.

Non-alcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) leads to hepatocellular carcinoma 
(HCC). However, the underlying mechanism remains largely unclear. Here, we 
investigated the role of the tumor suppressor Zinc fingers and homeoboxes 2 
(ZHX2) in the progression of NAFLD to HCC. ZHX2 expression was significantly 
decreased in fatty liver tissues, especially in the liver with NAFLD-HCC. ZHX2 
overexpression disturbed lipid homeostasis of cultured HCC cells, and inhibited 
lipid deposition in hepatocytes both in vitro and in vivo. Moreover, ZHX2 
inhibited uptake of exogenous lipids through transcriptional suppression of 
lipid lipase (LPL), leading to retarded proliferation of HCC cells. Importantly, 
LPL overexpression significantly reversed ZHX2-mediated inhibition of HCC cell 
proliferation, xenograft tumor growth, lipid deposition, and spontaneous liver 
tumor formation. Consistently, IHC staining demonstrated a negative correlation 
of ZHX2 with LPL in an HCC cohort. Collectively, ZHX2 protects hepatocytes from 
abnormal lipid deposition in NAFLD through transcriptional repression of LPL, 
which subsequently retards cell growth and NAFLD-HCC progression. These findings 
illustrate a novel mechanism of NAFLD progression into HCC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="477~497" text="ZHX2  overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="798~816" text="LPL overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="538~547" text="HCC cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="584~595" text="hepatocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="601~609" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="614~621" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="773~782" text="HCC cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="868~876" text="HCC cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="893~902" text="xenograft" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="951~956" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="756~769" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="878~891" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="903~915" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="958~973" text="tumor formation" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="747~755" text="retarded" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="854~864" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="831~839" text="reversed" effect="rescues" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>