<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Selective targeting of ubiquitination and degradation of PARP1 by E3 ubiquitin 
ligase WWP2 regulates isoproterenol-induced cardiac remodeling.

The elevated expression of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 (PARP1) and increased 
PARP1 activity, namely, poly(ADP-ribosyl)ation (PARylation), have been observed 
in cardiac remodeling, leading to extreme energy consumption and myocardial 
damage. However, the mechanisms underlying the regulation of PARP1 require 
further study. WWP2, a HECT-type E3 ubiquitin ligase, is highly expressed in the 
heart, but its function there is largely unknown. Here, we clarified the role of 
WWP2 in the regulation of PARP1 and the impact of this regulatory process on 
cardiac remodeling. We determined that the knockout of WWP2 specifically in 
myocardium decreased the level of PARP1 ubiquitination and increased the effects 
of isoproterenol (ISO)-induced PARP1 and PARylation, in turn aggravating 
ISO-induced myocardial hypertrophy, heart failure, and myocardial fibrosis. 
Similar findings were obtained in a model of ISO-induced H9c2 cells with WWP2 
knockdown, while the reexpression of WWP2 significantly increased PARP1 
ubiquitination and decreased PAPR1 and PARylation levels. Mechanistically, 
coimmunoprecipitation results identified that WWP2 is a novel interacting 
protein of PARP1 and mainly interacts with its BRCT domain, thus mediating the 
degradation of PARP1 through the ubiquitin-proteasome system. In addition, 
lysine 418 (K418) and lysine 249 (K249) were shown to be of critical importance 
in regulating PARP1 ubiquitination and degradation by WWP2. These findings 
reveal a novel WWP2-PARP1 signal transduction pathway involved in controlling 
cardiac remodeling and may provide a basis for exploring new strategies for 
treating heart disorders related to cardiac remodeling.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="744~760" text="knockout of WWP2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1084~1099" text="WWP2  knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1111~1131" text="reexpression of WWP2" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="778~788" text="myocardium" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="970~975" text="heart" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1068~1078" text="H9c2 cells" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>