<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[LINC00941 promotes CRC metastasis through preventing SMAD4 protein degradation 
and activating the TGF-β/SMAD2/3 signaling pathway.

LINC00941 is a novel lncRNA that has been found to exhibit protumorigenic and 
prometastatic behaviors during tumorigenesis. However, its role in metastatic 
CRC remains unknown. We aimed to investigate the functions and mechanisms of 
LINC00941 in CRC metastasis. LINC00941 was shown to be upregulated in CRC, and 
upregulated LINC00941 was associated with poor prognosis. Functionally, 
LINC00941 promoted migratory and invasive capacities and accelerated lung 
metastasis in nude mice. Mechanistically, LINC00941 activated EMT in CRC cells, 
as indicated by the increased expression of key molecular markers of cell 
invasion and metastasis (Vimentin, Fibronectin, and Twist1) and simultaneous 
decreased expression of the main invasion suppressors E-cadherin and ZO-1. 
LINC00941 was found to activate EMT by directly binding the SMAD4 protein MH2 
domain and competing with β-TrCP to prevent SMAD4 protein degradation, thus 
activating the TGF-β/SMAD2/3 signaling pathway. Our data reveal the essential 
role of LINC00941 in metastatic CRC via activation of the TGF-β/SMAD2/3 axis, 
which provides new insight into the mechanism of metastatic CRC and a novel 
potential therapeutic target for advanced CRC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="611~620" text="nude mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="666~675" text="CRC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="555~574" text="invasive capacities" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="591~607" text="lung  metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="659~662" text="EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="939~942" text="EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="532~540" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="579~590" text="accelerated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="649~658" text="activated" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="930~938" text="activate" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>