<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Induction of autophagy and suppression of type I IFN secretion by CSFV.

Macroautophagy/autophagy plays an essential role in cellular responses to 
pathogens. However, the precise mechanisms and signaling pathways that modulate 
cellular autophagy in classical swine fever virus (CSFV)-infected host cells 
have not been confirmed. In this study, we showed that CSFV infection inhibits 
the phosphorylation of MTOR (mechanistic target of rapamycin kinase), 
subsequently leading to autophagy initiation. We also show that MAPK/ERK 
(mitogen-activated protein kinase) signaling is involved in CSFV-induced 
autophagy. The CSFV-induced inhibition of AKT/PKB (AKT serine/threonine 
kinase)-MTOR was observed to be partially responsible for the MTOR inactivation 
and subsequent autophagy initiation. Moreover, the CAMKK2/CaMKKβ 
(calcium/calmodulin dependent protein kinase kinase 2)-PRKAA/AMPK (protein 
kinase AMP-activated catalytic subunit alpha) axis was found to be involved in 
CSFV-induced autophagy. Meanwhile, CSFV non-structural protein NS5A induced 
autophagy via the CAMKK2-PRKAA-MTOR signaling pathway but not the AKT-MTOR or 
MAPK1/ERK2-MAPK3/ERK1-MTOR pathway. Although the AKT-MTOR pathway also plays an 
important role in the induction of autophagy by CSFV. We also found the 
interaction between HSP90AB1/HSPCB and NS5A by tandem affinity 
purification/liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry (LC-MS) and 
immunoprecipitation. Furthermore, the CSFV-induced [Ca2+]cyto increase potently 
induced autophagy through CAMKK2 and PRKAA. Moreover, we isolated and identified 
the BECN1/Beclin 1 protein complexes by tandem affinity purification/LC-MS and 
immunoprecipitation, the interaction between BECN1 and MAVS was confirmed by 
immunoprecipitation, laser scanning confocal microscope technology, and GST 
affinity-isolation experiments. Furthermore, CSFV-mediated autophagy suppressing 
type I IFN production is related to the interaction between MAVS and BECN1. 
Finally, the modulation of autophagy induction pathways by different autophagy 
regulatory factors significantly affected the replication of CSFV.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1511~1520" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="995~1004" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="775~784" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1059~1068" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1503~1510" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="987~994" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="785~795" text="initiation" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1050~1057" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>