<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mitochondrial DNA stress triggers autophagy-dependent ferroptotic death.

Pancreatic cancer tends to be highly resistant to current therapy and remains 
one of the great challenges in biomedicine with very low 5-year survival rates. 
Here, we report that zalcitabine, an antiviral drug for human immunodeficiency 
virus infection, can suppress the growth of primary and immortalized human 
pancreatic cancer cells through the induction of ferroptosis, an iron-dependent 
form of regulated cell death. Mechanically, this effect relies on 
zalcitabine-induced mitochondrial DNA stress, which activates the 
STING1/TMEM173-mediated DNA sensing pathway, leading to 
macroautophagy/autophagy-dependent ferroptotic cell death via lipid 
peroxidation, but not a type I interferon response. Consequently, the genetic 
and pharmacological inactivation of the autophagy-dependent ferroptosis pathway 
diminishes the anticancer effects of zalcitabine in cell culture and animal 
models. Together, these findings not only provide a new approach for pancreatic 
cancer therapy but also increase our understanding of the interplay between 
autophagy and DNA damage response in shaping cell death.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="358~413" text="primary and immortalized human  pancreatic cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="943~955" text="cell culture" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="960~974" text="animal  models" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="348~354" text="growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="439~450" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="697~719" text="ferroptotic cell death" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="335~343" text="suppress" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="426~435" text="induction" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="650~660" text="leading to" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>