<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Chemotherapeutic paclitaxel and cisplatin differentially induce pyroptosis in 
A549 lung cancer cells via caspase-3/GSDME activation.

Gasdermin E (GSDME) has an important role in inducing secondary 
necrosis/pyroptosis. Upon apoptotic stimulation, it can be cleaved by activated 
caspase-3 to generate its N-terminal fragment (GSDME-NT), which executes 
pyroptosis by perforating the plasma membrane. GSDME is expressed in many human 
lung cancers including A549 cells. Paclitaxel and cisplatin are two 
representative chemotherapeutic agents for lung cancers, which induce apoptosis 
via different action mechanisms. However, it remains unclear whether they can 
induce GSDME-mediated secondary necrosis/pyroptosis in lung A549 cancer cells. 
Here we showed that both paclitaxel and cisplatin evidently induced apoptosis in 
A549 cells as revealed by the activation of multiple apoptotic markers. Notably, 
some of the dying cells displayed characteristic morphology of secondary 
necrosis/pyroptosis, by blowing large bubbles from the cellular membrane 
accompanied by caspase-3 activation and GSDME-NT generation. But the ability of 
cisplatin to induce this phenomenon was much stronger than that of paclitaxel. 
Consistent with this, cisplatin triggered much higher activation of caspase-3 
and generation of GSDME-NT than paclitaxel, suggesting that the levels of 
secondary necrosis/pyroptosis correlated with the levels of active caspase-3 and 
GSDME-NT. Supporting this, caspase-3 specific inhibitor (Ac-DEVD-CHO) suppressed 
cisplatin-induced GSDME-NT generation and concurrently reduced the secondary 
necrosis/pyroptosis. Besides, GSDME knockdown significantly inhibited cisplatin- 
but not paclitaxel-induced secondary necrosis/pyroptosis. These results 
indicated that cisplatin induced higher levels of secondary necrosis/pyroptosis 
in A549 cells than paclitaxel, suggesting that cisplatin may provide additional 
advantages in the treatment of lung cancers with high levels of GSDME 
expression.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1481~1523" text="caspase-3 specific inhibitor (Ac-DEVD-CHO)" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1644~1659" text="GSDME knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="827~837" text="A549 cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="927~932" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1853~1863" text="A549 cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="813~822" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="983~991" text="necrosis" phenotype="necrosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="992~1002" text="pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1614~1622" text="necrosis" phenotype="necrosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1623~1633" text="pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1733~1741" text="necrosis" phenotype="necrosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH6" spans="1742~1752" text="pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH7" spans="1829~1837" text="necrosis" phenotype="necrosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH8" spans="1838~1848" text="pyroptosis" phenotype="pyroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="805~812" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1591~1598" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1674~1683" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1794~1801" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>