<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DDX3 modulates cisplatin resistance in OSCC through ALKBH5-mediated 
m(6)A-demethylation of FOXM1 and NANOG.

Platinum based drugs alone or in combination with 5FU and docetaxel are common 
regimen chemotherapeutics for the treatment of advanced OSCC. Chemoresistance is 
one of the major factors of treatment failure in OSCC. Human RNA helicase DDX3 
plays an important role in cell proliferation, invasion, and metastasis in 
several neoplasms. The potential role of DDX3 in chemoresistance is yet to be 
explored. Enhanced cancer stem cells (CSCs) population significantly contributes 
to chemoresistance and recurrence. A recent study showed that m6A RNA regulates 
self-renewal and tumorigenesis property in cancer. In this study we found 
genetic (shRNA) or pharmacological (ketorolac salt) inhibition of DDX3 reduced 
CSC population by suppressing the expression of FOXM1 and NANOG. We also found 
that m6A demethylase ALKBH5 is directly regulated by DDX3 which leads to 
decreased m6A methylation in FOXM1 and NANOG nascent transcript that contribute 
to chemoresistance. Here, we found DDX3 expression was upregulated in both 
cisplatin-resistant OSCC lines and chemoresistant tumors when compared with 
their respective sensitive counterparts. In a patient-derived cell xenograft 
model of chemoresistant OSCC, ketorolac salt restores cisplatin-mediated cell 
death and facilitates a significant reduction of tumor burdens. Our work 
uncovers a critical function of DDX3 and provides a new role in m6 demethylation 
of RNA. A combination regimen of ketorolac salt with cisplatin deserves further 
clinical investigation in advanced OSCC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="764~815" text="pharmacological (ketorolac salt) inhibition of DDX3" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="825~839" text="CSC population" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1259~1319" text="patient-derived cell xenograft  model of chemoresistant OSCC" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1364~1375" text="cell  death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1336~1344" text="restores" effect="rescues" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>