<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Cytokine regulation of apoptosis-induced apoptosis and apoptosis-induced cell 
proliferation in vascular smooth muscle cells.

Vascular smooth muscle cells (VSMCs) are the main structural cell of blood 
vessels, and VSMC apoptosis occurs in vascular disease, after injury, and in 
vessel remodeling during development. Although VSMC apoptosis is viewed as 
silent, recent studies show that apoptotic cells can promote apoptosis-induced 
compensatory proliferation (AICP), apoptosis-induced apoptosis (AIA), and 
migration of both local somatic and infiltrating inflammatory cells. However, 
the effects of VSMC apoptosis on adjacent VSMCs, and their underlying signaling 
and mechanisms are unknown. We examined the consequences of VSMC apoptosis after 
activating extrinsic and intrinsic death pathways. VSMCs undergoing apoptosis 
through Fas/CD95 or the protein kinase inhibitor staurosporine transcriptionally 
activated interleukin 6 (IL-6) and granulocyte-macrophage colony stimulating 
factor (GM-CSF), leading to their secretion. Apoptosis induced activation of 
p38MAPK, JNK, and Akt, but neither p38 and JNK activation nor IL-6 or GM-CSF 
induction required caspase cleavage. IL-6 induction depended upon p38 activity, 
while Fas-induced GM-CSF expression required p38 and JNK. Conditioned media from 
apoptotic VSMCs induced VSMC apoptosis in vitro, and IL-6 and GM-CSF acted as 
pro-survival factors for AIA. VSMC apoptosis was studied in vivo using SM22α-DTR 
mice that express the diphtheria toxin receptor in VSMCs only. DT administration 
induced VSMC apoptosis and VSMC proliferation, and also signficantly induced 
IL-6 and GM-CSF. We conclude that VSMC apoptosis activates multiple 
caspase-independent intracellular signaling cascades, leading to release of 
soluble cytokines involved in regulation of both cell proliferation and 
apoptosis. VSMC AICP may ameliorate while AIA may amplify the effects of 
pro-apoptotic stimuli in vessel remodeling and disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1336~1340" text="VSMC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1351~1359" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1448~1455" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1473~1477" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1524~1529" text="VSMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="1563~1567" text="VSMC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C8" spans="1582~1586" text="VSMC" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1341~1350" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1568~1577" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1587~1600" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1555~1562" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1328~1335" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>