<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Acetylcholinesterase promotes apoptosis in insect neurons.

Apoptosis plays a major role in development, tissue renewal and the progression 
of degenerative diseases. Studies on various types of mammalian cells reported a 
pro-apoptotic function of acetylcholinesterase (AChE), particularly in the 
formation of the apoptosome and the degradation of nuclear DNA. While three AChE 
splice variants are present in mammals, invertebrates typically express two ache 
genes that code for a synaptically located protein and a protein with 
non-synaptic functions respectively. In order to investigate a potential 
contribution of AChE to apoptosis in insects, we selected the migratory locust 
Locusta migratoria. We established primary neuronal cultures of locust brains 
and characterized apoptosis progression in vitro. Dying neurons displayed 
typical characteristics of apoptosis, including caspase-activation, nuclear 
condensation and DNA fragmentation visualized by TUNEL staining. Addition of the 
AChE inhibitors neostigmine and territrem B reduced apoptotic cell death under 
normal culture conditions. Moreover, both inhibitors completely suppressed 
hypoxia-induced neuronal cell death. Exposure of live animals to severe hypoxia 
moderately increased the expression of ace-1 in locust brains in vivo. Our 
results indicate a previously unreported role of AChE in insect apoptosis that 
parallels the pro-apoptotic role in mammalian cells. This similarity adds to the 
list of apoptotic mechanisms shared by mammals and insects, supporting the 
hypothesized existence of an ancient, complex apoptosis regulatory network 
present in common ancestors of vertebrates and insects.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1211~1218" text="animals" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1286~1299" text="locust brains" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1300~1307" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="670~706" text="migratory locust  Locusta migratoria" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="723~748" text="primary neuronal cultures" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="752~765" text="locust brains" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="807~815" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="823~830" text="neurons" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1053~1073" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1182~1192" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="869~878" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1045~1052" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1145~1155" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>