<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Sphingosylphosphorylcholine alleviates hypoxia-caused apoptosis in cardiac 
myofibroblasts via CaM/p38/STAT3 pathway.

Blockade of hypoxia-caused nonmyocytes apoptosis helps improve survival and 
mitigate ventricular remodeling and dysfunction during the chronic stage of 
myocardial infarction. But tools affecting nonmyocyte apoptosis are very rare. 
Sphingosylphosphorylcholine (SPC), a naturally occurring bioactive sphingolipid 
in plasma, was proved to protect cardiomyocyte against apoptosis in an ischemic 
model in our previous study. Here, we showed that SPC also inhibited 
hypoxia-induced apoptosis in myofibroblasts, an important type of nonmyocytes in 
the heart. Calmodulin (CaM) is an identified receptor of SPC. We clarified that 
SPC inhibited myofibroblast apoptosis through CaM as evidenced by decreased 
cleaved caspase 3, PARP1 and condensed nucleus. Furthermore, the employment of 
inhibitor and agonist of p38 and STAT3 suggests that SPC inhibits myofibroblast 
apoptosis by regulating the phosphorylation of p38 and STAT3, and they act as 
downstream of CaM. The present work may provide new evidence on the regulation 
of myofibroblasts apoptosis by SPC and a novel target for heart remodeling after 
hypoxia.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="614~628" text="myofibroblasts" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="762~775" text="myofibroblast" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="971~984" text="myofibroblast" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="601~610" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="776~785" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="986~995" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="574~583" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="752~761" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="962~970" text="inhibits" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>