<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Baicalein attenuates caspase-independent cells death via inhibiting PARP-1 
activation and AIF nuclear translocation in cerebral ischemia/reperfusion rats.

It is reported that baicalein can activate PI3K/AKT pathway, inhibit caspase 
activation and reduce cerebral infarct volume in middle cerebral artery 
occlusion (MCAO) rats. However, a caspase-independent mechanism initiated by 
poly (ADP-ribose) polymerase-1 (PARP-1) activation has been reported to make 
more contribution to cells death after ischemic stroke. In the present study, we 
established a cerebral ischemia/reperfusion (I/R) rat model through middle 
cerebral artery occlusion following reperfusion to investigate the mechanisms of 
ischemic tissue recovery following baicalein treatment. The data showed that 
baicalein treatment at dose of 100 mg/kg for 7 days significantly inhibited the 
release of cytokines, activation of PARP-1, nuclear translocation of 
apoptosis-inducing factor (AIF) and macrophage migration inhibitory factor (MIF) 
in cerebral I/R rats, therefore decreased cerebral infarct volume and 
neurological scores. Then, we further investigated the signal transduction 
mechanisms of ischemic tissue protection by baicalein in vitro. Following oxygen 
and glucose deprivation (OGD) in SH-SY5Y cells, the mitochondrial AIF was 
translocated into nucleus after 12 h. The co-immunoprecipitation analysis showed 
that the interaction between AIF and MIF was activated by OGD and subsequently 
resulted in MIF nuclear translocation. Also, the baicalein inhibited apoptosis, 
reduced oxidative stress, protected mitochondrial function and restored 
mitochondrial membrane potential in OGD cells. The results obtained from both in 
vivo and in vitro study demonstrated the PARP-1/AIF pathway involved in 
mechanisms of baicalein to protect the cerebral tissues from ischemic injury.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="596~605" text="rat model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1031~1035" text="rats" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1277~1290" text="SH-SY5Y cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1216~1224" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1671~1680" text="OGD cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1550~1559" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1540~1549" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>