<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SPECT/CT imaging of apoptosis in aortic aneurysm with radiolabeled duramycin.

The objective of this research was to estimate whether a [99mTc]duramycin probe 
can be used for apoptosis imaging in patients with aortic aneurysm (AA). 
Vascular smooth muscle cell (SMC) apoptosis has an important influence on AA 
development. Thus, non-invasive imaging of SMC apoptosis may be able to evaluate 
AA progress and risk stratification. SMCs were treated with hydrogen peroxide 
(H2O2; 200 μΜ) or culture medium as a control. Apoptosis was measured using flow 
cytometry and [99mTc]duramycin to detect the binding efficiency to apoptotic 
SMCs. C57/BL6 mice were administered angiotensin-II and beta-aminopropionitrile 
(BAPN) subcutaneously to establish an AA model, or saline for controls. Aortic 
specimens underwent pathological evaluation and their aortic diameters were 
measured after 6 weeks. Micro-SPECT/CT scanning of [99mTc]duramycin and 18F-FDG 
PET detection were performed. SMCs treated with H2O2 showed more apoptosis 
compared with the control group (67.2 ± 3.8% vs. 16.1 ± 0.6%, P < 0.01). The 
experimental group showed a high rate of AA formation (70%) compared with no AA 
formation in the control group. The average aorta diameter was higher and 
[99mTc]duramycin uptake at the AA site was higher in the experimental group 
compared with the control group. Compared with the normal aorta in the control 
group, AA in experiment group had more severe medial degeneration, elastic fiber 
reduction and fracture, and collagen degeneration. TUNEL staining verified the 
higher apoptosis rate at the AA site in experiment group compared with the 
control group (63.9 ± 3.7% in ascending AA, 66.4 ± 4.0% in thoracic AA, vs. 
3.5 ± 0.3% in normal aorta, P < 0.01). [99mTc]Duramycin may be an effective 
probe to evaluate apoptosis in AA.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="431~435" text="SMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="633~637" text="SMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="639~651" text="C57/BL6 mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="982~986" text="SMCs" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1231~1236" text="aorta" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1755~1760" text="aorta" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1017~1026" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1588~1597" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1005~1016" text="showed more" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1581~1587" text="higher" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>