<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Autophagy inhibition with chloroquine reverts paclitaxel resistance and 
attenuates metastatic potential in human nonsmall lung adenocarcinoma A549 cells 
via ROS mediated modulation of β-catenin pathway.

Paclitaxel is one of the most commonly used drugs for the treatment of nonsmall 
cell lung cancer (NSCLC). However acquired resistance to paclitaxel, epithelial 
to mesenchymal transition and cancer stem cell formation are the major obstacles 
for successful chemotherapy with this drug. Some of the major reasons behind 
chemoresistance development include increased ability of the cancer cells to 
survive under stress conditions by autophagy, increased expression of drug 
efflux pumps, tubulin mutations etc. In this study we found that inhibition of 
autophagy with chloroquine prevented development of paclitaxel resistance in 
A549 cells with time and potentiated the effect of paclitaxel by increased 
accumulation of superoxide-producing damaged mitochondria, with elevated ROS 
generation, it also increased the apoptotic rate and sub G0/ G1 phase arrest 
with time in A549 cells treated with paclitaxel and attenuated the metastatic 
potential and cancer stem cell population of the paclitaxel-resistant cells by 
ROS mediated modulation of the Wnt/β-catenin signaling pathway, thereby 
increasing paclitaxel sensitivity. ROS here played a crucial role in modulating 
Akt activity when autophagy process was hindered by chloroquine, excessive ROS 
accumulation in the cell inhibited Akt activity. In addition, chloroquine 
pre-treatment followed by taxol (10 nM) treatment did not show significant 
toxicity towards non-carcinomas WI38 cells (lung fibroblast cells). Thus 
autophagy inhibition by CQ pre-treatment can be used as a fruitful strategy to 
combat the phenomenon of paclitaxel resistance development as well as metastasis 
in lung cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="840~850" text="A549 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1085~1095" text="A549 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1200~1226" text="paclitaxel-resistant cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1485~1489" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1633~1682" text="non-carcinomas WI38 cells (lung fibroblast cells)" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="762~771" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1028~1042" text="apoptotic rate" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1047~1070" text="sub G0/ G1 phase arrest" phenotype="cell cycle arrest" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1139~1160" text="metastatic  potential" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1403~1420" text="autophagy process" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1690~1699" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="747~757" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1014~1023" text="increased" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1124~1134" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1425~1433" text="hindered" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1700~1710" text="inhibition" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>