<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Caspase cleavage of transcription factor Sp1 enhances apoptosis.

Sp1 is a ubiquitous transcription factor that regulates many genes involved in 
apoptosis and senescence. Sp1 also has a role in the DNA damage response; at low 
levels of DNA damage, Sp1 is phosphorylated by ATM and localizes to 
double-strand break sites where it facilitates DNA double-strand-break repair. 
Depletion of Sp1 increases the sensitivity of cells to DNA damage, whereas 
overexpression of Sp1 can drive cells into apoptosis. In response to a variety 
of stimuli, Sp1 can be regulated through proteolytic cleavage by caspases and/or 
degradation. Here, we show that activation of apoptosis through DNA damage or 
TRAIL-mediated activation of the extrinsic apoptotic pathway induces 
caspase-mediated cleavage of Sp1. Cleavage of Sp1 was coincident with the 
appearance of cleaved caspase 3, and produced a 70 kDa Sp1 product. In vitro 
analysis revealed a novel caspase cleavage site at aspartic acid 183. Mutation 
of aspartic acid 183 to alanine conferred resistance to cleavage, and ectopic 
expression of the Sp1 D183A rendered cells resistant to apoptotic stimuli, 
indicating that Sp1 cleavage is involved in the induction of apoptosis. The 
70 kDa product resulting from caspase cleavage of Sp1 comprises amino acids 
184-785. This truncated form, designated Sp1-70C, which retains transcriptional 
activity, induced apoptosis when overexpressed in normal epithelial cells, 
whereas Sp1D183A induced significantly less apoptosis. Together, these data 
reveal a new caspase cleavage site in Sp1 and demonstrate for the first time 
that caspase cleavage of Sp1 promotes apoptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1067~1103" text="ectopic  expression of the Sp1 D183A" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1113~1118" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1444~1460" text="epithelial cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1405~1414" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1507~1516" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1397~1404" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1480~1487" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>