<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Doxorubicin sensitizes cancer cells to Smac mimetic via synergistic activation 
of the CYLD/RIPK1/FADD/caspase-8-dependent apoptosis.

Smac/Diablo is a pro-apoptotic protein via interaction with inhibitors of 
apoptosis proteins (IAPs) to relieve their inhibition of caspases. Smac mimetic 
compounds (also known as antagonists of IAPs) mimic the function of Smac/Diablo 
and sensitize cancer cells to TNF-induced apoptosis. However, the majority of 
cancer cells are resistant to Smac mimetic alone. Doxorubicin is a widely used 
chemotherapeutic drug and causes adverse effect of cardiotoxicity in many 
patients. Therefore, it is important to find strategies of combined chemotherapy 
to increase chemosensitivity and reduce the adverse effects. Here, we report 
that doxorubicin synergizes with Smac mimetic to trigger TNF-mediated apoptosis, 
which is mechanistically distinct from doxorubicin-induced cell death. 
Doxorubicin sensitizes cancer cells including human pancreatic and colorectal 
cancer cells to Smac mimetic treatment. The combined treatment leads to 
synergistic induction of TNFα to initiate apoptosis through activating NF-κB and 
c-Jun signaling pathways. Knockdown of caspase-8 or knockout of FADD 
significantly blocked apoptosis synergistically induced by Smac mimetic and 
doxorubicin, but had no effect on cell death caused by doxorubicin alone. 
Moreover, Smac mimetic and doxorubicin-induced apoptosis requires 
receptor-interacting protein kinase 1 (RIPK1) and its deubiquitinating enzyme 
cylindromatosis (CYLD), not A20. These in vitro findings demonstrate that 
combination of Smac mimetic and doxorubicin synergistically triggers apoptosis 
through the TNF/CYLD/RIPK1/FADD/caspase-8 signaling pathway. Importantly, the 
combined treatment induced in vivo synergistic anti-tumor effects in the 
xenograft tumor model. Thus, the combined therapy using Smac mimetic and 
doxorubicin presents a promising apoptosis-inducing strategy]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1180~1202" text="Knockdown of caspase-8" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1206~1222" text="knockout of FADD" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="943~955" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="966~1011" text="human pancreatic and colorectal  cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1783~1790" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1830~1851" text="xenograft tumor model" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1561~1569" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="836~845" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="907~917" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1114~1123" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1246~1255" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1335~1345" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="1423~1432" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH6" spans="1666~1675" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="815~822" text="trigger" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="899~906" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1105~1113" text="initiate" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1238~1245" text="blocked" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1322~1331" text="no effect" effect="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1415~1422" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1657~1665" text="triggers" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>