<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Artemisinin and dihydroartemisinin promote β-cell apoptosis induced by palmitate 
via enhancing ER stress.

Artemisinin (ART) and dihydroartemisinin (DHA) are first-line antimalarial drugs 
and have been reported to have anti-obesity effects. Hyperlipidemia is 
associated with β-cell damage in obese subjects, which could contribute to the 
pathogenesis of type 2 diabetes. In addition to their anti-obesity effects, ART 
and DHA also have protective roles in some diseases. Thus, we investigated the 
effects of ART and DHA in palmitate-induced β-cell apoptosis and the underlying 
mechanism. In this study, the rat pancreatic β-cell line INS-1 and mouse 
pancreatic β-cell line MIN6 were cultured with palmitate (PA) (0.1 mM) to induce 
cell apoptosis in the presence or absence of ART or DHA. Cell apoptosis was 
investigated by using flow cytometry, and the expression of ER stress markers, 
including CHOP, GRP78 and PDI, was detected by Western blotting and/or qRT-PCR. 
The results showed that ART and DHA significantly increased the apoptosis of 
β-cells induced by PA and exacerbated the ER stress caused by PA. An inhibitor 
of ER stress, 4-phenylbutyric acid (4-PBA), significantly ameliorated cell 
apoptosis caused by ART and DHA in PA-treated β-cells, consistent with the 
inhibition of ER stress. Together, the findings from the current study suggested 
that ART and DHA may promote lipid disorder-associated β-cell injury via 
enhancing ER stress when they were used to treat obesity.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="614~646" text="rat pancreatic β-cell line INS-1" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="651~685" text="mouse  pancreatic β-cell line MIN6" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="740~744" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="797~801" text="Cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1056~1063" text="β-cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1206~1210" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1258~1265" text="β-cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="745~754" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="802~811" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1042~1051" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1212~1221" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="732~738" text="induce" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1028~1037" text="increased" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1064~1071" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1194~1205" text="ameliorated" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>