<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Abdominal paracentesis drainage attenuates severe acute pancreatitis by 
enhancing cell apoptosis via PI3K/AKT signaling pathway.

Our previous studies have shown that abdominal paracentesis drainage (APD) is a 
safe and effective strategy for patients with severe acute pancreatitis (SAP). 
However, the underlying mechanisms behind APD treatment remain poorly 
understood. Given that apoptosis is a critical pathological response of SAP, we 
here aim to investigate the effect of APD on cell apoptosis in pancreatic 
tissues during SAP and to explore its potential molecular mechanism. SAP was 
induced by 5% sodium-taurocholate retrograde while APD group was inserted a 
drainage tube into the right lower abdomen of rats immediately after SAP 
induction. Histopathological staining, serum amylase, endotoxin and inflammatory 
mediators were measured. Cell apoptosis, apoptosis-related proteins and 
signaling pathway were also evaluated. Our results demonstrated that APD 
treatment significantly attenuated pancreatic damage and decreased the serum 
levels of amylase, endotoxin, TNF-α, IL-1 and IL-6 in rats with SAP. Notably, 
APD treatment enhanced cell apoptosis and reduced necrosis in pancreatic 
tissues, as evidenced by Tunnel staining, the increased pro-apoptosis proteins 
(Cleaved-caspase-3 and bax) and decreased anti-apoptosis protein (Bcl-2). 
Moreover, the effect of APD on cell apoptosis was further confirmed by the 
regulatory pathway of PI3K/AKT and NF-kB signaling pathway. These results 
suggest that APD attenuates the severity of SAP by enhancing cell apoptosis via 
suppressing PI3K/AKT signaling pathway. Our findings provide new insights for 
understanding the effectiveness of APD in patients with SAP.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="720~724" text="rats" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1109~1113" text="rats" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1157~1161" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1196~1215" text="pancreatic  tissues" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1394~1398" text="cell" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1162~1171" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1184~1192" text="necrosis" phenotype="oncosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1399~1408" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1148~1156" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1176~1183" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>