<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TGFB1-induced autophagy affects the pattern of pancreatic cancer progression in 
distinct ways depending on SMAD4 status.

Pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma (PDAC) is one of the most aggressive and lethal 
malignancies. Given that macroautophagy/autophagy activation is prevalent in 
PDAC, the dual roles of autophagy could be involved in PDAC heterogeneity. In 
this work, we demonstrated that TGFB1 induced autophagic flux through 
SMAD4-dependent or SMAD4-independent pathways based on a distinct genetic 
context. In SMAD4-positive PDAC cells, TGFB1-induced autophagy promoted 
proliferation and inhibited migration by decreasing the nuclear translocation of 
SMAD4. Conversely, TGFB1-induced autophagy inhibited proliferation and promoted 
migration in SMAD4-negative cells through the regulation of MAPK/ERK activation. 
TGFB1 expression also positively correlated with LC3B expression in PDAC 
specimens. A high level of LC3B was associated with unfavorable overall survival 
(OS) and disease-free survival (DFS) in SMAD4-negative PDAC patients, although 
LC3B could not predict OS and DFS for the 110 PDAC patients. Thus, TGFB1-induced 
autophagy contributed to the different patterns of PDAC progression. This 
knowledge can aid in improving our understanding of the molecular classification 
of PDAC and might guide the development of therapeutic strategies for PDAC, 
especially for SMAD4-negative PDAC.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="520~545" text="SMAD4-positive PDAC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="757~777" text="SMAD4-negative cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="561~570" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="581~594" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="609~618" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="696~705" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="716~729" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH5" spans="744~753" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH6" spans="1144~1153" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="553~560" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="571~579" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="599~608" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="688~695" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="706~715" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="734~742" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E6" spans="1135~1142" text="induced" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>