<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Lysophosphatidic acid promotes survival of T lymphoma cells by altering 
apoptosis and glucose metabolism.

Lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) is a bioactive lipid, which plays an indispensable 
role in various physiological and pathological processes. Moreover, an elevated 
level of LPA has been observed in malignancies of different origins and 
implicated in their progression via modulation of proliferation, apoptosis, 
invasion and metastasis. Interestingly, few recent reports suggest a pivotal 
role of LPA-modulated metabolism in oncogenesis of ovarian cancer. However, 
little is understood regarding the role of LPA in the development and 
progression of T cell malignancies, which are considered as one of the most 
challenging neoplasms for clinical management. Additionally, mechanisms 
underlying the LPA-dependent modulation of glucose metabolism in T cell lymphoma 
are also not known. Therefore, the present study was undertaken to explore the 
role of LPA-altered apoptosis and glucose metabolism on the survival of T 
lymphoma cells. Observations of this investigation suggest that LPA supports 
survival of T lymphoma cells via altering apoptosis and glucose metabolism 
through changing the level of reactive species, namely nitric oxide and reactive 
oxygen species along with expression of various survival and glucose metabolism 
regulatory molecules, including hypoxia-inducible factor 1-alpha, p53, Bcl2, and 
glucose transporter 3, hexokinase II, pyruvate kinase muscle isozyme 2, 
monocarboxylate transporter 1, pyruvate dehydrogenase kinase 1. Taken together' 
the results of the present investigation decipher the novel mechanisms of 
LPA-mediated survival of T lymphoma cells via modulation of apoptosis and 
glucose metabolism.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1122~1138" text="T lymphoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1152~1161" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1143~1151" text="altering" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>