<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Hypoxia-induced acetylation of PAK1 enhances autophagy and promotes brain 
tumorigenesis via phosphorylating ATG5.

Although the treatment of brain tumors by targeting kinase-regulated 
macroautophagy/autophagy, is under investigation, the precise mechanism 
underlying autophagy initiation and its significance in glioblastoma (GBM) 
remains to be defined. Here, we report that PAK1 (p21 [RAC1] activated kinase 1) 
is significantly upregulated and promotes GBM development. The Cancer Genome 
Atlas analysis suggests that the oncogenic role of PAK1 in GBM is mainly 
associated with autophagy. Subsequent experiments demonstrate that PAK1 indeed 
serves as a positive modulator for hypoxia-induced autophagy in GBM. 
Mechanistically, hypoxia induces ELP3-mediated PAK1 acetylation at K420, which 
suppresses the dimerization of PAK1 and enhances its activity, thereby leading 
to subsequent PAK1-mediated ATG5 (autophagy related 5) phosphorylation at the 
T101 residue. This event not only protects ATG5 from ubiquitination-dependent 
degradation but also increases the affinity between the ATG12-ATG5 complex and 
ATG16L1 (autophagy related 16 like 1). Consequently, ELP3-dependent PAK1 (K420) 
acetylation and PAK1-mediated ATG5 (T101) phosphorylation are required for 
hypoxia-induced autophagy and brain tumorigenesis by promoting autophagosome 
formation. Silencing PAK1 with shRNA or small molecule inhibitor FRAX597 
potentially blocks autophagy and GBM growth. Furthermore, SIRT1-mediated 
PAK1-deacetylation at K420 hinders autophagy and GBM growth. Clinically, the 
levels of PAK1 (K420) acetylation significantly correlate with the expression of 
ATG5 (T101) phosphorylation in GBM patients. Together, this report uncovers that 
the acetylation modification and kinase activity of PAK1 plays an instrumental 
role in hypoxia-induced autophagy initiation and maintaining GBM growth. 
Therefore, PAK1 and its regulator in the autophagy pathway might represent 
potential therapeutic targets for GBM treatment.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1363~1388" text="Silencing PAK1 with shRNA" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1304~1309" text="brain" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1459~1462" text="GBM" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1549~1552" text="GBM" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1290~1299" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1310~1323" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1445~1454" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1535~1544" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1282~1289" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1438~1444" text="blocks" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1527~1534" text="hinders" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>