<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Immunogenic Chemotherapy Enhances Recruitment of CAR-T Cells to Lung Tumors and 
Improves Antitumor Efficacy when Combined with Checkpoint Blockade.

Adoptive therapy using chimeric antigen receptor-modified T cells (CAR-T cells) 
is effective in hematologic but not epithelial malignancies, which cause the 
greatest mortality. In breast and lung cancer patients, CAR-T cells targeting 
the tumor-associated antigen receptor tyrosine kinase-like orphan receptor 1 
(ROR1) infiltrate tumors poorly and become dysfunctional. To test strategies for 
enhancing efficacy, we adapted the KrasLSL-G12D/+;p53f/f autochthonous model of 
lung adenocarcinoma to express the CAR target ROR1. Murine ROR1 CAR-T cells 
transferred after lymphodepletion with cyclophosphamide (Cy) transiently control 
tumor growth but infiltrate tumors poorly and lose function, similar to what is 
seen in patients. Adding oxaliplatin (Ox) to the lymphodepletion regimen 
activates tumor macrophages to express T-cell-recruiting chemokines, resulting 
in improved CAR-T cell infiltration, remodeling of the tumor microenvironment, 
and increased tumor sensitivity to anti-PD-L1. Combination therapy with Ox/Cy 
and anti-PD-L1 synergistically improves CAR-T cell-mediated tumor control and 
survival, providing a strategy to improve CAR-T cell efficacy in the clinic.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="583~604" text="KrasLSL-G12D/+;p53f/f" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="605~648" text="autochthonous model of  lung adenocarcinoma" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="959~970" text="macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1078~1083" text="tumor" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1117~1122" text="tumor" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="788~800" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="779~786" text="control" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>