<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Role of Wdr45b in maintaining neural autophagy and cognitive function.

Macroautophagy/autophagy functions as a quality control mechanism by degrading 
misfolded proteins and damaged organelles and plays an essential role in 
maintaining neural homeostasis. The phosphoinositide 
phosphatidylinositol-3-phosphate (PtdIns3P) effector Atg18 is essential for 
autophagosome formation in yeast. Mammalian cells contain four Atg18 homologs, 
belonging to two subclasses, WIPI1 (WD repeat domain, phosphoinositide 
interacting 1), WIPI2 and WDR45B/WIPI3 (WD repeat domain 45B), WDR45/WIPI4. The 
role of Wdr45b in autophagy and in neural homeostasis, however, remains unknown. 
Recent human genetic studies have revealed a potential causative role of WDR45B 
in intellectual disability. Here we demonstrated that mice deficient in Wdr45b 
exhibit motor deficits and learning and memory defects. Histological analysis 
reveals that wdr45b knockout (KO) mice exhibit a large number of swollen axons 
and show cerebellar atrophy. SQSTM1- and ubiquitin-positive aggregates, which 
are autophagy substrates, accumulate in various brain regions in wdr45b KO mice. 
Double KO mice, wdr45b and wdr45, die within one day after birth and exhibit 
more severe autophagy defects than either of the single KO mice, suggesting that 
these two genes act cooperatively in autophagy. Our studies demonstrated that 
WDR45B is critical for neural homeostasis in mice. The wdr45b KO mice provide a 
model to study the pathogenesis of intellectual disability.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="812~831" text="deficient in Wdr45b" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="925~945" text="wdr45b knockout (KO)" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1136~1145" text="wdr45b KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1153~1185" text="Double KO mice, wdr45b and wdr45" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="807~811" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="946~950" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1146~1150" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1243~1252" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1253~1260" text="defects" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>