<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[VCP maintains lysosomal homeostasis and TFEB activity in differentiated skeletal 
muscle.

Differentiated tissue is particularly vulnerable to alterations in protein and 
organelle homeostasis. The essential protein VCP, mutated in hereditary 
inclusion body myopathy, amyotrophic lateral sclerosis and frontotemporal 
dementia, is critical for efficient clearance of misfolded proteins and damaged 
organelles in dividing cells, but its role in terminally differentiated tissue 
affected by disease mutations is less clear. To understand the relevance of VCP 
in differentiated tissue, we inactivated it in skeletal muscle of adult mice. 
Surprisingly, knockout muscle demonstrated a necrotic myopathy with increased 
macroautophagic/autophagic proteins and damaged lysosomes. This was not solely 
due to a defect in autophagic degradation because age-matched mice with muscle 
inactivation of the autophagy essential protein, ATG5, did not demonstrate a 
myopathy. Notably, myofiber necrosis was preceded by upregulation of 
LGALS3/Galectin-3, a marker of damaged lysosomes, and TFEB activation, 
suggesting early defects in the lysosomal system. Consistent with that, myofiber 
necrosis was recapitulated by chemical induction of lysosomal membrane 
permeabilization (LMP) in skeletal muscle. Moreover, TFEB was activated after 
LMP in cells, but activation and nuclear localization of TFEB persisted upon VCP 
inactivation or disease mutant expression. Our data identifies VCP as central 
mediator of both lysosomal clearance and biogenesis in skeletal muscle. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="871~932" text="muscle  inactivation of the autophagy essential protein, ATG5" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1409~1426" text="VCP  inactivation" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="608~623" text="skeletal muscle" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="627~637" text="adult mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="861~865" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1279~1294" text="skeletal muscle" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="976~984" text="myofiber" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1171~1179" text="myofiber" context="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>