<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Long noncoding RNA CA7-4 promotes autophagy and apoptosis via sponging MIR877-3P 
and MIR5680 in high glucose-induced vascular endothelial cells.

Vascular endothelial cells (VECs) that form the inner wall of blood vessels can 
be injured by high glucose-induced autophagy and apoptosis. Although the role of 
long noncoding RNA in regulating cell fate has received widespread attention, 
long noncoding RNAs (lncRNAs) that can both regulate autophagy and apoptosis 
need to be discovered. In this study, we identified that a small chemical 
molecule, 3-benzyl-5-([2-nitrophenoxy] methyl)-dihydrofuran-2(3H)-one (3BDO), 
synthesized by us, could inhibit VEC autophagy and apoptosis induced by a high 
concentration of glucose. To find new lncRNAs that regulate autophagy and 
apoptosis in VECs, we performed lncRNA microarray analysis. We found and 
verified an upregulated lncRNA named CA7-4 that was induced by a high 
concentration of glucose could be downregulated by 3BDO most obviously among all 
of the detected lncRNAs. Meanwhile, we investigated the mechanism of CA7-4 in 
regulating VEC autophagy and apoptosis. The results showed that CA7-4 
facilitated endothelial autophagy and apoptosis as a competing endogenous RNA 
(ceRNA) by decoying MIR877-3P and MIR5680. Further study elucidated that 
MIR877-3P could trigger the decrease of CTNNBIP1 (catenin beta interacting 
protein 1) by combining with its 3' UTR and then upregulating CTNNB1 (catenin 
beta 1); MIR5680 inhibited the phosphorylation of AMP-activated protein kinase 
(AMPK) by targeting and decreasing DPP4 (dipeptidyl peptidase 4). Therefore, 
CA7-4, MIR877-3P and MIR5680 represent new signal pathways that regulate VEC 
autophagy and apoptosis under the high-glucose condition.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="654~657" text="VEC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1165~1176" text="endothelial" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="658~667" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="672~681" text="apoptosis" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1177~1186" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1191~1200" text="apoptosis" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="646~653" text="inhibit" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1153~1164" text="facilitated" effect="positive" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>