<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DRD3 (dopamine receptor D3) but not DRD2 activates autophagy through MTORC1 
inhibition preserving protein synthesis.

Growing evidence shows that autophagy is deficient in neurodegenerative and 
psychiatric diseases, and that its induction may have beneficial effects in 
these conditions. However, as autophagy shares signaling pathways with cell 
death and interferes with protein synthesis, prolonged use of autophagy inducers 
available nowadays is considered unwise. The search for novel autophagy inducers 
indicates that DRD2 (dopamine receptor 2)-DRD3 ligands may also activate 
autophagy, though critical aspects of the action mechanisms and effects of 
dopamine ligands on autophagy are still unknown. In order to shed light on this 
issue, DRD2- and DRD3-overexpressing cells and drd2 KO, drd3 KO and wild-type 
mice were treated with the DRD2-DRD3 agonist pramipexole. The results revealed 
that pramipexole induces autophagy through MTOR inhibition and a DRD3-dependent 
but DRD2-independent mechanism. DRD3 activated AMPK followed by inhibitory 
phosphorylation of RPTOR, MTORC1 and RPS6KB1 inhibition and ULK1 activation. 
Interestingly, despite RPS6KB1 inhibition, the activity of RPS6 was maintained 
through activation of the MAPK1/3-RPS6KA pathway, and the activity of MTORC1 
kinase target EIF4EBP1 along with protein synthesis and cell viability, were 
also preserved. This pattern of autophagy through MTORC1 inhibition without 
suppression of protein synthesis, contrasts with that of direct allosteric and 
catalytic MTOR inhibitors and opens up new opportunities for G protein-coupled 
receptor ligands as autophagy inducers in the treatment of neurodegenerative and 
psychiatric diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="752~781" text="DRD2- and DRD3-overexpressing" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="792~799" text="drd2 KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="801~808" text="drd3 KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="851~880" text="DRD2-DRD3 agonist pramipexole" perturbingaction="pharmacological augmentation" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="782~787" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="824~828" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="929~938" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1353~1367" text="cell viability" phenotype="cell survival" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="921~928" text="induces" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1380~1389" text="preserved" effect="no effect" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>