<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[DNA-dependent protein kinase regulates lysosomal AMP-dependent protein kinase 
activation and autophagy.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is a central component of the cytoprotective cellular 
stress response. To enlighten stress-induced autophagy signaling, we screened a 
human kinome siRNA library for regulators of autophagic flux in MCF7 human 
breast carcinoma cells and identified the catalytic subunit of DNA-dependent 
protein kinase PRKDC/DNA-PKcs as a positive regulator of basal and DNA 
damage-induced autophagy. Analysis of autophagy-regulating signaling cascades 
placed PRKDC upstream of the AMP-dependent protein kinase (AMPK) complex and 
ULK1 kinase. In normal culture conditions, PRKDC interacted with the AMPK 
complex and phosphorylated its nucleotide-sensing γ1 subunit PRKAG1/AMPKγ1 at 
Ser192 and Thr284, both events being significantly reduced upon the activation 
of the AMPK complex. Alanine substitutions of PRKDC phosphorylation sites in 
PRKAG1 reduced AMPK complex activation without affecting its nucleotide sensing 
capacity. Instead, the disturbance of PRKDC-mediated phosphorylation of PRKAG1 
inhibited the lysosomal localization of the AMPK complex and its 
starvation-induced association with STK11 (serine/threonine kinase 11). Taken 
together, our data suggest that PRKDC-mediated phosphorylation of PRKAG1 primes 
AMPK complex to the lysosomal activation by STK11 in cancer cells thereby 
linking DNA damage response to autophagy and cellular metabolism.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="905~968" text="Alanine substitutions of PRKDC phosphorylation sites in  PRKAG1" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="331~365" text="MCF7 human  breast carcinoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="508~517" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="465~474" text="regulator" effect="regulates" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>