<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MLKL contributes to Western diet-induced liver injury through inhibiting 
autophagy.

Macroautophagy/autophagy is critical in maintaining cellular functions and 
homeostasis. Dynamic regulation of autophagy is associated with development of 
nonalcoholic fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and nonalcoholic steatohepatitis 
(NASH); however, the mechanisms involved in the regulation of autophagy in 
NAFLD/NASH are not well understood. Here we discuss our recent work identifying 
MLKL as an important nexus between autophagy and necroptosis in models of 
NAFLD/NASH. Mlkl, but not Ripk3, deficiency protects mice from Western 
diet-induced liver injury. Mlkl deficiency also prevents the accumulation of 
SQSTM1/p62 and LC3-II in liver in response to Western diet feeding or challenge 
with the protease inhibitor leupeptin. Western diet increases expression, 
phosphorylation and oligomerization of MLKL. In hepatocytes, palmitic acid (PA) 
induces the expression and translocation of MLKL to autophagosomes prior to the 
plasma membrane. Importantly, Mlkl, but not Ripk3, deficiency prevents the 
inhibition of autophagy by PA or chloroquine in hepatocytes. In contrast, 
overexpression of Mlkl blocks autophagic flux. Importantly, inhibition of 
autophagy by leupeptin or chloroquine triggers MLKL translocation to the plasma 
membrane, suggesting that MLKL is intimately involved in the regulation of 
autophagy under multiple conditions. These data indicate that MLKL contributes 
to Western diet-induced liver injury through inhibition of autophagy and 
induction of necroptosis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="648~663" text="Mlkl deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1168~1190" text="overexpression of Mlkl" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="602~606" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="724~729" text="liver" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="903~914" text="hepatocytes" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1141~1152" text="hepatocytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1107~1116" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1198~1213" text="autophagic flux" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1079~1103" text="prevents the  inhibition" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1191~1197" text="blocks" effect="negative" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>