<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Activation of PPARA-mediated autophagy reduces Alzheimer disease-like pathology 
and cognitive decline in a murine model.

Alzheimer disease (AD) is the most common neurodegenerative disease. An 
imbalance between the production and clearance of Aβ (amyloid beta) is 
considered to be actively involved in AD pathogenesis. Macroautophagy/autophagy 
is a major cellular pathway leading to the removal of aggregated proteins, and 
upregulation of autophagy represents a plausible therapeutic strategy to combat 
overproduction of neurotoxic Aβ. PPARA/PPARα (peroxisome proliferator activated 
receptor alpha) is a transcription factor that regulates genes involved in fatty 
acid metabolism and activates hepatic autophagy. We hypothesized that PPARA 
regulates autophagy in the nervous system and PPARA-mediated autophagy affects 
AD. We found that pharmacological activation of PPARA by the PPARA agonists 
gemfibrozil and Wy14643 induces autophagy in human microglia (HM) cells and U251 
human glioma cells stably expressing the human APP (amyloid beta precursor 
protein) mutant (APP-p.M671L) and this effect is PPARA-dependent. Administration 
of PPARA agonists decreases amyloid pathology and reverses memory deficits and 
anxiety symptoms in APP-PSEN1ΔE9 mice. There is a reduced level of soluble Aβ 
and insoluble Aβ in hippocampus and cortex tissues from APP-PSEN1ΔE9 mice after 
treatment with either gemfibrozil or Wy14643, which promoted the recruitment of 
microglia and astrocytes to the vicinity of Aβ plaques and enhanced 
autophagosome biogenesis. These results indicated that PPARA is an important 
factor regulating autophagy in the clearance of Aβ and suggested gemfibrozil be 
assessed as a possible treatment for AD.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="848~930" text="pharmacological activation of PPARA by the PPARA agonists  gemfibrozil and Wy14643" perturbingaction="pharmacological augmentation" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1008~1094" text="stably expressing the human APP (amyloid beta precursor  protein) mutant (APP-p.M671L)" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1150~1164" text="PPARA agonists" perturbingaction="pharmacological augmentation" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1247~1259" text="APP-PSEN1ΔE9" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1362~1374" text="APP-PSEN1ΔE9" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="952~978" text="human microglia (HM) cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="983~1007" text="U251  human glioma cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1260~1264" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1375~1379" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1326~1337" text="hippocampus" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1342~1356" text="cortex tissues" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="939~948" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="931~938" text="induces" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="pharmacological activation of PPARA by the PPARA agonists  gemfibrozil and Wy14643" contextID="C0" contextText="human microglia (HM) cells" effectID="E0" effectText="induces" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="autophagy" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="pharmacological activation of PPARA by the PPARA agonists  gemfibrozil and Wy14643" effectID="E0" effectText="induces" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="autophagy" contextID="C1" contextText="U251  human glioma cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>