<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Glucose-6-Phosphate Dehydrogenase Is Not Essential for K-Ras-Driven Tumor Growth 
or Metastasis.

The enzyme glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) is a major contributor to 
NADPH production and redox homeostasis and its expression is upregulated and 
correlated with negative patient outcomes in multiple human cancer types. 
Despite these associations, whether G6PD is essential for tumor initiation, 
growth, or metastasis remains unclear. Here, we employ modern genetic tools to 
evaluate the role of G6PD in lung, breast, and colon cancer driven by oncogenic 
K-Ras. Human HCT116 colorectal cancer cells lacking G6PD exhibited metabolic 
indicators of oxidative stress, but developed into subcutaneous xenografts with 
growth comparable with that of wild-type controls. In a genetically engineered 
mouse model of non-small cell lung cancer driven by K-Ras G12D and p53 
deficiency, G6PD knockout did not block formation or proliferation of primary 
lung tumors. In MDA-MB-231-derived human triple-negative breast cancer cells 
implanted as orthotopic xenografts, loss of G6PD modestly decreased primary site 
growth without ablating spontaneous metastasis to the lung and moderately 
impaired the ability of breast cancer cells to colonize the lung when delivered 
via tail vein injection. Thus, in the studied K-Ras tumor models, G6PD was not 
strictly essential for tumorigenesis and at most modestly promoted disease 
progression. SIGNIFICANCE: K-Ras-driven tumors can grow and metastasize even in 
the absence of the oxidative pentose pathway, a main NADPH production route.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="612~624" text="lacking G6PD" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="859~869" text="K-Ras G12D" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="874~889" text="p53  deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="891~904" text="G6PD knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1072~1084" text="loss of G6PD" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="575~611" text="Human HCT116 colorectal cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="783~848" text="genetically engineered  mouse model of non-small cell lung cancer" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="949~969" text="primary  lung tumors" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1217~1236" text="breast cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="974~1034" text="MDA-MB-231-derived human triple-negative breast cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1049~1070" text="orthotopic xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="932~945" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1154~1176" text="metastasis to the lung" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="905~918" text="did not block" effect="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1125~1141" text="without ablating" effect="no effect" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="G6PD knockout" effectID="E0" effectText="did not block" contextID="C2" contextText="primary  lung tumors" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" contextID="C5" contextText="MDA-MB-231-derived human triple-negative breast cancer cells" perturbing_actionID="P4" perturbing_actionText="loss of G6PD" effectID="E1" effectText="without ablating" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="metastasis to the lung" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>