<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Nucleoporin 210 serves a key scaffold for SMARCB1 in liver cancer.

The roles of chromatin remodelers and their underlying mechanisms of action in 
cancer remain unclear. In this study, SMARCB1, known initially as a bona fide 
tumor suppressor gene, was investigated in liver cancer. SMARCB1 was highly 
upregulated in liver cancer patients and was associated with poor prognosis. 
Loss- and gain-of-function studies in liver cells revealed that SMARCB1 loss led 
to reduced cell proliferation, wound healing capacity, and tumor growth in vivo. 
And although upregulated SMARCB1 appeared to contribute to SWItch/Sucrose 
Non-Fermentable (SWI/SNF) complex stability and integrity, it did not act using 
its known pathways antagonism with EZH2 or association between TP53 or AMPK. 
SMARCB1 knockdown induced a mild reduction in global H3K27 acetylation, and 
chromatin immunoprecipitation sequencing of SMARCB1 and acetylated histone H3K27 
antibodies before and after SMARCB1 loss identified Nucleoporin210 (NUP210) as a 
critical target of SMARCB1, which bound its enhancer and changed H3K27Ac 
enrichment and downstream gene expression, particularly cholesterol homeostasis 
and xenobiotic metabolism. Notably, NUP210 was not only a putative tumor 
supporter involved in liver cancer but also acted as a key scaffold for SMARCB1 
and P300 to chromatin. Furthermore, SMARCB1 deficiency conferred sensitivity to 
doxorubicin and P300 inhibitor in liver cancer cells. These findings provide 
insights into mechanisms underlying dysregulation of chromatin remodelers and 
show novel associations between nucleoporins and chromatin remodelers in cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="446~458" text="SMARCB1 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="780~797" text="SMARCB1 knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1367~1385" text="SMARCB1 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="967~979" text="SMARCB1 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="420~431" text="liver cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="475~479" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="536~543" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1446~1464" text="liver cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="480~493" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="523~535" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="467~474" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="SMARCB1 loss" contextID="C1" contextText="cell" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" effectID="E0" effectText="reduced" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="SMARCB1 loss" effectID="E0" effectText="reduced" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="tumor growth" contextID="C2" contextText="in vivo" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>