<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[KIF15-Mediated Stabilization of AR and AR-V7 Contributes to Enzalutamide 
Resistance in Prostate Cancer.

The new generation androgen receptor (AR) pathway inhibitor enzalutamide can 
prolong the survival of patients with metastatic prostate cancer. However, 
resistance to enzalutamide inevitably develops in these patients, and the 
underlying mechanisms of this resistance are not fully defined. Here we 
demonstrate that the kinesin family member 15 (KIF15) contributes to 
enzalutamide resistance by enhancing the AR signaling in prostate cancer cells. 
KIF15 directly bound the N-terminus of AR/AR-V7 and prevented AR/AR-V7 proteins 
from degradation by increasing the protein association of ubiquitin-specific 
protease 14 (USP14) with AR/AR-V7. In turn, the transcriptionally active AR 
stimulated KIF15 expression. KIF15 inhibitors alone or in combination with 
enzalutamide significantly suppressed enzalutamide-resistant prostate cancer 
cell growth and xenograft progression. These findings highlight a key role of 
KIF15 in enabling prostate cancer cells to develop therapy resistance to 
enzalutamide and rationalize KIF15 as a potential therapeutic target. 
SIGNIFICANCE: These findings demonstrate how reciprocal activation between KIF15 
and AR contributes to enzalutamide resistance in prostate cancer and highlights 
cotargeting KIF15 and AR as a therapeutic strategy for these tumors.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="824~840" text="KIF15 inhibitors" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="909~947" text="enzalutamide-resistant prostate cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="965~974" text="xenograft" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="949~960" text="cell growth" phenotype="cell growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="898~908" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="KIF15 inhibitors" contextID="C0" contextText="enzalutamide-resistant prostate cancer" effectID="E0" effectText="suppressed" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>