<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[EZH2-Mediated Downregulation of the Tumor Suppressor DAB2IP Maintains Ovarian 
Cancer Stem Cells.

The majority of women diagnosed with epithelial ovarian cancer eventually 
develop recurrence, which rapidly evolves into chemoresistant disease. 
Persistence of ovarian cancer stem cells (OCSC) at the end of therapy may be 
responsible for emergence of resistant tumors. In this study, we demonstrate 
that in OCSC, the tumor suppressor disabled homolog 2-interacting protein 
(DAB2IP) is silenced by EZH2-mediated H3K27 trimethylation of the DAB2IP 
promoter. CRISPR/Cas9-mediated deletion of DAB2IP in epithelial ovarian cancer 
cell lines upregulated expression of stemness-related genes and induced 
conversion of non-CSC to CSC, while enforced expression of DAB2IP suppressed CSC 
properties. Transcriptomic analysis showed that overexpression of DAB2IP in 
ovarian cancer significantly altered stemness-associated genes and bioinformatic 
analysis revealed WNT signaling as a dominant pathway mediating the CSC 
inhibitory effect of DAB2IP. Specifically, DAB2IP inhibited WNT signaling via 
downregulation of WNT5B, an important stemness inducer. Reverse phase protein 
array further demonstrated activation of noncanonical WNT signaling via C-JUN as 
a downstream target of WNT5B, which was blocked by inhibiting RAC1, a prominent 
regulator of C-JUN activation. Coadministration of EZH2 inhibitor GSK126 and 
RAC1 inhibitor NSC23766 suppressed OCSC survival in vitro and inhibited tumor 
growth and increased platinum sensitivity in vivo. Overall, these data establish 
that DAB2IP suppresses the cancer stem cell phenotype via inhibition of 
WNT5B-induced activation of C-JUN and can be epigenetically silenced by EZH2 in 
OCSC. Targeting the EZH2/DAB2IP/C-JUN axis therefore presents a promising 
strategy to prevent ovarian cancer recurrence and has potential for clinical 
translation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="561~600" text="CRISPR/Cas9-mediated deletion of DAB2IP" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="740~769" text="enforced expression of DAB2IP" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="834~858" text="overexpression of DAB2IP" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1309~1324" text="inhibiting RAC1" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1370~1440" text="Coadministration of EZH2 inhibitor GSK126 and  RAC1 inhibitor NSC23766" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="604~641" text="epithelial ovarian cancer  cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="718~725" text="non-CSC" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="729~732" text="CSC" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="863~877" text="ovarian cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1452~1456" text="OCSC" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1466~1474" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1538~1545" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1489~1502" text="tumor  growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1479~1488" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P4" perturbing_actionText="Coadministration of EZH2 inhibitor GSK126 and  RAC1 inhibitor NSC23766" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="tumor  growth" contextID="C6" contextText="in vivo" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>