<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Blocking SHH/Patched Interaction Triggers Tumor Growth Inhibition through 
Patched-Induced Apoptosis.

The Sonic Hedgehog (SHH) pathway plays a key role in cancer. Alterations of SHH 
canonical signaling, causally linked to tumor progression, have become rational 
targets for cancer therapy. However, Smoothened (SMO) inhibitors have failed to 
show clinical benefit in patients with cancers displaying SHH 
autocrine/paracrine expression. We reported earlier that the SHH receptor 
Patched (PTCH) is a dependence receptor that triggers apoptosis in the absence 
of SHH through a pathway that differs from the canonical one, thus generating a 
state of dependence on SHH for survival. Here, we propose a dual function for 
SHH: its binding to PTCH not only activates the SHH canonical pathway but also 
blocks PTCH-induced apoptosis. Eighty percent, 64%, and 8% of human colon, 
pancreatic, and lung cancer cells, respectively, overexpressed SHH at 
transcriptional and protein levels. In addition, SHH-overexpressing cells 
expressed all the effectors of the PTCH-induced apoptotic pathway. Although the 
canonical pathway remained unchanged, autocrine SHH interference in colon, 
pancreatic, and lung cell lines triggered cell death through PTCH proapoptotic 
signaling. In vivo, SHH interference in colon cancer cell lines decreased 
primary tumor growth and metastasis. Therefore, the antitumor effect associated 
to SHH deprivation, usually thought to be a consequence of the inactivation of 
the canonical SHH pathway, is, at least in part, because of the engagement of 
PTCH proapoptotic activity. Together, these data strongly suggest that 
therapeutic strategies based on the disruption of SHH/PTCH interaction in 
SHH-overexpressing cancers should be explored. SIGNIFICANCE: Sonic 
Hedgehog-overexpressing tumors express PTCH-induced cell death effectors, 
suggesting that this death signaling could be activated as an antitumor 
strategy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1145~1171" text="autocrine SHH interference" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1283~1299" text="SHH interference" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1175~1214" text="colon,  pancreatic, and lung cell lines" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1274~1281" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1303~1326" text="colon cancer cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1225~1235" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1346~1358" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1363~1373" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1215~1224" text="triggered" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1327~1336" text="decreased" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" contextID="C0" contextText="colon,  pancreatic, and lung cell lines" effectID="E0" effectText="triggered" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="autocrine SHH interference" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="SHH interference" contextID="C2" contextText="colon cancer cell lines" effectID="E1" effectText="decreased" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="tumor growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="SHH interference" contextID="C2" contextText="colon cancer cell lines" effectID="E1" effectText="decreased" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="metastasis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>