<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[YAP and AP-1 Cooperate to Initiate Pancreatic Cancer Development from Ductal 
Cells in Mice.

The development of pancreatic cancer is heavily dependent upon the aberrant 
activation of KRAS signaling. Among the downstream targets of KRAS, the 
effectors of the Hippo pathway YAP and TAZ (YAP/TAZ) are crucial during cancer 
initiation and progression. However, little is known about the cell 
type-specific effects of YAP/TAZ on the development of pancreatic cancer. Here 
we clarify the unique consequences of YAP/TAZ activation in the ductal cell 
population of the pancreas by generating mice with pancreatic duct 
cell-specific, inducible knockouts of Lats1 and Lats2, the main kinases upstream 
of YAP/TAZ. Oncogenic activation of YAP by deletion of Lats1/2 in ductal cells 
led to the rapid transformation of the pancreas, which was accompanied by a 
robust increase in the expression of YAP and AP-1 target genes. Pharmacologic 
inhibition of AP-1 activity induced death in Lats1/2 knockout organoids and 
attenuated YAP-dependent transformation of the pancreas in vivo. Both YAP and 
AP-1 were activated during the development of KRAS-dependent cancer in mice and 
human patients with pancreatic ductal adenocarcinoma, suggesting that this 
signaling hub represents an important mediator of pancreatic cancer development 
and progression. Collectively, these data define a YAP-dependent mechanism of 
pancreatic cancer cell development and suggest that inhibition of AP-1 can 
suppress this development.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="743~762" text="deletion of Lats1/2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="921~963" text="Pharmacologic  inhibition of AP-1 activity" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="981~997" text="Lats1/2 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="766~778" text="ductal cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="819~827" text="pancreas" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="998~1007" text="organoids" context="organoid" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1060~1068" text="pancreas" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1069~1076" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="797~811" text="transformation" phenotype="transformation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1038~1052" text="transformation" phenotype="transformation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="780~786" text="led to" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1013~1023" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="deletion of Lats1/2" effectID="E0" effectText="led to" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="transformation" contextID="C1" contextText="pancreas" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Pharmacologic  inhibition of AP-1 activity" effectID="E1" effectText="attenuated" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="transformation" contextID="C3" contextText="pancreas" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>