<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[IRE1α Disruption in Triple-Negative Breast Cancer Cooperates with Antiangiogenic 
Therapy by Reversing ER Stress Adaptation and Remodeling the Tumor 
Microenvironment.

Cancer cells exploit the unfolded protein response (UPR) to mitigate endoplasmic 
reticulum (ER) stress caused by cellular oncogene activation and a hostile tumor 
microenvironment (TME). The key UPR sensor IRE1α resides in the ER and deploys a 
cytoplasmic kinase-endoribonuclease module to activate the transcription factor 
XBP1s, which facilitates ER-mediated protein folding. Studies of triple-negative 
breast cancer (TNBC)-a highly aggressive malignancy with a dismal posttreatment 
prognosis-implicate XBP1s in promoting tumor vascularization and progression. 
However, it remains unknown whether IRE1α adapts the ER in TNBC cells and 
modulates their TME, and whether IRE1α inhibition can enhance antiangiogenic 
therapy-previously found to be ineffective in patients with TNBC. To gauge IRE1α 
function, we defined an XBP1s-dependent gene signature, which revealed 
significant IRE1α pathway activation in multiple solid cancers, including TNBC. 
IRE1α knockout in TNBC cells markedly reversed substantial ultrastructural 
expansion of their ER upon growth in vivo. IRE1α disruption also led to 
significant remodeling of the cellular TME, increasing pericyte numbers while 
decreasing cancer-associated fibroblasts and myeloid-derived suppressor cells. 
Pharmacologic IRE1α kinase inhibition strongly attenuated growth of cell 
line-based and patient-derived TNBC xenografts in mice and synergized with 
anti-VEGFA treatment to cause tumor stasis or regression. Thus, TNBC cells 
critically rely on IRE1α to adapt their ER to in vivo stress and to adjust the 
TME to facilitate malignant growth. TNBC reliance on IRE1α is an important 
vulnerability that can be uniquely exploited in combination with antiangiogenic 
therapy as a promising new biologic approach to combat this lethal disease. 
SIGNIFICANCE: Pharmacologic IRE1α kinase inhibition reverses ultrastructural 
distension of the ER, normalizes the tumor vasculature, and remodels the 
cellular TME, attenuating TNBC growth in mice.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1126~1140" text="IRE1α knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1434~1471" text="Pharmacologic IRE1α kinase inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1144~1154" text="TNBC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1236~1243" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1330~1338" text="pericyte" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1365~1394" text="cancer-associated fibroblasts" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1399~1431" text="myeloid-derived suppressor cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1502~1554" text="cell  line-based and patient-derived TNBC xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1558~1562" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1614~1640" text="tumor stasis or regression" phenotype="tumour regression" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1608~1613" text="cause" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Pharmacologic IRE1α kinase inhibition" contextID="C5" contextText="cell  line-based and patient-derived TNBC xenografts" effectID="E0" effectText="cause" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="tumor stasis or regression" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>