<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A ZNRF3-dependent Wnt/β-catenin signaling gradient is required for adrenal 
homeostasis.

Spatiotemporal control of Wnt signaling is essential for the development and 
homeostasis of many tissues. The transmembrane E3 ubiquitin ligases ZNRF3 (zinc 
and ring finger 3) and RNF43 (ring finger protein 43) antagonize Wnt signaling 
by promoting degradation of frizzled receptors. ZNRF3 and RNF43 are frequently 
inactivated in human cancer, but the molecular and therapeutic implications 
remain unclear. Here, we demonstrate that adrenocortical-specific loss of ZNRF3, 
but not RNF43, results in adrenal hyperplasia that depends on Porcupine-mediated 
Wnt ligand secretion. Furthermore, we discovered a Wnt/β-catenin signaling 
gradient in the adrenal cortex that is disrupted upon loss of ZNRF3. Unlike 
β-catenin gain-of-function models, which induce high Wnt/β-catenin activation 
and expansion of the peripheral cortex, ZNRF3 loss triggers activation of 
moderate-level Wnt/β-catenin signaling that drives proliferative expansion of 
only the histologically and functionally distinct inner cortex. Genetically 
reducing β-catenin dosage significantly reverses the ZNRF3-deficient phenotype. 
Thus, homeostatic maintenance of the adrenal cortex is dependent on varying 
levels of Wnt/β-catenin activation, which is regulated by ZNRF3.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="528~565" text="adrenocortical-specific loss of ZNRF3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="780~793" text="loss of ZNRF3" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="922~932" text="ZNRF3 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1166~1181" text="ZNRF3-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1086~1098" text="inner cortex" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1008~1031" text="proliferative expansion" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1001~1007" text="drives" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="ZNRF3 loss" effectID="E0" effectText="drives" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferative expansion" contextID="C0" contextText="inner cortex" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>