<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Mutant IDH1 regulates the tumor-associated immune system in gliomas.

Gliomas harboring mutations in isocitrate dehydrogenase 1/2 (IDH1/2) have the 
CpG island methylator phenotype (CIMP) and significantly longer patient survival 
time than wild-type IDH1/2 (wtIDH1/2) tumors. Although there are many factors 
underlying the differences in survival between these two tumor types, 
immune-related differences in cell content are potentially important 
contributors. In order to investigate the role of IDH mutations in immune 
response, we created a syngeneic pair mouse model for mutant IDH1 (muIDH1) and 
wtIDH1 gliomas and demonstrated that muIDH1 mice showed many molecular and 
clinical similarities to muIDH1 human gliomas, including a 100-fold higher 
concentration of 2-hydroxygluratate (2-HG), longer survival time, and higher CpG 
methylation compared with wtIDH1. Also, we showed that IDH1 mutations caused 
down-regulation of leukocyte chemotaxis, resulting in repression of the 
tumor-associated immune system. Given that significant infiltration of immune 
cells such as macrophages, microglia, monocytes, and neutrophils is linked to 
poor prognosis in many cancer types, these reduced immune infiltrates in muIDH1 
glioma tumors may contribute in part to the differences in aggressiveness of the 
two glioma types.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="580~600" text="mutant IDH1 (muIDH1)" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="643~649" text="muIDH1" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="895~909" text="IDH1 mutations" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="564~575" text="mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="613~620" text="gliomas" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="650~654" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="937~946" text="leukocyte" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="947~957" text="chemotaxis" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="918~933" text="down-regulation" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="IDH1 mutations" effectID="E0" effectText="down-regulation" contextID="C3" contextText="leukocyte" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="chemotaxis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>