<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[A RhoA-YAP-c-Myc signaling axis promotes the development of polycystic kidney 
disease.

Autosomal dominant polycystic kidney disease (ADPKD) is an inherited disorder 
caused by mutations in PKD1 or PKD2 and affects one in 500-1000 humans. Limited 
treatment is currently available for ADPKD. Here we identify the Hippo signaling 
effector YAP and its transcriptional target, c-Myc, as promoters of cystic 
kidney pathogenesis. While transgenic overexpression of YAP promotes 
proliferation and tubule dilation in mouse kidneys, loss of YAP/TAZ or c-Myc 
suppresses cystogenesis in a mouse ADPKD model resulting from Pkd1 deficiency. 
Through a comprehensive kinase inhibitor screen based on a novel 
three-dimensional (3D) culture of Pkd1 mutant mouse kidney cells, we identified 
a signaling pathway involving the RhoGEF (guanine nucleotide exchange factor) 
LARG, the small GTPase RhoA, and the RhoA effector Rho-associated kinase (ROCK) 
as a critical signaling module between PKD1 and YAP. Further corroborating its 
physiological importance, inhibition of RhoA signaling suppresses cystogenesis 
in 3D culture of Pkd1 mutant kidney cells as well as Pkd1 mutant mouse kidneys 
in vivo. Taken together, our findings implicate the RhoA-YAP-c-Myc signaling 
axis as a critical mediator and potential drug target in ADPKD.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="434~466" text="transgenic overexpression of YAP" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="529~553" text="loss of YAP/TAZ or c-Myc" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="617~632" text="Pkd1 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="735~746" text="Pkd1 mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1119~1130" text="Pkd1 mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1155~1166" text="Pkd1 mutant" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="514~527" text="mouse kidneys" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="584~601" text="mouse ADPKD model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="747~765" text="mouse kidney cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1105~1115" text="3D culture" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1131~1143" text="kidney cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1167~1180" text="mouse kidneys" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="1182~1189" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="477~490" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="467~475" text="promotes" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="transgenic overexpression of YAP" contextID="C0" contextText="mouse kidneys" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" effectID="E0" effectText="promotes" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>