<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RAD52 and SLX4 act nonepistatically to ensure telomere stability during 
alternative telomere lengthening.

Approximately 15% of cancers use homologous recombination for alternative 
lengthening of telomeres (ALT). How the initiating genomic lesions invoke 
homology-directed telomere synthesis remains enigmatic. Here, we show that 
distinct dependencies exist for telomere synthesis in response to replication 
stress or DNA double-strand breaks (DSBs). RAD52 deficiency reduced spontaneous 
telomeric DNA synthesis and replication stress-associated recombination in G2, 
concomitant with telomere shortening and damage. However, viability and 
proliferation remained unaffected, suggesting that alternative telomere 
recombination mechanisms compensate in the absence of RAD52. In agreement, RAD52 
was dispensable for DSB-induced telomere synthesis. Moreover, a targeted CRISPR 
screen revealed that loss of the structure-specific endonuclease scaffold SLX4 
reduced the proliferation of RAD52-null ALT cells. While SLX4 was dispensable 
for RAD52-mediated ALT telomere synthesis in G2, combined SLX4 and RAD52 loss 
resulted in elevated telomere loss, unresolved telomere recombination 
intermediates, and mitotic infidelity. These findings establish that RAD52 and 
SLX4 mediate distinct postreplicative DNA repair processes that maintain ALT 
telomere stability and cancer cell viability.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="456~472" text="RAD52 deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="904~961" text="loss of the structure-specific endonuclease scaffold SLX4" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="992~1002" text="RAD52-null" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1091~1119" text="combined SLX4 and RAD52 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1003~1012" text="ALT cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="647~660" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="975~988" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="670~680" text="unaffected" effect="no effect" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="963~970" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="loss of the structure-specific endonuclease scaffold SLX4" contextID="C0" contextText="ALT cells" effectID="E1" effectText="reduced" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>