<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[CSF1R signaling is a regulator of pathogenesis in progressive MS.

Microglia serve as the innate immune cells of the central nervous system (CNS) 
by providing continuous surveillance of the CNS microenvironment and initiating 
defense mechanisms to protect CNS tissue. Upon injury, microglia transition into 
an activated state altering their transcriptional profile, transforming their 
morphology, and producing pro-inflammatory cytokines. These activated microglia 
initially serve a beneficial role, but their continued activation drives 
neuroinflammation and neurodegeneration. Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a chronic, 
inflammatory, demyelinating disease of the CNS, and activated microglia and 
macrophages play a significant role in mediating disease pathophysiology and 
progression. Colony-stimulating factor-1 receptor (CSF1R) and its ligand CSF1 
are elevated in CNS tissue derived from MS patients. We performed a large-scale 
RNA-sequencing experiment and identified CSF1R as a key node of disease 
progression in a mouse model of progressive MS. We hypothesized that modulating 
microglia and infiltrating macrophages through the inhibition of CSF1R will 
attenuate deleterious CNS inflammation and reduce subsequent demyelination and 
neurodegeneration. To test this hypothesis, we generated a novel potent and 
selective small-molecule CSF1R inhibitor (sCSF1Rinh) for preclinical testing. 
sCSF1Rinh blocked receptor phosphorylation and downstream signaling in both 
microglia and macrophages and altered cellular functions including 
proliferation, survival, and cytokine production. In vivo, CSF1R inhibition with 
sCSF1Rinh attenuated neuroinflammation and reduced microglial proliferation in a 
murine acute LPS model. Furthermore, the sCSF1Rinh attenuated a 
disease-associated microglial phenotype and blocked both axonal damage and 
neurological impairments in an experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis (EAE) 
model of MS. While previous studies have focused on microglial depletion 
following CSF1R inhibition, our data clearly show that signaling downstream of 
this receptor can be beneficially modulated in the context of CNS injury. 
Together, these data suggest that CSF1R inhibition can reduce deleterious 
microglial proliferation and modulate microglial phenotypes during 
neuroinflammatory pathogenesis, particularly in progressive MS.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1406~1415" text="sCSF1Rinh" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1610~1642" text="CSF1R inhibition with  sCSF1Rinh" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1756~1765" text="sCSF1Rinh" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1483~1492" text="microglia" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1497~1508" text="macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1601~1608" text="In vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1551~1564" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1695~1708" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1513~1520" text="altered" effect="regulates" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1676~1683" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="sCSF1Rinh" contextID="C0" contextText="microglia" effectID="E0" effectText="altered" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="sCSF1Rinh" contextID="C1" contextText="macrophages" effectID="E0" effectText="altered" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="CSF1R inhibition with  sCSF1Rinh" contextID="C2" contextText="In vivo" effectID="E1" effectText="reduced" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>