<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SKIL facilitates tumorigenesis and immune escape of NSCLC via upregulating 
TAZ/autophagy axis.

Immune escape is an important mechanism in tumorigenesis. The aim of this study 
was to investigate roles of SKIL in tumorigenesis and immune escape of 
non-small-cell lung cancer (NSCLC). SKIL expression levels in NSCLC cell line, 
clinical sample, and adjacent normal tissue were measured by quantitative PCR, 
western blot, or immunohistochemistry. Lentivirus was used to 
overexpress/silence SKIL or TAZ expression. Malignant phenotypes of NSCLC cells 
were evaluated by colony formation, transwell, and MTT assays, and in xenograft 
mice model. Syngeneic mice model and flow cytometry were used to evaluate T cell 
infiltration. Quantitative PCR and western blot were applied to evaluate 
relevant mRNA and protein levels, respectively. Co-immunoprecipitation was 
applied to unveil the interaction between SKIL and TAZ. SKIL expression was 
higher in NSCLC tissue compared to adjacent normal tissue. Silencing of SKIL 
inhibited malignant phenotypes of NSCLC cells and promoted T cell infiltration. 
SKIL-knockdown inhibited autophagy and activated the STING pathway in NSCLC 
cells through down-regulation of TAZ. Silencing of TAZ cancelled the effects of 
SKIL overexpression on malignant phenotypes and autophagy of NSCLC cells. 
Inhibition of autophagy reversed the effects of SKIL/TAZ overexpression on the 
STING pathway. In conclusion, SKIL promoted tumorigenesis and immune escape of 
NSCLC cells through upregulation of TAZ/autophagy axis and inhibition on 
downstream STING pathway.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1003~1020" text="Silencing of SKIL" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1103~1117" text="SKIL-knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1218~1234" text="Silencing of TAZ" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1261~1280" text="SKIL overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1384~1407" text="SKIL/TAZ overexpression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1056~1067" text="NSCLC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1173~1185" text="NSCLC  cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1322~1333" text="NSCLC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1128~1137" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1309~1318" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1350~1359" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1118~1127" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1336~1346" text="Inhibition" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="SKIL-knockdown" effectID="E1" effectText="inhibited" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="autophagy" contextID="C1" contextText="NSCLC  cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>