<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MAPT/Tau accumulation represses autophagy flux by disrupting IST1-regulated 
ESCRT-III complex formation: a vicious cycle in Alzheimer neurodegeneration.

Macroautophagy/autophagy deficit induces intracellular MAPT/tau accumulation, 
the hallmark pathology in Alzheimer disease (AD) and other tauopathies; however, 
the reverse role of MAPT accumulation in autophagy and neurodegeneration is not 
clear. Here, we found that overexpression of human wild-type full-length MAPT, 
which models MAPT pathologies as seen in sporadic AD patients, induced autophagy 
deficits via repression of autophagosome-lysosome fusion leading to 
significantly increased LC3 (microtubule-associated protein 1 light chain 3)-II 
and SQSTM1/p62 (sequestosome 1) protein levels with autophagosome accumulation. 
At the molecular level, intracellular MAPT aggregation inhibited expression of 
IST1 (IST1 factor associated with ESCRT-III), a positive modulator for the 
formation of ESCRT (the Endosomal Sorting Complex Required for Transport) 
complex that is required for autophagosome-lysosome fusion. Upregulating IST1 in 
human MAPT transgenic mice attenuated autophagy deficit with reduced MAPT 
aggregation and ameliorated synaptic plasticity and cognitive functions, while 
downregulating IST1 per se induced autophagy deficit with impaired synapse and 
cognitive function in naïve mice. IST1 can facilitate association of CHMP2B 
(charged multivesicular body protein 2B) and CHMP4B/SNF7-2 to form ESCRT-III 
complex, while lack of IST1 impeded the complex formation. Finally, we 
demonstrate that MAPT accumulation suppresses IST1 transcription with the 
mechanisms involving the ANP32A-regulated mask of histone acetylation. Our 
findings suggest that the AD-like MAPT accumulation can repress 
autophagosome-lysosome fusion by deregulating ANP32A-INHAT-IST1-ESCRT-III 
pathway, which also reveals a vicious cycle of MAPT accumulation and autophagy 
deficit in the chronic course of AD neurodegeneration.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="424~474" text="overexpression of human wild-type full-length MAPT" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1081~1098" text="Upregulating IST1" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1103~1124" text="human MAPT transgenic" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1258~1277" text="downregulating IST1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1125~1129" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1366~1370" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1141~1150" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="548~557" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1293~1302" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1130~1140" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1151~1158" text="deficit" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="540~547" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="559~567" text="deficits" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1285~1292" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1303~1310" text="deficit" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="downregulating IST1" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="autophagy" effectID="E5" effectText="deficit" contextID="C2" contextText="mice" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>