<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Legumain promotes tubular ferroptosis by facilitating chaperone-mediated 
autophagy of GPX4 in AKI.

Legumain is required for maintenance of normal kidney homeostasis. However, its 
role in acute kidney injury (AKI) is still unclear. Here, we induced AKI by 
bilateral ischemia-reperfusion injury (IRI) of renal arteries or folic acid in 
lgmnWT and lgmnKO mice. We assessed serum creatinine, blood urea nitrogen, 
histological indexes of tubular injury, and expression of KIM-1 and NGAL. 
Inflammatory infiltration was evaluated by immunohistological staining of CD3 
and F4/80, and expression of TNF-α, CCL-2, IL-33, and IL-1α. Ferroptosis was 
evaluated by Acsl4, Cox-2, reactive oxygen species (ROS) indexes H2DCFDA and 
DHE, MDA and glutathione peroxidase 4 (GPX4). We induced ferroptosis by hypoxia 
or erastin in primary mouse renal tubular epithelial cells (mRTECs). Cellular 
survival, Acsl4, Cox-2, LDH release, ROS, and MDA levels were measured. We 
analyzed the degradation of GPX4 through inhibition of proteasomes or autophagy. 
Lysosomal GPX4 was assessed to determine GPX4 degradation pathway. 
Immunoprecipitation (IP) was used to determine the interactions between 
legumain, GPX4, HSC70, and HSP90. For tentative treatment, RR-11a was 
administrated intraperitoneally to a mouse model of IRI-induced AKI. Our results 
showed that legumain deficiency attenuated acute tubular injury, inflammation, 
and ferroptosis in either IRI or folic acid-induced AKI model. Ferroptosis 
induced by hypoxia or erastin was dampened in lgmnKO mRTECs compared with lgmnWT 
control. Deficiency of legumain prevented chaperone-mediated autophagy of GPX4. 
Results of IP suggested interactions between legumain, HSC70, HSP90, and GPX4. 
Administration of RR-11a ameliorated ferroptosis and renal injury in the AKI 
model. Together, our data indicate that legumain promotes chaperone-mediated 
autophagy of GPX4 therefore facilitates tubular ferroptosis in AKI.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1539~1545" text="lgmnKO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="820~873" text="primary mouse renal tubular epithelial cells (mRTECs)" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1292~1303" text="mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1546~1552" text="mRTECs" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="782~793" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1421~1432" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1480~1491" text="Ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1636~1645" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="1773~1784" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="774~781" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1369~1379" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1493~1500" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1527~1535" text="dampened" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1607~1616" text="prevented" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E5" spans="1761~1772" text="ameliorated" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="lgmnKO" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="Ferroptosis" effectID="E3" effectText="dampened" contextID="C2" contextText="mRTECs" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>