<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ATRIP protects progenitor cells against DNA damage in vivo.

The maintenance of genomic stability during the cell cycle of progenitor cells 
is essential for the faithful transmission of genetic information. Mutations in 
genes that ensure genome stability lead to human developmental syndromes. 
Mutations in Ataxia Telangiectasia and Rad3-related (ATR) or in ATR-interacting 
protein (ATRIP) lead to Seckel syndrome, which is characterized by developmental 
malformations and short life expectancy. While the roles of ATR in replicative 
stress response and chromosomal segregation are well established, it is unknown 
how ATRIP contributes to maintaining genomic stability in progenitor cells in 
vivo. Here, we generated the first mouse model to investigate ATRIP function. 
Conditional inactivation of Atrip in progenitor cells of the CNS and eye led to 
microcephaly, microphthalmia and postnatal lethality. To understand the 
mechanisms underlying these malformations, we used lens progenitor cells as a 
model and found that ATRIP loss promotes replicative stress and TP53-dependent 
cell death. Trp53 inactivation in Atrip-deficient progenitor cells rescued 
apoptosis, but increased mitotic DNA damage and mitotic defects. Our findings 
demonstrate an essential role of ATRIP in preventing DNA damage accumulation 
during unchallenged replication.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="779~812" text="Conditional inactivation of Atrip" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1033~1043" text="ATRIP loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1104~1122" text="Trp53 inactivation" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1126~1141" text="Atrip-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="816~851" text="progenitor cells of the CNS and eye" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="984~1005" text="lens progenitor cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1142~1158" text="progenitor cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1092~1102" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1168~1177" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1044~1052" text="promotes" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1159~1166" text="rescued" effect="rescues" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ATRIP loss" contextID="C1" contextText="lens progenitor cells" effectID="E0" effectText="promotes" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="Trp53 inactivation" contextID="C2" contextText="progenitor cells" effectID="E1" effectText="rescued" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>