<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[RING-finger protein 166 plays a novel pro-apoptotic role in neurotoxin-induced 
neurodegeneration via ubiquitination of XIAP.

The dopaminergic neurotoxin, 6-hydroxydopamine (6-OHDA), has been widely 
utilized to establish experimental models of Parkinson disease and to reveal the 
critical molecules and pathway underlying neuronal death. The profile of gene 
expression changes following 6-OHDA treatment of MN9D dopaminergic neuronal 
cells was investigated using a TwinChip Mouse-7.4K microarray. Functional 
clustering of altered sets of genes identified RING-finger protein 166 (RNF166). 
RNF166 is composed of an N-terminal RING domain and C-terminal ubiquitin 
interaction motif. RNF166 localized in the cytosol and nucleus. At the tissue 
level, RNF166 was widely expressed in the central nervous system and peripheral 
organs. In the cerebral cortex, its expression decreased over time. In certain 
conditions, overexpression of RNF166 accelerates the naturally occurring 
neuronal death and 6-OHDA-induced MN9D cell death as determined by TUNEL and 
annexin-V staining, and caspase activation. Consequently, 6-OHDA-induced 
apoptotic cell death was attenuated in RNF166-knockdown cells. In an attempt to 
elucidate the mechanism underlying this pro-apoptotic activity, binding protein 
profiles were assessed using the yeast two-hybrid system. Among several 
potential binding candidates, RNF166 was shown to interact with the cytoplasmic 
X-linked inhibitor of apoptosis (XIAP), inducing ubiquitin-dependent degradation 
of XIAP and eventually accelerating caspase activation following 6-OHDA 
treatment. RNF166's interaction with and resulting inhibition of the XIAP 
anti-caspase activity was further enhanced by XIAP-associated factor-1 (XAF-1). 
Consequently, depletion of RNF166 suppressed 6-OHDA-induced caspase activation 
and apoptotic cell death, which was reversed by XIAP knockdown. In summary, our 
data suggest that RNF166, a novel E3 ligase, plays a pro-apoptotic role via 
caspase activation in neuronal cells.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="922~946" text="overexpression of RNF166" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1175~1191" text="RNF166-knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1777~1796" text="depletion of RNF166" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1891~1905" text="XIAP knockdown" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="411~444" text="MN9D dopaminergic neuronal  cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1018~1022" text="MN9D" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1192~1197" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1023~1033" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1136~1156" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1847~1867" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="947~958" text="accelerates" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1127~1134" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1161~1171" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1797~1807" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="overexpression of RNF166" contextID="C1" contextText="MN9D" effectID="E0" effectText="accelerates" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="RNF166-knockdown" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="apoptotic cell death" effectID="E2" effectText="attenuated" contextID="C2" contextText="cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>