<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[P53-regulated miR-320a targets PDL1 and is downregulated in malignant 
mesothelioma.

Malignant pleural mesothelioma (MPM) is an aggressive cancer, related to 
asbestos exposure, which has a dismal prognosis. MPM diagnosis is late and often 
challenging, suggesting the need to identify more reliable molecular biomarkers. 
Here, we set out to identify differentially expressed miRNAs in epithelioid, 
biphasic, and sarcomatoid MPMs versus normal mesothelium and explored specific 
miRNA contribution to mesothelial tumorigenesis. We screened an LNA™-based 
miRNA-microrray with 14 formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded (FFPE) MPMs and 6 
normal controls. Through real-time qRT-PCR we extended the analysis of a miRNA 
subset and further investigated miR-320a role through state-of-the-art 
techniques. We identified 16 upregulated and 32 downregulated miRNAs in MPMs 
versus normal tissue, including the previously identified potential biomarkers 
miR-21, miR-126, miR-143, miR-145. We showed in an extended series that miR-145, 
miR-10b, and miR-320a levels can discriminate tumor versus controls with high 
specificity and sensitivity. We focused on miR-320a because other family members 
were found downregulated in MPMs. However, stable miR-320a ectopic expression 
induced higher proliferation and migration ability, whereas miR-320a silencing 
reduced these processes, not supporting a classic tumor-suppressor role in MPM 
cell lines. Among putative targets, we found that miR-320a binds the 3'-UTR of 
the immune inhibitory receptor ligand PDL1 and, consistently, miR-320a 
modulation affects PDL1 levels in MPM cells. Finally, we showed that p53 
over-expression induces the upregulation of miR-320a, along with miR-200a and 
miR-34a, both known to target PDL1, and reduces PDL1 levels in MPM cells. Our 
data suggest that PDL1 expression might be due to a defective p53-regulated 
miRNA response, which could contribute to MPM immune evasion or tumorigenesis 
through tumor-intrinsic roles.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1230~1264" text="stable miR-320a ectopic expression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1326~1344" text="miR-320a silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1647~1667" text="p53  over-expression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1421~1436" text="MPM  cell lines" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1612~1621" text="MPM cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1794~1803" text="MPM cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1281~1294" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1299~1308" text="migration" phenotype="migration" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1266~1273" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="stable miR-320a ectopic expression" effectID="E0" effectText="induced" contextID="C0" contextText="MPM  cell lines" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="stable miR-320a ectopic expression" effectID="E0" effectText="induced" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="migration" contextID="C0" contextText="MPM  cell lines" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>