<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[m(6)A mRNA methylation controls autophagy and adipogenesis by targeting Atg5 and 
Atg7.

N: 6-methyladenosine (m6A), the most abundant internal modification on mRNAs in 
eukaryotes, play roles in adipogenesis. However, the underlying mechanism 
remains largely unclear. Here, we show that m6A plays a critical role in 
regulating macroautophagy/autophagy and adipogenesis through targeting Atg5 and 
Atg7. Mechanistically, knockdown of FTO, a well-known m6A demethylase, decreased 
the expression of ATG5 and ATG7, leading to attenuation of autophagosome 
formation, thereby inhibiting autophagy and adipogenesis. We proved that FTO 
directly targeted Atg5 and Atg7 transcripts and mediated their expression in an 
m6A-dependent manner. Further study identified that Atg5 and Atg7 were the 
targets of YTHDF2 (YTH N6-methyladenosine RNA binding protein 2). Upon FTO 
silencing, Atg5 and Atg7 transcripts with higher m6A levels were captured by 
YTHDF2, which resulted in mRNA degradation and reduction of protein expression, 
thus alleviating autophagy and adipogenesis. Furthermore, we generated an 
adipose-selective fto knockout mouse and find that FTO deficiency decreased 
white fat mass and impairs ATG5- and ATG7-dependent autophagy in vivo. Together, 
these findings unveil the functional importance of the m6A methylation machinery 
in autophagy and adipogenesis regulation, which expands our understanding of 
such interplay that is essential for development of therapeutic strategies in 
the prevention and treatment of obesity.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="423~439" text="knockdown of FTO" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="862~876" text="FTO  silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1152~1166" text="FTO deficiency" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1101~1131" text="adipose-selective fto knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1132~1137" text="mouse" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1240~1247" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="586~595" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1043~1052" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1230~1239" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="575~585" text="inhibiting" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1031~1042" text="alleviating" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1197~1204" text="impairs" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="FTO deficiency" contextID="C2" contextText="in vivo" effectID="E2" effectText="impairs" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="autophagy" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="adipose-selective fto knockout" contextID="C1" contextText="mouse" effectID="E2" effectText="impairs" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>