<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[IGF2BP2 regulates DANCR by serving as an N6-methyladenosine reader.

The major function of Insulin-like growth factor 2 mRNA-binding protein 2 
(IGF2BP2) is to regulate cell metabolism. However, emerging evidence indicates 
that IGF2BP2 plays a role in cancer, but the underlying mechanism is largely 
unknown. Here we showed that upregulation of IGF2BP2 is associated with poor 
outcomes of pancreatic cancer patients and suppression of IGF2BP2 inhibits cell 
proliferation. We further showed that IGF2BP2 regulates lncRNA DANCR. Ectopic 
expression IGF2BP2 enhances, whereas knockdown (KD) or knockout (KO) of IGF2BP2 
suppresses DANCR expression. Moreover, in vivo RNA precipitation and reciprocal 
RNA immunoprecipitation revealed that IGF2BP2 interacts with DANCR. DANCR 
promotes cell proliferation and stemness-like properties. Experiments with 
xenograft models revealed that while ectopic expression of DANCR promotes, DANCR 
KO suppresses tumor growth. Mechanistically, DANCR is modified at 
N6-methyladenosine (m6A) and mutagenesis assay identified that adenosine at 664 
of DANCR is critical to the interaction between IGF2BP2 and DANCR where IGF2BP2 
serves a reader for m6A modified DANCR and stabilizes DANCR RNA. Together, these 
results suggest that DANCR is a novel target for IGF2BP2 through m6A 
modification, and IGF2BP2 and DANCR work together to promote cancer 
stemness-like properties and pancreatic cancer pathogenesis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="531~558" text="Ectopic  expression IGF2BP2" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="595~619" text="knockout (KO) of IGF2BP2" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="423~445" text="suppression of IGF2BP2" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="890~917" text="ectopic expression of DANCR" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="928~937" text="DANCR  KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="455~459" text="cell" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="853~869" text="xenograft models" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="461~474" text="proliferation" phenotype="proliferation" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="949~961" text="tumor growth" phenotype="tumour growth" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="446~454" text="inhibits" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="918~926" text="promotes" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="938~948" text="suppresses" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" effectID="E0" effectText="inhibits" contextID="C0" contextText="cell" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="proliferation" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="suppression of IGF2BP2" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="ectopic expression of DANCR" effectID="E1" effectText="promotes" contextID="C2" contextText="xenograft models" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="tumor growth" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P4" perturbing_actionText="DANCR  KO" contextID="C2" contextText="xenograft models" effectID="E2" effectText="suppresses" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="tumor growth" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>