<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Kinome screen of ferroptosis reveals a novel role of ATM in regulating iron 
metabolism.

Ferroptosis is a specialized iron-dependent cell death that is associated with 
lethal lipid peroxidation. Modulation of ferroptosis may have therapeutic 
potential since it has been implicated in various human diseases as well as 
potential antitumor activities. However, much remains unknown about the 
underlying mechanisms and genetic determinants of ferroptosis. Given the 
critical role of kinases in most biological processes and the availability of 
various kinase inhibitors, we sought to systemically identify kinases essential 
for ferroptosis. We performed a forward genetic-based kinome screen against 
ferroptosis in MDA-MB-231 cells triggered by cystine deprivation. This screen 
identified 34 essential kinases involved in TNFα and NF-kB signaling. 
Unexpectedly, the DNA damage response serine/threonine kinase ATM (mutated in 
Ataxia-Telangiectasia) was found to be essential for ferroptosis. The 
pharmacological or genetic inhibition of ATM consistently rescued multiple 
cancer cells from ferroptosis triggered by cystine deprivation or erastin. 
Instead of the canonical DNA damage pathways, ATM inhibition rescued ferroptosis 
by increasing the expression of iron regulators involved in iron storage 
(ferritin heavy and light chain, FTH1 and FTL) and export (ferroportin, FPN1). 
The coordinated changes of these iron regulators during ATM inhibition resulted 
in a lowering of labile iron and prevented the iron-dependent ferroptosis. 
Furthermore, we found that ATM inhibition enhanced the nuclear translocation of 
metal-regulatory transcription factor 1 (MTF1), responsible for regulating 
expression of Ferritin/FPN1 and ferroptosis protection. Genetic depletion of 
MTF-1 abolished the regulation of iron-regulatory elements by ATM and 
resensitized the cells to ferroptosis. Together, we have identified an 
unexpected ATM-MTF1-Ferritin/FPN1 regulatory axis as novel determinants of 
ferroptosis through regulating labile iron levels.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1025~1050" text="genetic inhibition of ATM" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1204~1218" text="ATM inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1578~1592" text="ATM inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1764~1791" text="Genetic depletion of  MTF-1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1450~1464" text="ATM inhibition" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="721~737" text="MDA-MB-231 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1082~1094" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1874~1879" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1100~1111" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1227~1238" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1537~1548" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1883~1894" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH4" spans="988~999" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1064~1071" text="rescued" effect="rescues" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1112~1121" text="triggered" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1219~1226" text="rescued" effect="rescues" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1508~1517" text="prevented" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1857~1869" text="resensitized" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="genetic inhibition of ATM" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="ferroptosis" effectID="E0" effectText="rescued" contextID="C1" contextText="cancer cells" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="Genetic depletion of  MTF-1" effectID="E4" effectText="resensitized" contextID="C2" contextText="cells" phenotypeID="PH3" phenotypeText="ferroptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>