<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TAK1 suppresses RIPK1-dependent cell death and is associated with disease 
progression in melanoma.

Melanoma cells are highly resistant to conventional genotoxic agents, and 
BRAFV600/MEK-targeted therapies as well as immunotherapies frequently remain 
inefficient. Alternative means to treat melanoma, in particular through the 
induction of programmed cell death modalities such as apoptosis or necroptosis, 
therefore still need to be explored. Here, we report that melanoma cell lines 
expressing notable amounts of RIPK1, RIPK3 and MLKL, the key players of 
necroptosis signal transduction, fail to execute necroptotic cell death. 
Interestingly, the activity of transforming growth factor β-activated kinase 1 
(TAK1) appears to prevent RIPK1 from contributing to cell death induction, since 
TAK1 inhibition by (5Z)-7-Oxozeaenol, deletion of MAP3K7 or the expression of 
inactive TAK1 were sufficient to sensitize melanoma cells to RIPK1-dependent 
cell death in response to TNFα or TRAIL based combination treatments. However, 
cell death was executed exclusively by apoptosis, even when RIPK3 expression was 
high. In addition, TAK1 inhibitor (5Z)-7-Oxozeaenol suppressed intrinsic or 
treatment-induced pro-survival signaling as well as the secretion of cytokines 
and soluble factors associated with melanoma disease progression. 
Correspondingly, elevated expression of TAK1 correlates with reduced disease 
free survival in patients diagnosed with primary melanoma. Overall, our results 
therefore demonstrate that TAK1 suppresses the susceptibility to RIPK1-dependent 
cell death and that high expression of TAK1 indicates an increased risk for 
disease progression in melanoma.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="800~836" text="TAK1 inhibition by (5Z)-7-Oxozeaenol" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="838~856" text="deletion of MAP3K7" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="864~892" text="expression of  inactive TAK1" perturbingaction="other" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1138~1170" text="TAK1 inhibitor (5Z)-7-Oxozeaenol" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="922~936" text="melanoma cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="957~967" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1037~1047" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1076~1085" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="912~921" text="sensitize" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="TAK1 inhibition by (5Z)-7-Oxozeaenol" effectID="E0" effectText="sensitize" contextID="C0" contextText="melanoma cells" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="deletion of MAP3K7" effectID="E0" effectText="sensitize" contextID="C0" contextText="melanoma cells" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN2" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="expression of  inactive TAK1" effectID="E0" effectText="sensitize" contextID="C0" contextText="melanoma cells" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>