<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Circular RNA circAGO2 drives cancer progression through facilitating 
HuR-repressed functions of AGO2-miRNA complexes.

Argonaute 2 (AGO2), the core component of microRNA (miRNA)-induced silencing 
complex, plays a compelling role in tumorigenesis and aggressiveness. However, 
the mechanisms regulating the functions of AGO2 in cancer still remain elusive. 
Herein, we indentify one intronic circular RNA (circRNA) generated from AGO2 
gene (circAGO2) as a novel regulator of AGO2-miRNA complexes and cancer 
progression. CircAGO2 is up-regulated in gastric cancer, colon cancer, prostate 
cancer, and neuroblastoma, and is associated with poor prognosis of patients. 
CircAGO2 promotes the growth, invasion, and metastasis of cancer cells in vitro 
and in vivo. Mechanistic studies reveal that circAGO2 physically interacts with 
human antigen R (HuR) protein to facilitate its activation and enrichment on the 
3'-untranslated region of target genes, resulting in reduction of AGO2 binding 
and repression of AGO2/miRNA-mediated gene silencing associated with cancer 
progression. Pre-clinically, administration of lentivirus-mediated short hairpin 
RNA targeting circAGO2 inhibits the expression of downstream target genes, and 
suppresses the tumorigenesis and aggressiveness of xenografts in nude mice. In 
addition, blocking the interaction between circAGO2 and HuR by cell-penetrating 
inhibitory peptide represses the tumorigenesis and aggressiveness of cancer 
cells. Taken together, these results indicate that oncogenic circAGO2 drives 
cancer progression through facilitating HuR-repressed functions of AGO2-miRNA 
complexes.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1118~1175" text="lentivirus-mediated short hairpin  RNA targeting circAGO2" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="728~740" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="741~749" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="755~762" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1284~1307" text="xenografts in nude mice" context="xenograft" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="700~708" text="invasion" phenotype="invasion" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="714~724" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1248~1261" text="tumorigenesis" phenotype="tumourigenesis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="679~687" text="promotes" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1233~1243" text="suppresses" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="lentivirus-mediated short hairpin  RNA targeting circAGO2" effectID="E1" effectText="suppresses" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="tumorigenesis" contextID="C3" contextText="xenografts in nude mice" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>