<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[SLC3A2/CD98hc, autophagy and tumor radioresistance: a link confirmed.

SLC3A2/CD98hc (solute carrier family 3 member 2) and its light chain subunits 
constitute the heterodimeric transmembrane complexes that mediate amino acid 
transport and regulate MTOR and macroautophagy/autophagy. Despite the proven 
tumorigenic role of SLC3A2 in a number of cancers including head and neck 
squamous cell carcinomas (HNSCC), the link between SLC3A2, autophagy regulation 
and tumor radioresistance remained elusive. In a recently published study we 
demonstrated that low levels of SLC3A2 and SLC7A5/LAT1 protein expression 
significantly correlate with good clinical prognosis in locally advanced HNSCC 
treated with primary radiochemotherapy. The SLC3A2-deficient HNSCC cells show a 
higher radiosensitivity and increased autophagy levels. We found that autophagy 
activation is a tumor survival strategy to overcome nutrient stress by lack of 
SLC3A2 and to withstand radiation-mediated cell damage. Inhibition of the 
autophagy activation in SLC3A2 knockout HNSCC cells by knockdown of ATG5 
expression or treatment with bafilomycin A1 results in radiosensitivity. 
Consequently, the expression levels of ATG5 correlates with overall survival in 
HNSCC patients, and autophagy inhibition in combination with SLC3A2-targeted 
therapy can be a promising strategy for HNSCC radiosensitization. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="739~755" text="SLC3A2-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1036~1051" text="SLC3A2 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1067~1084" text="knockdown of ATG5" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1052~1063" text="HNSCC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="756~767" text="HNSCC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="814~823" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="804~813" text="increased" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="SLC3A2-deficient" contextID="C2" contextText="HNSCC cells" effectID="E0" effectText="increased" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>