<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[CASP9 (caspase 9) is essential for autophagosome maturation through regulation 
of mitochondrial homeostasis.

CASP9 (caspase 9) is a well-known initiator caspase which triggers intrinsic 
apoptosis. Recent studies also suggest various non-apoptotic roles of CASP9, 
including macroautophagy/autophagy regulation. However, the involvement of CASP9 
in autophagy and its molecular mechanisms are not well understood. Here we 
report the non-apoptotic function of CASP9 in positive regulation of autophagy 
through maintenance of mitochondrial homeostasis. Growth factor or amino acid 
deprivation-induced autophagy activated CASP9, but without apoptotic features. 
Pharmacological inhibition or genetic ablation of CASP9 decreased autophagy 
flux, while ectopic expression of CASP9 rescued autophagy defects. In CASP9 
knockout (KO) cells, initiation and elongation of phagophore membranes were 
normal, but sealing of the membranes and autophagosome maturation were impaired, 
and the lifetime of autophagosomes was prolonged. Ablation of CASP9 caused an 
accumulation of inactive ATG3 and decreased lipidation of the Atg8-family 
members, most severely that of GABARAPL1. Moreover, it resulted in abnormal 
mitochondrial morphology with depolarization of the membrane potential, reduced 
reactive oxygen species production, and aberrant accumulation of mitochondrial 
fusion-fission proteins. CASP9 expression or exogenously added H2O2 in the CASP9 
KO cells corrected the ATG3 level and lipidation status of Atg8-family members, 
and restored autophagy flux. Of note, only CASP9 expression but not H2O2 rescued 
mitochondrial defects, revealing regulation of mitochondrial homeostasis by 
CASP9. Our findings suggest a new regulatory link between mitochondria and 
autophagy through CASP9 activity, especially for the proper operation of the 
Atg8-family conjugation system and autophagosome closure and maturation.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="694~719" text="genetic ablation of CASP9" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="753~780" text="ectopic expression of CASP9" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="811~831" text="CASP9  knockout (KO)" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1027~1044" text="Ablation of CASP9" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1394~1410" text="CASP9 expression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P5" spans="1444~1453" text="CASP9  KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P6" spans="1575~1591" text="CASP9 expression" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="832~837" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1454~1459" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="604~613" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="730~739" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="789~798" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1545~1559" text="autophagy flux" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="596~603" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="720~729" text="decreased" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="781~788" text="rescued" effect="rescues" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1536~1544" text="restored" effect="rescues" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P4" perturbing_actionText="CASP9 expression" contextID="C1" contextText="cells" effectID="E3" effectText="restored" phenotypeID="PH3" phenotypeText="autophagy flux" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>