<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Urolithin A suppresses high glucose-induced neuronal amyloidogenesis by 
modulating TGM2-dependent ER-mitochondria contacts and calcium homeostasis.

Hyperglycemia in diabetes mellitus (DM) patients is a causative factor for 
amyloidogenesis and induces neuropathological changes, such as impaired neuronal 
integrity, neurodegeneration, and cognitive impairment. Regulation of 
mitochondrial calcium influx from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) is considered a 
promising strategy for the prevention of mitochondrial ROS (mtROS) accumulation 
that occurs in the Alzheimer's disease (AD)-associated pathogenesis in DM 
patients. Among the metabolites of ellagitannins that are produced in the gut 
microbiome, urolithin A has received an increasing amount of attention as a 
novel candidate with anti-oxidative and neuroprotective effects in AD. Here, we 
investigated the effect of urolithin A on high glucose-induced amyloidogenesis 
caused by mitochondrial calcium dysregulation and mtROS accumulation resulting 
in neuronal degeneration. We also identified the mechanism related to 
mitochondria-associated ER membrane (MAM) formation. We found that urolithin 
A-lowered mitochondrial calcium influx significantly alleviated high 
glucose-induced mtROS accumulation and expression of amyloid beta (Aβ)-producing 
enzymes, such as amyloid precursor protein (APP) and β-secretase-1 (BACE1), as 
well as Aβ production. Urolithin A injections in a streptozotocin (STZ)-induced 
diabetic mouse model alleviated APP and BACE1 expressions, Tau phosphorylation, 
Aβ deposition, and cognitive impairment. In addition, high glucose stimulated 
MAM formation and transglutaminase type 2 (TGM2) expression. We first discovered 
that urolithin A significantly reduced high glucose-induced TGM2 expression. In 
addition, disruption of the AIP-AhR complex was involved in urolithin A-mediated 
suppression of high glucose-induced TGM2 expression. Markedly, TGM2 silencing 
inhibited inositol 1, 4, 5-trisphosphate receptor type 
1 (IP3R1)-voltage-dependent anion-selective channel protein 1 (VDAC1) 
interactions and prevented high glucose-induced mitochondrial calcium influx and 
mtROS accumulation. We also found that urolithin A or TGM2 silencing prevented 
Aβ-induced mitochondrial calcium influx, mtROS accumulation, Tau 
phosphorylation, and cell death in neuronal cells. In conclusion, we suggest 
that urolithin A is a promising candidate for the development of therapies to 
prevent DM-associated AD pathogenesis by reducing TGM2-dependent MAM formation 
and maintaining mitochondrial calcium and ROS homeostasis.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1944~1958" text="TGM2 silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="2223~2237" text="TGM2 silencing" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1476~1496" text="diabetic mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="2350~2364" text="neuronal cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="2336~2346" text="cell death" phenotype="cell death" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="2238~2247" text="prevented" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="TGM2 silencing" effectID="E0" effectText="prevented" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="cell death" contextID="C2" contextText="neuronal cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>