<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ATG12 deficiency leads to tumor cell oncosis owing to diminished mitochondrial 
biogenesis and reduced cellular bioenergetics.

In contrast to the "Warburg effect" or aerobic glycolysis earlier generalized as 
a phenomenon in cancer cells, more and more recent evidence indicates that 
functional mitochondria are pivotal for ensuring the energy supply of cancer 
cells. Here, we report that cancer cells with reduced autophagy-related protein 
12 (ATG12) expression undergo an oncotic cell death, a phenotype distinct from 
that seen in ATG5-deficient cells described before. In addition, using 
untargeted metabolomics with ATG12-deficient cancer cells, we observed a global 
reduction in cellular bioenergetic pathways, such as β-oxidation (FAO), 
glycolysis, and tricarboxylic acid cycle activity, as well as a decrease in 
mitochondrial respiration as monitored with Seahorse experiments. Analyzing the 
biogenesis of mitochondria by quantifying mitochondrial DNA content together 
with several mitochondrion-localizing proteins indicated a reduction in 
mitochondrial biogenesis in ATG12-deficient cancer cells, which also showed 
reduced hexokinase II expression and the upregulation of uncoupling protein 2. 
ATG12, which we observed in normal cells to be partially localized in 
mitochondria, is upregulated in multiple types of solid tumors in comparison 
with normal tissues. Strikingly, mouse xenografts of ATG12-deficient cells grew 
significantly slower as compared with vector control cells. Collectively, our 
work has revealed a previously unreported role for ATG12 in regulating 
mitochondrial biogenesis and cellular energy metabolism and points up an 
essential role for mitochondria as a failsafe mechanism in the growth and 
survival of glycolysis-dependent cancer cells. Inducing oncosis by imposing an 
ATG12 deficiency in solid tumors might represent an anticancer therapy 
preferable to conventional caspase-dependent apoptosis that often leads to 
undesirable consequences, such as incomplete cancer cell killing and a silencing 
of the host immune system.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="626~641" text="ATG12-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1088~1103" text="ATG12-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1419~1434" text="ATG12-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="410~466" text="reduced autophagy-related protein  12 (ATG12) expression" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="642~654" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1104~1116" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1399~1415" text="mouse xenografts" context="xenograft" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1435~1440" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1500~1505" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="392~404" text="cancer cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="478~496" text="oncotic cell death" phenotype="oncosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="467~474" text="undergo" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P3" perturbing_actionText="reduced autophagy-related protein  12 (ATG12) expression" contextID="C5" contextText="cancer cells" effectID="E0" effectText="undergo" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="oncotic cell death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>