<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Nuclear miR-30b-5p suppresses TFEB-mediated lysosomal biogenesis and autophagy.

Lysosome is a crucial organelle in charge of degrading proteins and damaged 
organelles to maintain cellular homeostasis. Transcription factor EB (TFEB) is 
the master transcription factor regulating lysosomal biogenesis and autophagy. 
Under external stimuli such as starvation, dephosphorylated TFEB transports into 
the nucleus to specifically recognize and bind to the coordinated lysosomal 
expression and regulation (CLEAR) elements at the promotors of autophagy and 
lysosomal biogenesis-related genes. The function of TFEB in the nucleus is fine 
regulated but the molecular mechanism is not fully elucidated. In this study, we 
discovered that miR-30b-5p, a small RNA which is known to regulate a series of 
genes through posttranscriptional regulation in the cytoplasm, was translocated 
into the nucleus, bound to the CLEAR elements, suppressed the transcription of 
TFEB-dependent downstream genes, and further inhibited the lysosomal biogenesis 
and the autophagic flux; meanwhile, knocking out the endogenous miR-30b-5p by 
CRISPR/Cas9 technique significantly increased the TFEB-mediated transactivation, 
resulting in the increased expression of autophagy and lysosomal 
biogenesis-related genes. Overexpressing miR-30b-5p in mice livers showed a 
decrease in lysosomal biogenesis and autophagy. These in vitro and in vivo data 
indicate that miR-30b-5p may inhibit the TFEB-dependent transactivation by 
binding to the CLEAR elements in the nucleus to regulate the lysosomal 
biogenesis and autophagy. This novel mechanism of nuclear miRNA regulating gene 
transcription is conducive to further elucidating the roles of miRNAs in the 
lysosomal physiological functions and helps to understand the pathogenesis of 
abnormal autophagy-related diseases.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1076~1140" text="knocking out the endogenous miR-30b-5p by  CRISPR/Cas9 technique" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1293~1318" text="Overexpressing miR-30b-5p" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1322~1333" text="mice livers" context="tissue/organ" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1381~1390" text="autophagy" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1344~1352" text="decrease" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Overexpressing miR-30b-5p" contextID="C0" contextText="mice livers" effectID="E0" effectText="decrease" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="autophagy" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>