<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[ARID1A prevents squamous cell carcinoma initiation and chemoresistance by 
antagonizing pRb/E2F1/c-Myc-mediated cancer stemness.

Squamous cell carcinoma (SCC) is defined as a category of aggressive 
malignancies arising from the squamous epithelium of various organs. Resistance 
to chemotherapies is a common feature of SCCs, which leads to a poor prognosis 
among SCC patients. Recently, studies have illustrated the essential tumor 
suppressive role of ARID1A in several cancer types, but its role in SCCs remains 
unclear. Cancer stemness has been recognized as a main reason for tumorigenesis 
and is commonly correlated with chemoresistance, yet the relationship between 
ARID1A and cancer stemness remains unknown. In this study, we showed that Arid1a 
conditional knockout mice had a high incidence of SCCs occurring in the tongue 
and esophagus. ARID1A depletion promoted tumor initiation and cancer stemness in 
human SCC cells. Mechanistic studies revealed that ARID1A blocked the 
interaction between cyclin-dependent kinases (CDKs) and retinoblastoma protein 
(Rb), reducing the phosphorylation of Rb. Dephosphorylated Rb suppressed E2F1 
activity and then suppressed cancer stemness by inactivating c-Myc. Furthermore, 
we showed that ARID1A depletion significantly increased the chemoresistance of 
SCC and that a CDK inhibitor exhibited a favorable effect on rescuing the 
chemoresistance caused by ARID1A loss. Collectively, our study showed that 
ARID1A inhibits the cancer stemness of SCCs by competing with CDKs to bind with 
Rb to inhibit the E2F1/c-Myc pathway.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="753~781" text="Arid1a  conditional knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="856~872" text="ARID1A depletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1250~1266" text="ARID1A depletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="1416~1427" text="ARID1A loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="782~786" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="811~815" text="SCCs" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="833~839" text="tongue" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="845~854" text="esophagus" context="tissue/organ" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="923~938" text="human SCC cells" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1315~1318" text="SCC" context="neoplasm" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="882~898" text="tumor initiation" phenotype="tumour initiation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="873~881" text="promoted" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="ARID1A depletion" contextID="C4" contextText="human SCC cells" effectID="E0" effectText="promoted" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="tumor initiation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>