<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Roles of mTORC1 and mTORC2 in controlling γδ T1 and γδ T17 differentiation and 
function.

The metabolism-controlled differentiation of αβ T cells has been well 
documented; however, the role of a metabolism program in γδ T cell 
differentiation and function has not been clarified. Here, using CD2-cre; mTORC1 
Raptor-f/f, and mTORC2 Rictor-f/f mice (KO mice), we found that mTORC1, but not 
mTORC2, was required for the proliferation and survival of peripheral γδ T 
cells, especially Vγ4 γδ T cells. Moreover, mTORC1 was essential for both γδ T1 
and γδ Τ17 differentiation, whereas mTORC2 was required for γδ T17, but not for 
γδ Τ1, differentiation. We further studied the underlying molecular mechanisms 
and found that depletion of mTORC1 resulted in the increased expression of 
SOCS1, which in turn suppressed the key transcription factor Eomes, 
consequentially reducing IFN-γ production. Whereas the reduced glycolysis 
resulted in impaired γδ Τ17 differentiation in Raptor KO γδ T cells. In 
contrast, mTORC2 potentiated γδ Τ17 induction by suppressing mitochondrial ROS 
(mitoROS) production. Consistent with their cytokine production profiles, the 
Raptor KO γδ T cells lost their anti-tumor function both in vitro and in vivo, 
whereas both Raptor and Rictor KO mice were resistant to imiquimod (IMQ)-induced 
psoriasis-like skin pathogenesis. In summary, we identified previously unknown 
functions of mTORC1 and mTORC2 in γδ T cell differentiation and clarified their 
divergent roles in mediating the activity of γδ T cells in tumors and 
autoimmunity.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="726~745" text="depletion of mTORC1" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="978~987" text="Raptor KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1163~1172" text="Raptor KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P4" spans="1256~1276" text="Raptor and Rictor KO" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="988~998" text="γδ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1173~1183" text="γδ T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1220~1228" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1233~1240" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1277~1281" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="952~974" text="γδ Τ17 differentiation" phenotype="differentiation" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="943~951" text="impaired" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Raptor KO" contextID="C1" contextText="γδ T cells" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="γδ Τ17 differentiation" effectID="E0" effectText="impaired" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>