<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Loss of ferroportin induces memory impairment by promoting ferroptosis in 
Alzheimer's disease.

Iron homeostasis disturbance has been implicated in Alzheimer's disease (AD), 
and excess iron exacerbates oxidative damage and cognitive defects. Ferroptosis 
is a nonapoptotic form of cell death dependent upon intracellular iron. However, 
the involvement of ferroptosis in the pathogenesis of AD remains elusive. Here, 
we report that ferroportin1 (Fpn), the only identified mammalian nonheme iron 
exporter, was downregulated in the brains of APPswe/PS1dE9 mice as an 
Alzheimer's mouse model and Alzheimer's patients. Genetic deletion of Fpn in 
principal neurons of the neocortex and hippocampus by breeding Fpnfl/fl mice 
with NEX-Cre mice led to AD-like hippocampal atrophy and memory deficits. 
Interestingly, the canonical morphological and molecular characteristics of 
ferroptosis were observed in both Fpnfl/fl/NEXcre and AD mice. Gene set 
enrichment analysis (GSEA) of ferroptosis-related RNA-seq data showed that the 
differentially expressed genes were highly enriched in gene sets associated with 
AD. Furthermore, administration of specific inhibitors of ferroptosis 
effectively reduced the neuronal death and memory impairments induced by Aβ 
aggregation in vitro and in vivo. In addition, restoring Fpn ameliorated 
ferroptosis and memory impairment in APPswe/PS1dE9 mice. Our study demonstrates 
the critical role of Fpn and ferroptosis in the progression of AD, thus provides 
promising therapeutic approaches for this disease.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="620~643" text="Genetic deletion of Fpn" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="912~927" text="Fpnfl/fl/NEXcre" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="1308~1321" text="restoring Fpn" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="648~698" text="principal neurons of the neocortex and hippocampus" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="935~939" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1273~1281" text="in vitro" context="in vitro" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1286~1293" text="in vivo" context="in vivo" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1386~1390" text="mice" context="organism" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="878~889" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1335~1346" text="ferroptosis" phenotype="ferroptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1322~1333" text="ameliorated" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P2" perturbing_actionText="restoring Fpn" effectID="E1" effectText="ameliorated" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="ferroptosis" contextID="C4" contextText="mice" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>