<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Upregulation of microRNA-532 enhances cardiomyocyte apoptosis in the diabetic 
heart.

Type 2 diabetes has a strong association with the development of cardiovascular 
disease, which is grouped as diabetic heart disease (DHD). DHD is associated 
with the progressive loss of cardiovascular cells through the alteration of 
molecular signalling pathways associated with cell death. In this study, we 
sought to determine whether diabetes induces dysregulation of miR-532 and if 
this is associated with accentuated apoptosis. RT-PCR analysis showed a 
significant increase in miR-532 expression in the right atrial appendage tissue 
of type 2 diabetic patients undergoing coronary artery bypass graft surgery. 
This was associated with marked downregulation of its anti-apoptotic target 
protein apoptosis repressor with caspase recruitment domain (ARC) and increased 
TUNEL positive cardiomyocytes. Further analysis showed a positive correlation 
between apoptosis and miR-532 levels. Time-course experiments in a mouse model 
of type 2 diabetes showed that diabetes-induced activation of miR-532 occurs in 
the later stage of the disease. Importantly, the upregulation of miR-532 
preceded the activation of pro-apoptotic caspase-3/7 activity. Finally, 
inhibition of miR-532 activity in high glucose cultured human cardiomyocytes 
prevented the downregulation of ARC and attenuated apoptotic cell death. 
Diabetes induced activation of miR-532 plays a critical role in accelerating 
cardiomyocytes apoptosis. Therefore, miR-532 may serve as a promising 
therapeutic agent to overcome the diabetes-induced loss of cardiomyocytes.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1255~1285" text="inhibition of miR-532 activity" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1014~1025" text="mouse model" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1311~1331" text="human cardiomyocytes" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1384~1404" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1373~1383" text="attenuated" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="inhibition of miR-532 activity" contextID="C1" contextText="human cardiomyocytes" effectID="E0" effectText="attenuated" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="apoptotic cell death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>