<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[MicroRNA-663 antagonizes apoptosis antagonizing transcription factor to induce 
apoptosis in epithelial cells.

MicroRNAs are small functional RNAs that modulate various biological processes 
in cells by interfering with gene translation. We have previously demonstrated 
that certain miRNAs play a crucial role in the innate immune responses of human 
oral epithelial cells to Porphyromonas gingivalis. While addressing the 
mechanisms of P. gingivalis induced apoptosis in these cells, we discovered that 
certain miRNAs are upregulated upon stimulation with live bacteria. These 
upregulated miRNAs include hsa-miR-584, hsa-miR-572, hsa-miR-210, hsa-miR-492, 
hsa-miR-623 and hsa-miR-663. Further analysis revealed an unexpected role for 
hsa-miR-663 (miR-663). To further evaluate miR-663 function, we overexpressed 
miR-663 in epithelial cells which resulted in cellular apoptosis. The 
bioinformatics analysis of the miR-663 target prediction, revealed a strong 
binding affinity to a 3' UTR region of Apoptosis Antagonizing Transcription 
Factor (AATF) mRNA. To demonstrate the binding of miR-663 to AATF mRNA, the 
putative miR-663 target site within the 3'-UTR region of AATF was cloned in 
luciferase vector and transfected to HEK293T cells. Luminescence data showed the 
downregulation of luciferase activity in cells that had the full length target 
region of the putative binding site, confirming that AATF is one of the targets 
for miR-663. This prompted us to further evaluate its role in a cancer cell line 
(MCF-7) to determine miR-663s' apoptotic function. The overexpression of miR-663 
led to a significant increase in apoptosis of MCF-7 cells. Taken together, 
miR-663 may function as an 'apoptomiR' by inhibiting the anti-apoptotic gene 
AATF to induce apoptosis. These findings could have therapeutic implications for 
epithelial cell targeting in cancer therapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="806~828" text="overexpressed  miR-663" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1580~1605" text="overexpression of miR-663" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="481~486" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="832~848" text="epithelial cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1237~1250" text="HEK293T cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="1323~1328" text="cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C4" spans="1507~1532" text="cancer cell line  (MCF-7)" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="1653~1664" text="MCF-7 cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="462~471" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="876~885" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1640~1649" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="454~461" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="855~866" text="resulted in" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1628~1636" text="increase" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="overexpressed  miR-663" contextID="C1" contextText="epithelial cells" effectID="E1" effectText="resulted in" phenotypeID="PH1" phenotypeText="apoptosis" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN1" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="overexpression of miR-663" effectID="E2" effectText="increase" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="apoptosis" contextID="C5" contextText="MCF-7 cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>