<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[M1 macrophage dependent-p53 regulates the intracellular survival of 
mycobacteria.

Tumor suppressor p53 is not only affects immune responses but also contributes 
to antibacterial activity. However, its bactericidal function during 
mycobacterial infection remains unclear. In this study, we found that the 
p53-deficient macrophages failed to control Mycobacterium tuberculosis (Mtb), 
manifested as a lower apoptotic cell death rate and enhanced intracellular 
survival. The expression levels of p53 during Mtb infection were stronger in M1 
macrophages than in M2 macrophages. The TLR2/JNK signaling pathway plays an 
essential role in the modulation of M1 macrophage polarization upon Mtb 
infection. It facilitates p53-mediated apoptosis through the production of 
reactive oxygen species, nitric oxide and inflammatory cytokines in Mtb-infected 
M1 macrophages. In addition, nutlin-3 effectively abrogated the intracellular 
survival of mycobacteria in both TB patients and healthy controls after H37Ra 
infection for 24 h, indicating that the enhancement of p53 production 
effectively suppressed the intracellular survival of Mtb in hosts. These results 
suggest that p53 can be a new therapeutic target for TB therapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="309~322" text="p53-deficient" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="323~334" text="macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="541~556" text="M1  macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C3" spans="565~579" text="M2 macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C5" spans="658~671" text="M1 macrophage" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C6" spans="853~867" text="M1 macrophages" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C7" spans="965~976" text="TB patients" context="patient" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="410~430" text="apoptotic cell death" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="734~743" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="404~409" text="lower" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="709~720" text="facilitates" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="725~733" text="mediated" effect="regulates" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="p53-deficient" contextID="C0" contextText="macrophages" effectID="E0" effectText="lower" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="apoptotic cell death" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>