<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[CNOT3 contributes to cisplatin resistance in lung cancer through inhibiting 
RIPK3 expression.

Chemotherapeutic resistance always results in poor clinical outcomes of cancer 
patients and its intricate mechanisms are large obstacles in overcoming drug 
resistance. CCR4-NOT transcription complex subunit 3 (CNOT3), a 
post-translational regulator, is suggested to be involved in cancer development 
and progression. However, its role in chemotherapeutic resistance is not well 
understood. In this study, after screening the CNOT3 mRNA in a cancer microarray 
database called Oncomine and examining the expression levels of CNOT3 mRNA in 
normal tissues and lung cancer tissues, we found that CNOT3 was up-regulated in 
lung cancer tissues. Besides, its high-expression was associated with poor 
prognosis of lung cancer patients. We also found higher expression level of 
CNOT3 and lower expression level of receptor-interacting protein kinase 3 
(RIPK3) in cisplatin-resistant A549 (A549/DDP) cells, and knocking down CNOT3 
expression could sensitize A549/DDP cells to cisplatin-induced apoptosis. We 
demonstrated that CNOT3 depletion up-regulated the expression level of RIPK3 and 
the enhanced apoptosis was mediated by the elevated RIPK3 to further trigger 
Caspase 8 activation. Taken together, our results reveal a role of CNOT3 in 
cisplatin resistance of lung cancer and provide a potential target for lung 
cancer therapy.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1007~1026" text="knocking down CNOT3" perturbingaction="rnai/knockdown" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="1124~1139" text="CNOT3 depletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="1055~1069" text="A549/DDP cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="1091~1100" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1201~1210" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="1045~1054" text="sensitize" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1083~1090" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1192~1200" text="enhanced" effect="positive" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="knocking down CNOT3" effectID="E0" effectText="sensitize" contextID="C0" contextText="A549/DDP cells" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="apoptosis" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>