<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Overexpression of augmenter of liver regeneration (ALR) mitigates the effect of 
H(2)O(2)-induced endoplasmic reticulum stress in renal tubule epithelial cells.

Ischemia/reperfusion is a major cause of acute kidney injury and can induce 
apoptosis in renal epithelial tubule (HK-2) cells. Accumulating evidence 
indicates that endoplasmic reticulum (ER) stress is a major contributor to 
apoptosis in acute kidney injury. We previously reported that augmenter of liver 
regeneration (ALR) functions as an anti-apoptotic factor in H2O2-treated HK-2 
cells although the precise mechanism underlying this action remains unclear. In 
the present study, we investigate the role of ALR in H2O2-induced ER 
stress-mediated apoptosis. We overexpressed ALR and established a H2O2-induced 
ER stress model in HK-2 cells. Overexpression of ALR reduced the level of 
reactive oxygen species and the rate of apoptosis in H2O2-treated HK-2 cells. 
Using confocal microscopy and western blot, we observed that ALR colocalized 
with the ER and mitochondria compartment. Moreover, ALR suppressed ER stress by 
maintaining the morphology of the ER and reducing the levels of the ER-related 
proteins, glucose-regulated protein 78 (GRP78), phospho-protein kinase-like ER 
kinase (p-PERK), phospho-eukaryotic initiation factor 2α (p-eIF2α) and 
C/EBP-homologous protein (CHOP) significantly (p < 0.05). Mechanistically, ALR 
promoted Bcl-2 expression and suppressed Bax and cleaved-caspase-3 expression 
significantly during ER-stress induced apoptosis (p < 0.05). Furthermore, ALR 
attenuated calcium release from the ER, and transfer to mitochondria, under ER 
stress. To conclude, ALR alleviates H2O2-induced ER stress-mediated apoptosis in 
HK-2 cells by suppressing ER stress response and by maintaining calcium 
homeostasis. Consequently, ALR may protect renal tubule epithelial cells from 
ischemia/reperfusion induced acute kidney injury.
]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="731~748" text="overexpressed ALR" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="812~833" text="Overexpression of ALR" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="800~810" text="HK-2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="922~932" text="HK-2 cells" context="cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="1726~1736" text="HK-2 cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="896~905" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="1524~1533" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1712~1721" text="apoptosis" phenotype="apoptosis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="834~841" text="reduced" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1516~1523" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="1685~1692" text="induced" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E3" spans="1669~1679" text="alleviates" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E4" spans="1703~1711" text="mediated" effect="regulates" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="Overexpression of ALR" effectID="E0" effectText="reduced" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="apoptosis" contextID="C1" contextText="HK-2 cells" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>