<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Senescence Reprogramming by TIMP1 Deficiency Promotes Prostate Cancer 
Metastasis.

Metastases account for most cancer-related deaths, yet the mechanisms underlying 
metastatic spread remain poorly understood. Recent evidence demonstrates that 
senescent cells, while initially restricting tumorigenesis, can induce tumor 
progression. Here, we identify the metalloproteinase inhibitor TIMP1 as a 
molecular switch that determines the effects of senescence in prostate cancer. 
Senescence driven either by PTEN deficiency or chemotherapy limits the 
progression of prostate cancer in mice. TIMP1 deletion allows senescence to 
promote metastasis, and elimination of senescent cells with a senolytic BCL-2 
inhibitor impairs metastasis. Mechanistically, TIMP1 loss reprograms the 
senescence-associated secretory phenotype (SASP) of senescent tumor cells 
through activation of matrix metalloproteinases (MMPs). Loss of PTEN and TIMP1 
in prostate cancer is frequent and correlates with resistance to docetaxel and 
worst clinical outcomes in patients treated in an adjuvant setting. Altogether, 
these findings provide insights into the dual roles of tumor-associated 
senescence and can potentially impact the treatment of prostate cancer.]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="506~521" text="PTEN deficiency" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="590~604" text="TIMP1 deletion" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="699~715" text="BCL-2  inhibitor" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P3" spans="753~763" text="TIMP1 loss" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="565~580" text="prostate cancer" context="neoplasm" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="584~588" text="mice" context="organism" />
<CONTEXT id="C2" spans="832~853" text="senescent tumor cells" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="478~488" text="Senescence" phenotype="senescence" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="635~645" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="724~734" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="489~495" text="driven" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="627~634" text="promote" effect="positive" />
<EFFECT id="E2" spans="716~723" text="impairs" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="PTEN deficiency" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="Senescence" effectID="E0" effectText="driven" contextID="C1" contextText="mice" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>