<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[TRAF6 inhibits colorectal cancer metastasis through regulating selective 
autophagic CTNNB1/β-catenin degradation and is targeted for GSK3B/GSK3β-mediated 
phosphorylation and degradation.

Aberrant CTNNB1 signaling is one of the fundamental processes in cancers, 
especially colorectal cancer (CRC). Here, we reported that TRAF6, an E3 
ubiquitin ligase important for inflammatory signaling, inhibited 
epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT) and CRC metastasis through driving a 
selective autophagic CTNNB1 degradation machinery. Mechanistically, TRAF6 
interacted with MAP1LC3B/LC3B through its LC3-interacting region 'YxxL' and 
catalyzed K63-linked polyubiquitination of LC3B. The K63-linked ubiquitination 
of LC3B promoted the formation of the LC3B-ATG7 complex and was critical to the 
subsequent recognition of CTNNB1 by LC3B for the selective autophagic 
degradation. However, TRAF6 was phosphorylated at Thr266 by GSK3B in most 
clinical CRC, which triggered K48-linked polyubiquitination and degradation of 
TRAF6 and thereby attenuated its inhibitory activity towards the 
autophagy-dependent CTNNB1 signaling. Clinically, decreased expression of TRAF6 
was associated with elevated GSK3B protein levels and activity and reduced 
overall survival in CRC patients. Pharmacological inhibition of GSK3B activity 
stabilized the TRAF6 protein, promoted CTNNB1 degradation, and effectively 
suppressed EMT and CRC metastasis. Thus, targeting TRAF6 and its pathway may be 
meaningful for treating advanced CRC. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="1278~1322" text="Pharmacological inhibition of GSK3B activity" perturbingaction="pharmacological inhibition" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="448~451" text="CRC" context="transformed cells" />
<CONTEXT id="C1" spans="1419~1422" text="CRC" context="transformed cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="404~443" text="epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH1" spans="452~462" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH2" spans="1411~1414" text="EMT" phenotype="epithelial-mesenchymal transition" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH3" spans="1423~1433" text="metastasis" phenotype="metastasis" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="393~402" text="inhibited" effect="negative" />
<EFFECT id="E1" spans="1400~1410" text="suppressed" effect="negative" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" perturbing_actionID="P0" perturbing_actionText="Pharmacological inhibition of GSK3B activity" effectID="E1" effectText="suppressed" phenotypeID="PH2" phenotypeText="EMT" contextID="C1" contextText="CRC" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>