<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>

<Genomics_ConceptTask>
<TEXT><![CDATA[Neuropathy-causing mutations in HSPB1 impair autophagy by disturbing the 
formation of SQSTM1/p62 bodies.

HSPB1 (heat shock protein family B [small] member 1) is a ubiquitously expressed 
molecular chaperone. Most mutations in HSPB1 cause axonal Charcot-Marie-Tooth 
neuropathy and/or distal hereditary motor neuropathy. In this study we show that 
mutations in HSPB1 lead to impairment of macroautophagic/autophagic flux. In 
HSPB1 knockout cells, we demonstrate that HSPB1 is necessary for autophagosome 
formation, which was rescued upon re-expression of HSPB1. Employing a label-free 
LC-MS/MS analysis on the various HSPB1 variants (wild type and mutants), we 
identified autophagy-specific interactors. We reveal that the wild-type HSPB1 
protein binds to the autophagy receptor SQSTM1/p62 and that the PB1 domain of 
SQSTM1 is essential for this interaction. Mutations in HSPB1 lead to a decrease 
in the formation of SQSTM1/p62 bodies, and subsequent impairment of phagophore 
formation, suggesting a regulatory role for HSPB1 in autophagy via interaction 
with SQSTM1. Remarkably, autophagy deficits could also be confirmed in 
patient-derived motor neurons thereby indicating that the impairment of 
autophagy might be one of the pathomechanisms by which mutations in HSPB1 lead 
to peripheral neuropathy. ]]></TEXT>
<TAGS>
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P0" spans="428~442" text="HSPB1 knockout" perturbingaction="gene loss-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P1" spans="542~564" text="re-expression of HSPB1" perturbingaction="gene gain-of-function" />
<PERTURBING_ACTION id="P2" spans="867~885" text="Mutations in HSPB1" perturbingaction="other" />
<CONTEXT id="C0" spans="443~448" text="cells" context="cells" />
<PHENOTYPE id="PH0" spans="493~517" text="autophagosome  formation" phenotype="autophagy" />
<EFFECT id="E0" spans="529~536" text="rescued" effect="rescues" />
<ENTITY_LINKING id="EN0" contextID="C0" contextText="cells" effectID="E0" effectText="rescued" perturbing_actionID="P1" perturbing_actionText="re-expression of HSPB1" phenotypeID="PH0" phenotypeText="autophagosome  formation" />
</TAGS>
</Genomics_ConceptTask>